Welcome back, in this second half of the lecture we'll continue with our overview
of the structure of a compiler. Recall that a compiler has five major phases,
lexical analysis, parsing, semantic analysis, optimization, and code
generation. And now we're going to briefly talk about each one, and we're going to
explain how a compiler understands these with an analogy to how humans understand
English. The first step at understanding a program, both for a compiler and for a
human, is to understand the words. Now, humans can look at this example sentence
and immediately recognize that there are four words 'this is a' and 'sentence. And
this is so automatic that you don't even think about it but there is [inaudible]
real computation going on here. You have to recognize the separators, namely the
blanks. And the punctuation, things like the periods, and also clues like capital
letters. And these help you to divide up this group of letters into, a bunch of
words that you can understand. And just to emphasize that this is not completely
trivial, let's take a look at this sentence. And you can read this, but it
takes a little bit of time Because I've put the separators in, in odd places. So
you can see the word is, the word this, the word a, and the word sentence. But
again this isn't something that comes to you immediately. You actually have to do
some work to see where the divisions lie Because they're not given to you in the
way that you're used to. The goal of lexical analysis, then, is to divide the
program text into its words, or what we call in compiler speak, the tokens. So,
here's an, an example piece of program text now, instead of a piece of English
text, and let's walk through this and identify the tokens. So, there's some
obvious ones that are keywords, like if, and then. >> And else that we want to
identify. And then there are variable names, things like X, and Y, and Z.
There's also constants, things like number one, and the number two. And then there
are some operators, double equals is one, and the assignment operator is another.
And here's already an interesting question. How do we know that double
equals is not two individual equals signs? How do we know that we want this? To be a
double equal so we want, and not two single equals. Well, we don't know right
now but we'll talk about that. >> In the lecture on how we implement Lexico
analysis. But we're not done with all the tokens in this example either, there's a
few more. The semi colons, the punctuation are also tokens, and then the separators
are also tokens, so here's a blank, that's a token, here's another blank, that's
another token, and then there are lots of blanks here that serve to separate things
like the keywords and the variable names and other symbols from each other. And
those are the tokens of this example. So for humans, once the words are understood,
the next step is to understand the structure of the sentence, and this is
called parsing. And as we all learned in elementary school, this means diagramming
sentences, and these diagrams are trees, and it's a very simple procedure. Let's
look at this example. This line is a longer sentence. The first step in parsing
is to identify the role of each word in the sentence. So we have things like nouns
and verbs and adjectives. But then, the actual work of parsing is to group these
words together into higher level constructs. So for example, this
particular sentence consists of a subject, a verb, and an object, okay? And that
actually forms an entire sentence. So, right here we have the root of the tree
called a sentence, and that's broken down into constituent parts. The high level
structure, as we said, is subject verb to object. And then the subject is more
complicated, as is the object. And this is an example of parsing an English sentence.
The analogy between parsing English text and parsing program text is very strong.
In fact, they're exactly the same thing. So here's our little example piece of code
again, so let's work through parsing it. So, clearly, this is an if then else
statement, and so, the root of our diagram, of our parse tree, is gonna be if
then else. [inaudible] Nothing else consists of three parts. There's a
predicate, a then statement, and an L statement. And now let?s look at the
predicate which consists of three pieces. There's a variable, a comparison operator
and another variable and together those form a relation. So the comparison between
two things is one of the things you can have as a valid predicate. Similarly, the
then statement consists of an assignment where Z gets one, and the else statement also
has the form of an assignment, Z gets two. And to, all together this is a parse tree,
of the if-then-else, showing its structure, breaking it up into its
constituent pieces. Now, once we've understood the sentence structure, the
next step is to try to understand the meaning, of what has been written. And,
this is hard. So, actually we don't know how this works for humans still. We don't
understand, what happens after lexical analysis and parsing. We do know that
people do lexical analysis and parsing in much the same way, that compilers
lexically analyze and parse programs. But frankly, understanding meaning is
something that is simply too hard for compilers. So, the first important thing
to understand about, semantic analysis is that compilers can only do very limited
kinds of semantic analysis. And in particular the kinds of things that
compilers generally do are try to catch inconsistencies. So, if the program is
somehow self inconsistent, [inaudible] compilers can often notice that and report
errors. But they don't really know what the program is supposed to do. As an
example of the kind of thing that we do in semantic analysis, again, using an analogy
in English, let's consider the following sentence. So, Jack said Jerry left his
assignment at home. And the question is, what, who does his, refer to here? It
could be that his refers to Jerry, in which case we would read, Jack said Jerry
left Jerry's assignment at home. Or it could refer to Jack. In which case, we
could read the sentence as, Jack said Jerry left Jack's assignment at home. And
without more information, we actually don't know which one. His is referring to,
whether it's Jack, or it's Jerry. And even worse, let's take a look at this sentence
down here. Jack said, Jack left his assignment at home. And the question is
how many people are actually involved in this sentence? It could be as many as
three, there could be two separate Jacks and his, could even refer to somebody
completely different. We don't know without seeing the rest of the story. That
surrounds this sentence, all the possibilities for his. But it could also
be as few as, only a single person. It could be that Jack and Jack and his are
all the same person in this sentence. And so this kind of ambiguity is a real
problem, in semantic analysis. And the analogy in programming languages is
variable bindings. So we would have variables, in this case, a variable called
Jack or maybe more than one variable called Jack. And a programming language is
going to have very strict rules to prevent the kind of ambiguities we had in the
English sentences on the previous slide. So you know, in this example. Question is
what value is printed by this output statement, and the answer is it's going to
print four because this use of the variable Jack binds to this definition
here. And the outer definition is hidden. So the outer definition is not active in
this scope because it is hidden by the inner definition and that is just a
standard rule of a lot of lexically scoped programming languages. Now the pilots
perform many semantic texts besides analyzing the variable bindings. And so
here's another example in English. So Jack looked her homework at home. And, under
the usual naming conventions, assuming that Jack is male, we know there's a type
mismatch between Jack and her. So we know that, whatever her is, it is not Jack.
And, and therefore we known that this sentence is talking about two different
people. And so this is, analogous to type checking. The fourth compiler phase,
optimization, doesn't have a very strong counterpart in everyday English usage but
it's a little bit like editing. And, in fact, it's a lot like what professional
editors do when they have to reduce the length of an article to get it down to
some word budget. So, for example, I have this phrase right here, but a little bit
like ending; and if I didn't like it, if I thought it was too long, I could replace
the middle four words, with two words. Akin to. So now it says, but akin to
editing, and that means exactly the same thing as the original phrase, but uses
fewer words. And the goal in program optimization Is to modify the program so
that it uses less of some resource. Maybe we want to use less time, we want the
program to run faster maybe we want it to use less space so that we can fit more
data in memory. For a handheld device we might be interested in reducing the amount
of power that it uses. If we have external communication we might be interested in
reducing the number of network messages or the number of database accesses. And
there's any number of resources that we might want to improve other program's use
of. So here's a simple example of the kinds of optimizations a program might do.
We can have a rule in our compiler that says X equals Y times zero, is the same as
X equals zero. And this seems like a real improvement, because instead of doing the
multiply, we can just do an assignment. So we save some computation by doing that.
Now unfortunately this is not a correct rule. And this is one of the important
things to know about compiling optimization, is that it's not always
obvious when it's legal to do certain optimizations or not. Now it turns out
That this particular rule is valid for integers. Okay, so if X and Y are
integers, then multiplying by zero is always the same thing as just signing
zero. But, it's invalid for floating point. And why is that, well because you
have to know some details of the IEEE floating point standard, but there is a
special number in the IEEE standard called not a number and it turns out that
not a number called a NaN times zero is equal to not a number. Any particular
non-number times zero is not equal to zero If X and Y are plotting point numbers, you
can't do this optimization. In fact, if you did this optimization, it would break
certain very important algorithms that rely on the proper propagation of
not a number. Finally, the last compiler phase is code generation, often
referred to as Code Gen, and Code Gen, can produce assembly code. That's the most
common thing that a compiler would produce. But in general, it's a
translation into some other language. And this is, entirely analogous to human
translation. So just as a human translator might translate, English into French, a
compiler will translate a high level program into assembly code. To wrap up,
almost every compiler has the five phases that we outlined. However, the proportions
have changed a lot over the years, and if we were to go back to FORTRAN I and
look inside of that compiler, we would probably see a size and complexity that
looks something like this. We have a fairly complex lexical analysis phase, an
equally complicated parsing phase, a very small semantic analysis phase, a. A fairly
involved optimization phase and another fairly involved code generation phase. And
so we see a compiler where the complexity was sp, spread fairly evenly throughout
except for its semantic analysis which is very weak in the early days. And today
if we look at a modern compiler you'll see almost nothing in lengthening, very little
in parsing, because we have extremely good tools to help us write those two phases.
We would see a fairly involved thematic analysis phase. We would see a very large
optimization phase, and this is in fact the dominant component off all modern
compilers, and the a small code-generation phase because again we understand that
phase very, very well. That's it for this lecture. Future lectures, we'll look at
each of these phases in detail.