Welcome back, In this video we're going to talk about converting regular expressions
into non-deterministic finite automata. Before we get started I wanna give you an
overview of the plan for the next few videos. We have a lexical specification
that we want to implement and the first step is for someone to write that down as
a set of regular expressions. Now that bites all the courses not implementation,
that's just specification. So we have to translate that into a program that can
actually do lexical analysis and this actually happens in several steps. The
first part is a translate Those regular expressions into non-deterministic finite
automata that recognize the same, exactly the same thing. And then those
non-deterministic automata are translated into deterministic automata and finally
those deterministic automata are implemented as a set of Lookup tables and
a little bit of code for traversing those tables. So in previous videos, we talked
about this piece and we've also defined this piece. And so now we're ready to put
the whole thing together and in this particular video, we're going to focus on
this component right here, The translation of regular expressions to
non-deterministic finite automata. So the plan is that for each kind of regular
expression we're going to find an equivalent Non-deterministic Automata,
automaton that accepts exactly the same language as the language or a regular
expression. And here's a little bit of notation we're gonna use. We'll define
these automaton for regular expressions and usually, what we're going to be doing
is needing to modify their start states and their final states so we'll just
indicate the start state with the l and the final state. With the double circle
and we won't worry too much about the overall structure of the machine as long
as we have a handle on the start state and the final state. I should say that in the
machines we'll build here, there will only be one final state. Okay, so let's begin.
So for the epsilon regular expression, once the machine that accepts that, well
this is a very simple machine. We can just have a start state and a final state and
epsilon transition between them so this machine accepts exactly the empty string.
Certainly for a single character A, we can define a one transition two state machine
that accepts that one character. So from the start state we can move to the final
state if it only, if we read that particular character, okay. So those are
out two simple regular expressions and now we have to do the compound regular
expressions. And these are little [inaudible] involved. So let's talk about
concatenation first. And so, because we're gonna build these machines up from
smaller. Regular expressions to larger ones, we can assume that we've already
converted A and B separately in two machines. So I have the machine for A. And
to have a machine for B and now all I have to do is say how I'm going to paste
together these two machines to form a machine, a compound machine that
recognizes the same language as a concatenated with B. And here's the
construction, the start state for the compound machine will be the start state
for A so we'll just keep that start state for A the same and then we modify the
final state of A. So we make the final state of A no longer a final state and
I've done that here by removing the double circle on the final state of A andthe
epsilon transition to the start state of B. Now if we think about it, that does
exactly the right thing but that says, is that first you recognize some portion of
the input that belongs to the language of A, and when we get to that, what would
been the final state of A, we can jump to the start state of B without consuming any
input and then try to read the rest of the string as part of the language, as, as a
string in the language of B. And for union we have a similar way of phasing together
the machines. Although the, the structure is somewhat different so we, at a new
start state for the compound machine and What does A + B mean? It means either the
input is in the language of A, or it's in the language of B. And epsilon transitions
are really good for capturing this because we just make a decision right from the
start state is the string going to be in language of A or is it going to be in the
language of B. So we make a non-deterministic choice and then we read
the string as using that, the automaton that we chose and if we get to the final
state. Either those machines we can make the epsilon transition to the new final
state for the compound machine. Now remember what the notion is of acceptance
for Nondeterministic Automata, you know? They make these guesses but if there's any
guess that works, then we say that it's in the language of the machine. So, if in
fact the string is in the union of A or B then either choosing A or choosing B will
work and so the machine will accept the string. And finally the most complicated
case for iteration is star, we have the following construction, So here's the
machine for A, Embedded in here. We've added a new start state and a new final
state, And now, let's talk about how this works. So one possibility is, remember
that epsilon is always in the language of A star, and so we have this transition here,
We can go straight from the start state to the final state and accept the empty
string. And so, that just guarantees that the empty string is in the language.
Otherwise, what do we do? Otherwise, we can make a transition, an epsilon
transition to the start state of A. And then we can, from the final state of A if
we reach it, we can go back to the start state of the whole machine and we can do
this as many times as we like. Okay, So, there's the iteration of A, Surround this
loop right here, And when we reach the final state of A we can also decide to
just make a transition to the final state of the machine, we conclude that the last
time. And so this machine recognizes zero or more strings in the language of A. So
now, let's do an example, So here's a regular expression and we want to build a
equivalent nondeterministic machine that recognizes the sa me language and we're
gonna follow our construction, Which works by induction on the structure of the
regular expressions starting with the simple regular expressions and building up
to the compound one so what do we have here? So we have a machine for accepting
one, okay. So we need a machine that accepts one and if we call it had two
states and it just, you know made a transition between the two on the number
one, Similarly a machine for accepting zero. Okay, And now, we need to put them
together in a machine that accepts either one or zero. And the way we did that is we
made a choice from A, from a start state for the compound machine where you can
either move to the machine for accepting one or the machine for accepting zero. And
then we have, at the end, also epsilon moves back to the final state of the
compound machine. Okay, And now we need to iterate this so we need to be able to
accept zero or more of one's or zero's and so we're going to take this entire Block
here and paste it into the pattern that we had for iteration so how do we do that?
Well, we have a new start state and a new final state, okay. And there's an epsilon
move from the start state to the new final state to guarantee that we accept the
empty string. And then we can just iterate this inner machine as many times as we
like. We can make an epsilon move to the start state, We could execute the machine
ones and if we decide we want to do it again, well we can do that. Okay, Go back
around for another time, Or from the final state, we can decide that we've seen
enough and we can just move to the final state of the compound machine. So this
machine then accepts the language one + zero'lt;i>. And now, we have a little bit more'lt;/i>
to do. We have to accept, we have other machine that accepts just one so we build
another machine that accepts The digit one and now we need to compose two of these
things, to concatenate them and that was very simple. We just have an epsilon move
from the final state of the first machine to the start state of the second mac hine
and then these are all the states of the final machine. And we just need to now
label our final, final state or the end of the state that we're actually gonna use in
the end of the final state of the entire machine which should be that one and the
start state, Which is this state over here. And that's the entire construction
for the non-deterministic automata or a non-deterministic automata that recognizes
this language.