Welcome back. In this video, we're going to talk about converting nondeterministic
finite automata into deterministic finite automata. Here again is our little diagram
of the pipeline of a lexical analyzer, how one is constructed. So beginning with the
lexical specification, we write our regular expressions. Last time we talked
about the step, the conversion of regular expressions and the non-deterministic
finite automata and this time we're going to talk about this step. And as you might
guess in the final video in the series we'll talk about the final step which is
the implementation of DFA's. So here's the Nondeterministic Finite Automata and we
finished up with last time. And, the first thing we're gonna discuss today is an
important idea called the Epsilon Closure of a state. And the basic idea of the
epsilon culture is that I pick the states. And it could a set of states but we'll
just do it for a single state. And then I look at all the states that I can reach by
following only epsilon moves. And so b is the state that we're starting with so b
would be included in the set and then there's an epsilon move to c. So c would
be included in the set and there's another epsilon move to d so d would be included
in the set. So we would say, the epsilon closure of b is = the set b c d. And let's
do one more as an example. Want to take the epsilon closure of g. And when we
switch colors up to this one, I'll erase that and to this one in pink, Our
purple-ish pink. So the epsilon closure of g, we always have to follow all the
epsilon transitions out of g. So, h would be in the epsilon closure of g but it's
not just single epsilon move. This is recursive. So any number of epsilon moves
that I can take, all of those states are included in the epsilon closure of g. So,
in fact, i would also be included. A would be included and b and c and d will also be
included And now, if I look at all of these states that have been colored in the
light purple color. I can see that I can't reach any new states from those states
using only epsilon moves and so the epsilon closure of g would be equal to and
[inaudible] out here it's a, b, c, d. Ghi. Okay. So that is the epsilon closure of a
state. Recall from the last video that an NFA maybe in many states any given point
in time that is because of the choices it can make for a given input and NFA may
reach multiple different states. And the question we want to address now is how
many different states can it be in? Well if a non-deterministic automaton has n
states. And it winds up in some subset of those states as how big can that subset b
will clearly the cardinality of that said has to be less than or equal to n. So the
NFA can get into a most and different states. Now instead, I want to know the
number of different subsets, well how many different subsets are there of any things.
Well that means there are two to the n - one possible subsets of n states. And
there's something very interesting about this number. First of all it's a very big
number so clearly the NFA can get into lots of different configurations
particularly one it has a lot of different states but the important thing is that
this is a finite set of possible configurations. And this is going to give
us the seed of the idea. For converting an NFA into a DFA or Deterministic Automata
because all we have to be able to do to convert a Nondeterministic Automata into
Deterministic Automata is come up with a way for the Deterministic Automata to
simulate for the [inaudible] of the Nondeterministic Automata and the fact
that the Nondeterministic Automata can only get into a finite set of
configurations even that configurations is very large, is exactly what we will
exploit in the construction. Now we're ready to give the construction showing how
to map an arbitrary nondeterministic finite automaton to an equivalent
deterministic finite automaton. So let's begin by saying what's in our NFA. So,
we'll have a set of states, Which we'll call s and these are the states of the
Nondeterministic machine. There's a star t state, a little s which is one of the
states and there is a set of final states F. And then we also have to give the
transition function and I want to write out the state transition function. I want
to use the state transition function to define a, a operator that we're going to
find handy for defining our DFA. So I'd say that a applied to a set of states so x
here is a set of states and a is a character in the input language. So, a and
x is = those states y such that there is some x little x here, single state in the
set of states such that there's a transition from x to y on input a. Okay.
So this is just a way of saying I've given the transition function at this set level.
It says for a given set of state x, show me all the states that you can reach on
input a. Alright. So now we're ready to define our DFA. So what will the DFA be?
Well, it's gonna have to have all of these things. It's gonna have to have, perhaps
where the states are? What are the start state is? What's the final states are and
what's the transition function is? So let's begin with the set of states. The
states will be the subsets Of s. So the states of the DFA will be all possible
subsets of the states of the NFA so there will be one state of DFA for each subset
of possible, each possible subset of states of the NFA. And of course this is
potentially a very big number but it's still finite and so we can use that set
of, of subsets of states as the states based of the Deterministic machine So, now
what's the start state of the DFA. Well that's going
to
be the  epsilon closure. Now one of the set of final states, Well,
so the final states will be consist of those state x and every member of the
states of the DFA are sets of states of the NFA. So that x is a set and is can be
every x such that x intersected with the set of final states of the NFA is not
empty. And finally we need to define the transition function. And do we do that?
Well, we, we need to say that for a given state x and another state y, when is there
a transition between them on some input a. Well that, there will be such a transition
under that conditions and well let's write them out. So, remember we're in state x.
And what do we need to know? Well we need to know, the set of states that we can
reach on input A, and we'll be justifying that that's A of X, and then once we've
gotten to where these, once we've seen where we can go from the set of states X
of input A. There's also a possibility of making [inaudible] after that so
furthermore we have to take the [inaudible] closer of that set of states,
okay? And So we'll say that there's a transition from x to y if y is equal to
this set of states. Alright, And notice that there's only one such set of states
for any x and that guarantees of this is a deterministic machine. Each machine, each
state will only have one possible move on each input so. We can just, now it goes to
our check list and see if we have a deterministic machine. We have a finite
set of states. We have a start state and we have a set of final states and we have
a transition function with only one more per input and no epsilon moves. And so
that is in fact a deterministic machine and the property that it maintain is that
each step of computation. The state of the DFA records the set of possible states
that the NFA could have gotten into the same input So let's work to an example of
constructing a Deterministic machine from a Nondeterministic machine. Here's the
Nondeterministic Finite Automata that we built in the last video and again this is
the one that I used at the beginning of the video to define epsilon enclosure. So
we're gonna do the example slightly differently than the construction I gave
on the previous slide. If we actually have to write out all the subsets of this many
states, it will take us a very, very long time. And it turns out that not all of the
subsets were actually used by the DFA. So we're just going to enumerate the states
that we actually need and we'll do that by beginning with the start sta te of DFA and
then working out which additional states are required. So how do we do that? Well,
we begin with the start state of the NFA which is just this state a. And then
recall at the start of the DFA is the epsilon closure of that state so that
corresponds to this purple set here. Alright. So the first state of the DFA,
the start state is the subset of states a, b, c, d, h, i. And now we have to work out
from this particular state from the start state what happens on each of the
impossible input values. So, the alphabet of this machine is one and zero so you
would have to have two transitions out of the state, one for an input of one and one
for an input of zero. So let's do input zero first. And, we can see looking at the
purple set that there's only one possible transition and that's from the state D to
the state F. So certainly the state s is included in the set of states if the NFA
can reach but then once we get the state f there's a lot of epsilon moves that we can
take and so in fact the second state of the DFA corresponds to a much larger set.
It's all the, it's the epsilon closure of f and that is, this set of states f, g, h,
i, a, b, c, and d, okay. So these are the set of possible states that the NFA could
be in after reading a single zero. Next, let's consider what happens from the start
state on an input of one. Which possible states can the NFA reach? And, if we look
at the transition function, we see there are two possible moves that the NFA could
take. It could be in state c. In which case it would move to state e or it could
have been state i, that's also part of the purple set in which case it would move to
state j. So, there are two possible states that the NFA can get into as a result of
reading a one and then after that, there's a bunch of epsilon moves that can take
place and in fact, it turns out that after reading a one, the machine could be in any
state except for state f. And that's this set of states and you'll notice that this
particular set of states, the read set includes the final state of the NFA so
this is also a final state indicating that after reading one, the NFA could be in an
accepting state. So this would be an accepting state of the DFA Well, we still
have to fill in for both of the two states that we've added here. The two states on
the right of the machine what they do on input zero, what they do on input one. So
let's figure that out. So beginning with the red state on input zero, what can
happen? Well, look the red state includes state d and it can move to state f but
we've already computed what happens on the epsilon, what the epsilon closure that is
just the green state. And so if I'm in the red state and I read zero, I move to the
green state. If I'm in the red state and I read a one, you'll see that both states,
NFA states c and i are in the red set. And so, it just takes us back to the red set.
And similarly for the green state, if I read a one, I move to the red state. And
if I read a zero, I stay in the green state. And so, this then is our
deterministic machine down here. This is the deterministic machine and again, it
simulates the NFA. So every move at the deterministic machine, it records the set
of possible states that the NFA could be in and it will accept a string infinitely
if the NFA could accept the string.