In this video, we're gonna begin our discussion of parsing technology with
context-free grammars. Now as we know, not all strings of tokens are actually valid
programs and the parser has to tell the difference. It has to know which strings
of tokens are valid and which ones are invalid and give error messages for the
invalid ones. So, we need some way of describing the valid strings of tokens and
then some kind of algorithm for distinguishing the valid and invalid
strings of tokens from each other. Now we've also discussed that programming
languages have a natural recursive structure, So for example in Cool, an
expression That can be anyone of a very large number of things. So two of the
things that can be are an if expression and a while expression but these
expressions are themselves recursively composed of other expressions. So for
example, the predicate of an if is a, a [inaudible] expression as is the then
branch and the else branch and in a while loop the termination test is an expression
and so is the loop body. And context-free grammars are in natural notation for
describing such recursive structures. So within a context-free grammar so formally
it consist a set of terminals t, a set of nonterminals n, a start symbol s and s is
one of the nonterminals and a set of productions and what's a production? A
production is a symbol followed by an arrow followed by a list of symbols. And
these symbols, there are certain rules about them so the x thing on the left hand
side of the arrow has to be a nonterminal. That's what it means to be on the left
hand side so the set of things on the left hand side of productions are exactly the
nonterminals. And then the right hand side every yi on the right hand side can be
either a nonterminal or it can be a terminal or it can be the special symbol
epsilon. So let's do a simple example of a Context-free Grammar. Strings of balanced
parenthesis which we discussed in an earlier video can be expressed as follows.
So, we have our start symbol and. One possibility for a string o f balanced
parentheses is that it consists of an open paren on another string of balanced
parentheses and a close paren. And, the other possibility for a string of balanced
parentheses that is empty because the empty string is also a string of balanced
parentheses. So, there are two productions for this grammar and just to go over the
to, to relate this example to the formal definition we gave on the previous slide,
what is our set of nine terminals, it's just. The singles nonterminal s, what our
terminal symbols in this context-free grammar is just open and close paren. No
other symbols. What's the start symbol? Well, it's s. It's the only nonterminal so
it has to be the start symbol but generally we will, when we give grammars
the first production will name a start symbol so rather than name and explicitly
whichever production occurs first the symbol on the left hand side will be the
nonterminal for that particular context-free grammar. And then finally,
what are the productions with the, we said there could be a set of productions and
here are the two productions for this particular Context-Free Grammar. Now,
productions can be read as rules. So, let's write down one of our productions
from the from the example grammar and what does this mean? This means wherever we see
an s, we can replace it by the string of symbols on the right hand side. So,
Wherever I see an s I can substitute and I can take the s out. If that important, I
remove the s that appears on the left side and I replace it by the string of symbols
on the right hand side so productions can be read as replacement rule so right hand
side replaces the left hand side. So here's a little more formal description of
that process. We begin with the string that has only the start symbol s, so we
always start with just the start symbol. And now, we look at our string initially
it's just a start symbol but it changes overtime, and we can replace any
non-terminal in the string by the right hand side, side of some production for
that non-terminal. So for exam ple, I can replace a non-terminal x by the right hand
side of some production for x. X in this case, x goes to y1 through yn. And then we
just repeat step two over and over again until there are no non-terminals left
until the string consist of only terminals. And at that point, we're done.
So, to write this out slightly more formally, a single step here consist of a
state which is a, which is a string of symbols, so this can be terminals and
non-terminals. And, somewhere in the string is a non-terminal x and there is a
production for x, in our grammar. So this is part of the grammar, okay? This is a
production And we can use now production to take a step from, to a new state Where
we have replaced X by the right hand side of the production, Okay? So this is one
step of a context-free derivation. So now if you wanted to do multiple steps, we
could have a bunch of steps, alpha zero goes to alpha one goes to alpha two and
these are strings now. Alpha i's are all strings and as we go along we eventually
get to some strong alpha n, alright. And then we say that alpha zero rewrites in
zero or more steps to alpha n so this means n zero, greater than or equal to
zero steps. Okay. So this is just a short hand for saying there is some sequence of
individual productions. Individual rules being applied to a string that gets us
from the string alpha string zero to the string alpha n and remember that in
general we start with just the start symbol and so we have a whole bunch of
sequence of steps like this that get us from start symbol to some other string. So
finally, we can define the language of a Context-Free Grammar. So, [inaudible]
context-free grammar has a start symbol s, so then the language of the context-free
grammar is gonna be the string of symbols alpha one through alpha n such that for
all i. Alpha i is an element of the terminals of g, okay. So t here is the set
of terminals of g and s goes, the start symbol s goes in zero or more steps to
alpha one, I'm sorry a1 to an, okay. And so we're just saying, this is just saying
that all the strings of terminals that I can derive beginning with just the start
symbol, those are the strings in the language. So the name terminal comes from
the fact that once terminals are included in the string, there is no rule of
replacing them. That is once the terminal is generated, it's a permanent feature of
the string and in applications to programming languages and context-free
grammars, the terminals are to be the tokens of the language that we are
modeling with our context-free grammar. With that in mind, let's try the
context-free grammar for a fragment of [inaudible]. So, [inaudible] expressions,
we talked about these earlier, but one possibility for a [inaudible] expression
is that it's an if statement or an if expression. And, we call that [inaudible]
if statements have three parts. And they end with the keyword [inaudible] which is
a little bit unusual. And so looking at this looking at this particular rule, we
can see some conventions that way, that are pretty standard and that we'll use so
that non-terminals are in all caps. Okay, so in this case was just [inaudible] we'll
try that in caps and then the terminal symbols are in, in lower case, all right?
And another possibility Is that it could be a while expression. And finally the
last possibility Is that it could be identifier id and there actually many,
many more possibilities and lots of other cases for expressions and let me just show
you one bit of notation to make things look a little bit nicer. So we have many
we have many productions for the same non-terminal. We usually group those
together in the grammar and we only write a non-terminal on the right hand side once
and then we write explicit alternative. So this is actually. Completely the same as
writing out expert arrow two more times but we here we just is, this is just a way
of grouping these three productions together and saying that expr- is the
non-terminal for all three right hand sides. Let's take a look at some of the
strings on the language of this Context- Free Grammar. So, a valid Kuhl expression
is just a single identifier and that's easy to see because EXPR is our start
symbol, I'll call it EXPR. And, so the production it does says it goes to id. So
I can take the start symbol directly to a string of terminals, a single variable
name is a valid Kuhl expression. Another example is an e-th expression where e-th
of the subexpressions is just a variable name. So this is perfectly fine structure
for a Kuhl expression. Similarly I can do the same thing with the while expression.
I can take the structure of a while and then replace each of the subexpressions
just with a single variable name and that would be a syntactically valid cool while
loop. There are more complicated expressions so for example, here we have a
why loop as the predicate of an if expression. That's something you might
normally think or writing but perfectly well form and tactically. Similarly, I
could have an if statement or an if expression as the predicate of and if it's
inside of an if expression. So, so nested if expressions like this one are also
syntactically valid. Let's do another grammar, this time for simple arithmetic
expressions. So, we'll have our start symbol and only non-terminal for this
grammar be called e and one of the possibilities while e could be the sum of
expressions. Or and remember this is an alternative notation for e arrow. It's
just a way of saying I'm going to use the nonterminal for another production. We can
have a sum of two expressions or we could have the Multiplication of two
expressions. And then we could have expressions that appear inside the
parentheses, so parenthesized expressions. And just to keep things simple, we could
just have as our base, only base case simple identifier so variable names. And
here's a small grammar over plus and times to see and in parentheses and variable
names. [inaudible] a few elements of this language. So for example, a single
variable name is a perfectly good element of the language id + id is also in this
language. Which s is id + id id and we could also use parens to group things so
we could say id + id id that's also something you can generate using these
rules and so on and so forth. There are many, many more strings in this language.