In this video, we're gonna continue our discussion of parsing with the idea of a
derivation. So a derivation is a sequence of productions so beginning with the start
symbol, we can apply productions one at a time. In sequence and that produces a
derivation. And a derivation can be drawn in a different way instead of as a linear
sequence of replacements, we can draw it as a tree. So for example, if I have a
nonterminal x it appears in a derivation, then when I replace x, I can represent
that by making the children Of x, the left hand side of the rule that I used to
replace x. So I applied production x goes to y1 to yn, I add the y1 to yn is
children of x in the tree that I'm building up. Let's do an example. Here is
our simple grammar of arithmetic expressions and let's consider this
particular string id id + id. So what we're going to do now is we're going to
parse this string and we're going to show how to produce a derivation for the string
and also at the same time build the tree. And here it is, Over here, there is
derivation beginning in e and ending in the string that we're interested in with
one production applied each step along the way and here is the corresponding tree and
this is called a parse tree. This is a parse tree of this expression or this
input string. So let's walk through this derivation in detail. The right side in
red, we're going to have the tree that we're building up. And on the left side in
blue, we're going to have the steps in the derivation that we've taken so far. So
initially, our derivation consists of just the start symbol e and our tree consists
of just the root which is also the start symbol. So the first step is that we have
a production e goes to e + e and what that means is over on the tree, we take the
root of the tree and we make, we give it three children e + ne. So now, we replace
the first t by e z. We use the production e goes to e z and that means
we take the first e in the tree and we give it to three children, e
[inaudible]. Continuing along we take the fi rst e here that remains in this
expression and we replace it by id which means we make id a child of the left most
e in the tree that we're building. And then we replace the second e by id using
the production e goes to id and finally, we use the same thing with the third e and
now, we have completed our Parse Tree. So here again, from the start symbol to the
string, we were interested in parsing and in the process we built up this Parse Tree
of the expression. Now there are lots of interesting things to say about parse
trees. So first of all, parse trees have terminals at the leaves and nonterminals
at the interior nodes and furthermore, in-order traversal of the leaves is the
original input. So let's back up and look at our example and confirm all this. If we
look at the leaves, we can see that they are all terminals, Okay? And the interior
nodes are all nonterminals. In this case, it's only one nonterminal in our language,
all the interior nodes are e and the leaves are the terminals of the string.
And then we can see if we do an inward reversal of the leaves, we get exactly
this input string that we started with. Furthermore, the Parse Tree shows the
association of the operations and the input string does not. So you may notice
here that the way that this Parse Tree is constructed, the times binds more tightly
than the plus because the times is a sub-tree. Of the tree containing plus. And
so this means that we would do the e e first before we would add e and some, some
of you may have wondered well, how did I know. To pick this Parse Tree because
actually if you think about it, there's another derivation. Actually there are
several derivations that will give me a different Parse Tree where the plus, where
the times is towards the root and the plus is nested inside the times. So let's not
worry about that for right now, and let's just say that somehow we knew that this
was the Parse Tree we wanted and I gave you a derivation that produces that Parse
Tree. Continuing on, the previous derivation I showed you is actually a very
special derivation. It's what's called a leftmost derivation where each step will
replace the leftmost nonterminal in our string of terminals and nonterminals. And
there's a natural and equivalent notion of a rightmost derivation and here it is.
Here is a rightmost derivation for the same string. Again, beginning with the
start symbol ending with a string we're interested in. And notice that at each
step, we're replacing the rightmost non-terminal. So here, we replace the only
non-terminal e and we get e + c. And then in the second step, we replace the second
non-terminal e with id and so on for the rest of the string. So let's just
illustrate this entirely with our little picture here of the tree and the
derivation simultaneously so once again over here is our tree and this is the
root, the start symbol e and, and in blue is our derivation so we begin by replacing
e by e + e. That's the only nonterminal so it's the rightmost one and then working
from the right side of the tree, we replace the right e by id and then the
left id gets replaced by e z. And now the right most e that remains is replaced
by id and finally the only e that remains is also replaced by id. Now I want to
point out that the rightmost and leftmost derivations I showed you have exactly the
same Parse Tree. And, this was not an accident. Every Parse Tree has a rightmost
and a leftmost derivation. It's just about the order in which the branches are added.
So for example, if I have the first production e goes to e + e, now I have a
choice on how to build my tree. I can either work on. This sub-tree or I can
work on that sub-tree. And if I build this one first, that will be a rightmost
derivation. If I continue to always work on the rightmost non-terminal of course,
And if I work on this one first, I can use that to do a leftmost derivation. Now it's
important also to realize that there are many derivations besides rightmost and
leftmost. I could, I could choose non-terminals in some random order to do
my replacements. But th e rightmost and leftmost ones are the ones that we're most
concerned with.