In this video, I'm going to cover a limitation of the Recursive Descent
Algorithm that I presented last time. Here's the grammar from our last
presentation, and here's its implementation again, as a set of
mutually recursive function that together, implement this simple recursive
descent strategy. And now, let's think about what happens.
When we go to parse the input int, simplest possible input strength.
Well, let's work through it. So remember, we start with the function
that implements all the productions for the non-terminal e.
And so what we're going to do here, we're going to call e.
And that will try calling E1. All right?
And what is E1 going to do? E1 is going to call T.
Because, of course, the first production is E goes to T.
So let's take a look at what T does. T is going to try out the production of
T1, all right? And what does T1 do?
Well, T1 recognizes an int. Okay, so that's good.
And it will match it and return, okay, and then E will return and we will
succeed in parsing. And I forgot to mention it, also the
process, the input point will be moved across the int, and so when we're done
you will return, and we will have succeeded in parsing the string int
because E return true the production for E return true, and we consumed all of the
input. All right?
So now, let's consider a slightly more complicated example, okay?
So let's try the input string Int times int.
All right? So again, we start with the production E.
Okay? And the first thing we'll do, is we'll
try the production E1. Same thing we did last time.
E1 is going to call the function T. And T is going to try the first
production for T. Which, again, is the production int.
Okay? And the input pointer, of course, is
here, and then it will try to match that against an int.
Okay? If I match the first token in the input
stream against the, the terminal int. And it will succeed.
Okay? So the input pointer will be moved over.
So T1 will return true. All right?
And as a result. This right hand side here of the function
T will also succeed, because T1 returns true, so T will return true.
Okay? Therefore, E1 will return true and E, E1
returning true will cause E to return true.
And in fact that will be the end of the execution of the program will terminate.
E will return true and the input player will only have advanced as far as int,
and so we will reject the parse. This is actually, ends up getting
rejected. And the question of course is what
happened? All right.
Why didn't we succeed in parsing this input?
Which is clearly in the language of this grammar.
Well, the story here is actually a little bit interesting.
What happened is down here when we discovered that Int matched the first
production for T, we said that T was done.
Okay, T had succeeded, had matched it's input.
And then, when E ultimately returns and the whole parse fails, because we haven't
consumed the input, we don't have a way to back track and try another alternative
for T. If we were going to succeed we would have
to say, oh, well even though, we found a production for T that matched part of the
input. Since the overall parts fail, that must
not have been the right production to choose for T.
Maybe we should try some other productions for T.
And in fact if we'd tried the second production for T, T2.
We would have matched Int times T, and then we probably would of succeeded.
We would have been able to manage int times int.
Okay? And so, the problem here is that even
though there is backtracking within a production; while we're trying to find a
production that works for a given non-terminals.
So, while there is backtracking For a non-terminal during the time that we're
trying to find a production that works for that non-terminal, but there is no
backtracking once we have found a production that succeeds for
non-terminals. So once a non-terminal commits and
returns and says, I have found a way to parse part of the input using one of my
productions. There's no way, in this particular
structure, this particular algorithm, to go back and revisit that decision and try
a different production. All right?
So the problem is that if a production for non-terminal x succeeds, there's no
way to backtrack to try a different production for x later.
So once x, once the function for x has returned.
And we're really committed to that production.
Now that means that the particularly Recursive Descent Algorithm that I showed
in the last video, is not completely general, and Recursive Descent is a
general technique. There are algorithms for Resursive
Descent parsing that can parse any grammar.
That can implement the full language of any grammar.
And they have more sophisticated backtracking, than what I showed in the
algorithm that I presented last time. Now the reason for showing this
particular algorithm is that it's easy to implement by hand.
So this is actually an algorithm, or approach to Recursive Descent that while
it has this limitation, as you can see, it's very mechanical and very
straightforward to design a parser for a given for a given grammar.
And it will work for a rather large class, class of grammar.
So in particular, it'll work for any grammar where for any non-terminal at
most one production can succeed. So if you know from the way that you've
built your grammar, that in any situation, that the grammar can get into
or the Recursive Descent Algorithm can get into during parsing, that at most one
production can succeed. Then it this, this parsing is gradually
will be sufficient, because there will never be, once you find a production that
succeeds, there will never be a need to go back and revisit that decision,
because it must be the case that none of the other productions could have
succeeded. And it turns out that the example grammar
that we're working with in the last couple of videos could actually be
written to work with this algorithm. All right.
And we would have to left factor the grammar.
Well, actually there's more than one way to rewrite the grammar to work with this
Recursive Decent Algorithm but one way to do it Is to left factor it.
I'm not going to say any more about left factoring in this video, because that's
going to be a topic of a video that's coming up shortly.