In this video, we're going to use our example automaton for recognizing viable
prefixes, to introduce one more idea, The idea of a valid item. To refresh your
memory, here's where we left off last time. This is the complete
nondeterministic automaton for recognizing the viable prefixes of the example grammar
[sound]. And Using the standard subset of states construction, we can build a
deterministic automaton that is equivalent to the non-deterministic automaton. So
here's the deterministic automaton that recognizes exactly the same language. This
automa, this deterministic automaton notices the viable prefixes, of our
example grammar. But now notice that each state is a set of items. So there's a set
of non-deterministic automaton states, in each of these states. And recall that what
that means is that the non-deterministic automaton could be in any one of these
states. And in particular, this state here is the start state because it has the item
S prime goes to dot E. The states of this deterministic automaton are called
variously cananugal collections of items or the cananugal collections of LR zero
items. If you look in the dragon book it gives another way of constructing the LR
zero items than the one that I gave. Mine is somewhat simplified but I think also a
little easier to understand if you are seeing this for the first time. Now we
need another definition. We'll say that a given item is valid for a viable prefix
alpha beta. If the following is true, that beginning from the start symbol, this is
our extra start symbol, and by a series of right-most derivation steps, we can get to
a configuration, alpha-x-omega, and then in one step, x can go to beta-gamma. And,
what this says is after parsing alpha and beta, after seeing. Alpha and beta on the
stack, the valid items are the possible tops of the stack of items. That, that we
could, that this item, could be the determination state of the
nondeterministic automaton. A simpler way of explaining the same idea is that for a
given viable prefix alpha the items that are valid in that prefix are exactly the
items that are in the final state of the DFA after it reads that prefix. So these
are the items that describe the state after you've seen the stack alpha. Now, an
item is often valid for many, many prefixes. So, for example, the item T goes
to open paren .e closed paren is valid for all sequences of open parens. And to see
that, We can just look at our automaton and confirm that if we see an open paren,
remember, this is the start state. So if we see an open paren, we take this
transition, we wind up in this state here. And then every open paren we see, we just
go round and round in this state. So if I have a sequence of five open parens as my
input, then I'll have transitions one, two, three, four, five, all looping in
this state. And notice that this item. Is, in, is one of the items in that state. And
that just says that this item is valid for any prefix, or for, excuse me, any
sequence of open parens.