In this video, we're going to introduce another important concept in bottom-up
parsing, the notion of a handle. To review, bottom up parsing is these two
kinds of actions: we have shift moves, which just read one token of input and
move the vertical bar one to the right, And reduced moves, which replace the right
hand side of a production [inaudible] to the left of the vertical bar by a
production left hand side. So in this case, the production must have been A goes
to XY. And also reviewing what we did in the last video, the left string can be
implemented by a stack, where the top of the stack is marked by the vertical bar.
So shift pushes the terminal on to the stack and reduce pops zero or more symbols
of the stack, and that's gonna be the right hand stack of some production. And
then it's going to push one non-terminal on to the stack which is the left hand
side of that same production. And the key question in bottom of parsing and the one
we haven't addressed at all yet is how do we decide when to shift and when to
reduce. So let's take a look at this example grammar. And let's think about a
step of a parse where we've shifted one token onto the stack. We have Nth on the
stack, and then we have times N plus N still to go that we haven't seen yet. Now
at this point we could decide to reduce by T goes to N because we have the production
T goes to Nth right here. And so we could then get into this particul-, potential
state, or this particular state, where we have T on the stack and then the rest of
the input that looks like that. A-, but you can see that this would be a mistake.
There is no production in the grammar that begins Hence T times. There's no
production up here that looks like T times. And therefore if we were to, to, to
make this move, we would get stuck. We could continue to do reductions, to
rummage around in the string. But we would never be able to get back to the start
symbol. Because there is no way to deal a sub string that has t times something in
it. So what that shows us is that we don't always want to reduce just because we have
the right-hand side of a production on top of the stack. To repeat that, even if
there's the right-hand side of some production sitting right there on top of
the stack, it might be a mistake to do a reduction. We might want to wait and do
our reduction someplace else. And the idea about how we decide is that we only want
to reduce if the result can still be reduced to the start symbol. So let's take
a look at a right most innervations. So, beginning with the start symbol, we get to
some state after, after some number of steps where that means, just an arbitrary
number of steps. We get to some state X is the right most non-terminal and then the
next step is to replace X with by the right hand side of some production. And
remember, again, with bottom up parsing, the parsers are actually going in this
direction, okay. So, this is the reduction direction. The derivation direction, the
production direction, Because that's the easiest way to talk about what strings are
derived. We wanna begin with a start symbol. But the [inaudible], but the
parser's actually going against the flow of these arrows. Anyway if this is a
rightmost derivation Then we say that alpha beta is a handle of alpha beta
omega. And that just means that, yes, it would be okay in this situation to reduce
beta to X. And we could replace beta by X, because it's not a mistake. We can still,
by some sequence of moves, get back to the start symbol. You know, by, by doing more
reductions. So handles formulize the intuition about where it is okay to do a
reduction. A handle is just a reduction that also allows further reduction back to
the start symbol And we clearly only want to do reduction at handles. If we do a
reduction at a place that is not a handle even though it looks like it's the right
hand side or maybe actually be the right hand side of some production, that does
not mean. That it's actually a handle, and we might, if we could reduce there, we may
get stuck. So all we said so far is what a handle is. We've defined, a handle, We
haven't said anything about how to find the handles. And actually, how we find the
handles is gonna consume much of the rest of our discussion of parsing.