In this video, we're finally going to give an actual bottom up parsing algorithm. In
particular, we'll talk about SLR, or simple LR parsing, which will build on the
ideas of valid items, and viable prefixes that we've been discussing in our recent
videos. The first thing we're going to do is to define a very weak bottom up parsing
algorithm called LR0 parsing. And the basic idea here is that we're going to
assume a stack contains a contents alpha, and that the next input is token T And
that the DFA, this is the DFA that recognizes, the viable prefixes. On input
alpha, that is, when it reads the stack contents, it terminates in some state S.
[sound] And There's only gonna be two things that this that this parsing
algorithm needs to do. So if S, if the final state of the DFA contains the item X
goes to beta dot. Well, what does that say? That says we've seen the complete
right hand side, of X goes to beta on the top of the stack, and that furthermore,
everything that's below the stack still says that x goes to beta dot is a valid,
or a viable, sorry, is a valid item for this state. Meaning its okay to reduce by
X goes to beta. So if we see a complete production dot all the way in the right
hand side in the final state of the DFA, then we're just going to reduce by that
production. The other possible move is a shift. If we wind up in a state, where, X
goes to beta .t, and then some other stuff is a valid item, what does that say? That
says that it would be okay at this point to add a T to the stack. And if T is our
input, well, then we should do a shift move [sound]. Now, when does LR0 parsing
get into trouble? Well, there are two possible problems it could have. It might
not be able to decide. Between two possible reduced moves. So, if any state
of DFA has two possible reductions, meaning it seem two complete productions
and it could reduce by either one then there's not enough information to decide
which reduction to perform and the parts won't be completely deterministic, and
this is called a reduced, reduced co nflict. So again, this happens if a
particular state has two separate items indicating two separate reductions. The
other possibility is that the final state of the DFA, after reading the stack
contents, might have An item that says to reduce and another item that says to
shift. And this is called a shift-reduce conflict. So in this case, there would
only be a conflict in a state where T was the next item in the input. But in that
situation, we wouldn't know whether to shift T onto the stack, or to reduce by X
goes to beta [sound]. Let's take a look at the DFA for recognizing viable prefixes
that we've been using for the last couple of ideas, and in fact this particular DFA
does have some conflicts. So, let's take a look at this state right here, here we
could either reduced by E goes to T you are in this state or if the next input is
a plus we could do a shift and. In, so in this particular situation, if the next
input is plus, we could either shift and use this item or we can reduce and use
that item. So this particular state has a shift reduced conflict. Now, that's not
the only conflict in this in this grammar, though. In this state here, we have a very
similar problem. Here we could shift if the next input is a times. Or we could
reduce by T goes to [inaudible]. And so this state also has a shift reduce
conflict. It turns out that it's not difficult to improve on LR0 parsing, and,
we'll present one such improvement in this video called SLR or simple LR parsing. And
this is going to improve on LR0 by adding some heuristics that will refine when we
shift and when we reduce, so that fewer states have conflicts. The modification to
LR0 parsing that gives us SLR parsing is really quite small. We just add one new
condition to the reduction case. So before, if we saw it, X goes to beta dot,
in the final state of our DFA, recall what that means. That means beta is on the top
of the stack, and it is viable And so it's fine to reduce. Now, We do have a little
bit more information. So, so notice that the automaton her e doesn't take any
advantage of what's coming up in the input. This is based entirely, this
decision here is based entirely on the stack contents. But it might be that it
doesn't make sense to reduce based on what the next input symbol is. And how can we
take advantage of that? Well, if you think about it, what's going to happen? We have
our stack contents. And, it ends in a beta, and now we're going to make a move
where we're going to replace that by X. Okay. And if the next input symbol is t,
so remember we have a vertical bar here and a t following, what does that mean?
Well, that means that x has to come before t in the derivation. Or in another words,
t is gonna follow x. And if t can't follow x, if t is a terminal symbol that can't
come after the non-terminal x than it makes no sense to do this reduction. So we
only do the reduction if t is in the follow of x. We just add that restriction
and that is the only change to the parsing algorithm. So if there are any conflicts
under these rules either shift reduce or reduce, reduce, then the grammar is not an
slr grammar. Just notice that these rules amount to a heuristic, for detecting the
handles. So, we take into account two pieces of information. The contents of the
stack, that's that the DFA, does for us, and it tells us what items are possible
when we get to the top of the stack, and also what's coming up in input, and we can
use that to define our reduction decisions. And for those grammars where
there are no conflicts, meaning there is a, there is a unique move, in every
possible state, under those rules. Then this heuristic is exact, you know, for,
for those grammars. And we just define those grammars to be the SLR grammars.
Let's consider how things have changed for our running example. The deterministic
automaton for recognizing the viable prefixes of the grammar we've been looking
at for several videos now. Recall that we had shift reduced conflicts under LR zero
rules in two states. So now let's look at this state first, the upper state. So
here, we 're going to shift if there's a plus in the input. That's what this item
tells us to do. It tells us there's if there's a plus, then the right move is to
shift. And so Now the question is, when are we going to reduce? Well we're only
going to reduce if the input is in the follow of E. And what is the follow of E?
We computed that a long time ago, but just to remind you remember that E here is the
original start symbol of the grammar so certainly dollar sign will wind up in the
follow of E. And the other possibility for the follow of E is close paren, because
here at this point in the grammar close paren comes after E. And that's the only
two possibilities. So what that says now, what that means is that, in this
particular state, we are going to reduce, if either we're out of input. Or if the
next I, the next, token in the input is a closed paren, and will shift if the next
token in the input is a plus. And in any other situation, we will report a parsing
error. And so there's no longer any shift reduced conflict in this state, and
there's always a unique move for every possible input. The situation is
similarly, similarly improved, for the other state. So here, we're going to shift
in there's a times in the input, and we're going to reduce if the input is in the
follow of T. And what is the follow of T? [sound]. Recall, We computed this again a
long time ago and I just happen to know what it is. And so I'll just tell you.
Well it included everything in the follow of e. So a dollar sign in close paren are
in the follow of T. But also, a plus is in the follow of T because of this usage over
here in the grammar where plus appears really after T. But those are the only
things in the follow of T. And so now we're going to reduce, only if we're out
of input or if the next input item is a close paren or a plus and there's also a
no shift reduce, no longer any shift reduce conflict in this state. And so this
grammar, is an SLR1 grammar. Now many grammars are not SLR. To emphasize that
SLR is an improvement on LR0 but it 's still, not a really very general class of
grammars. So All ambiguous grammars for example are not SLR. We can improve a
little bit on the SLR situation. We can make SLR parsers even more grammarous, by
using precedence declarations to tell it how to resolve conflicts. So let's revert
to the most natural and also most ambiguous grammar for plus and times over
the integers, and we've looked at this grammar before. If you build the DFA for
this grammar, if you go through and build the DFA for the viable prefix of this
grammar, you will discover that there is a state. That has the following two items in
it, one says that if we see E times E that we have seen E times E on a stack, and
that we can now reduce by ecos E times E. The other one will say that if there's a
plus coming up in the input we should shift. And notice that this is exactly the
question. Of whether, times has higher precedence than plus. When you're in this
situation, should you. Reduce, thereby grouping the two E's together here,
Grouping the multiplication operation first. Or should you shift the plus, in
which case you'll be working on that for a sentence at the top of the stack. So, in
this situation, the declaration times has higher precedence than plus resolves the
conflict in favor of the reduction. So we would not do the shift, and we would wind
up with no shift-reduce conflict. Note that the term precedence declaration is
actually quite misleading. These declarations don't define precedence. They
don't. Do that directly at all. What they really define are conflict resolution.
They say, make this move instead of that move. It happens that in this particular
case. Because we're dealing with a national grammar, simple grammar for plus
and times that the conflict resolution has exactly the effect of enforcing the
precedence declaration that we want. But in more complicated grammars where there
are more interactions between various pieces of the grammar, these declarations
might not do what you expect in terms of enforcing precedence, fortuna tely, you
can always print out the automaton. The tools provide, Usually a way for you to
inspect the parsing automaton. And then you can see exactly how, the conflicts are
being resolved, and whether those are the resolutions that you had intended. And I
recommend when you're building parsers, especially if it's a, a fairly complex
parser, that you do examine the parsing automaton to make sure that it's doing
what you expect. So now we're ready to give the algorithm for SLR parsing. So
[inaudible] automaton, our parsing automaton that recognizes viable prefixes.
The initial configuration is going to be with the vertical bar all the way to the
left so the stack is empty. This is our full input and we [inaudible] dollar to
indicate the end of the input. And now we're going to repeat until the
configuration has just the start symbol on the stack, and dollar in the input.
Meaning all the input is gone and we've reduced the entire input to the start
symbol. So. An [inaudible] configuration will be written as alpha-omega; where
alpha is the contents of the stack and omega is the remaining input, and what
we're going to do is we're going to run M, run the machine on the current stack alpha
and if M rejects alpha, if M says that alpha is not a viable prefix, then we're
going to report a parsing error. We're gonna stop right there. Now, if M accepts
alpha, and it accepts it in a state, if it ends in a state with items I, then we're
gonna look at the next input, call that A, and what are we going to do? Well, we're
going to shift. Yes, there's an item. In I that says, it would be okay to see the
terminal A. Next. Okay? So that's just our shift move. And then we're going to reduce
if there's a reduction item, in the in the set of valid items. And the next input can
follow the non-terminal on the left hand side. So these are just the two rules that
we discussed before. And then we'll report a parsing error if neither of these
applies. Okay, now one interesting thing about this algorithm, if you read it
carefully and you th ink about it for awhile. You'll realize that this step is
actually not needed, that we don't need to check here For whether M accepts the
stack, or not. Because this staff down here, where we report a parsing error, if
neither of these steps applies, this already implies that we will never form an
invalid stack, That our, their stacks will always be viable. The parsing errors will
be caught at this line, and we won't pollute the stack with symbols that can't
possibly result in viable prefixes. So in fact, this error check here, is not
needed, M is always going to accept the stack. If there are any conflicts in the
last step, meaning, it's not clear whether to shift or reduce in some state for some,
input symbol, then the grammar is not, SLRK. And K, again, is the amount of look
ahead. In practice, we just use one token of look ahead, So typically, just looking
at the next token in the input stream.