Welcome back, In this video, we're going to do an extended example of SLR parsing.
To review, here is the parsing automaton for the grammar that we've been looking at
in the last couple of videos. And this is just the deterministic version of the, non
deterministic automaton we built last time. And I've just gone through and
numbered all of the states. So let's take a look at what happens when we parse the
input [inaudible] times [inaudible]. And just to review, we've appended dollar sign
here to the end, to indicate where the end of the input occurs. That's just an end of
input marker. And because this is the beginning of the parse we haven't seen any
input yet. And so the vertical bar is all the way at the left hand side of the
input. So the machine begins in state one, and there's nothing on the stack. The
vertical bar is all the way to the left again, so the stack is empty. So it just
terminates in state one. And these are the possible items, that are valid for the
initial state of the parser. So among those items, we see that there are two
that tell us that it's okay to shift an integer in this state. And, of course, the
first input is an integer, and so there are no reduced moves. All the other items
in here also have their jobs all the way at the left side of the item, so there's
no possible reduced move in this state. The only thing we could possibly do is
shift, and it's okay to shift an integer. So to summarize, on the initial
configuration of the parser, the DFA halts in state one, it never even gets out of
state one, so it starts there and ends there without even reading any input
because the stack is empty and the action that, that state tells us to do is to
shift. So that leads us in the following state, there's an int on the stack and we
have a times coming up on the input. So, what happens in that situation? Well, we
begin. The automaton is going to read the stack. So, starting from the bottom of the
stack, we're in the start state. And then we read an int, there's an int on the
stack, and we win d up in this state. And what does this state tell us we can do?
Well, it tells us one possibility is to reduce by T goes to int. But again, we
will only do that, if the following input is in the follow of T, And times, which is
the next input item, is not in the follow of T. So times is not in the follow. Of T
and so reducing here is not a possibility. That leaves only the other item to
consider and here we see that this item says we can the time. So if the times the
next thing in input, which it is, it's okay to shift. So the DFA halts in state
three and because there's a times in the input the move is to shift. And that puts
us into this configuration where we have int and times on the stack. Times is at
the top of the stack, int is below it and we have an int coming up in the input. So
what happens now, again, the DFA is going to read the entire stack. So beginning at
the bottom of the stack, the first thing it sees is an int, and it moves to that
state. And then it sees a times, and so it moves to this state. And now, in this
particular state, what are the possibilities? Well, we can see, first of
all, that there are no reduced moves. There are no items with the dot all the
way at the right end. So the only possibility is a, is a shift. And we could
shift if the upcoming input's a open paren, which it's not. More usefully, we
could shift if the upcoming input is an [inaudible], which is exactly what we see.
So, the DFA terminates in state eleven, and the move in that state is to shift.
And that puts us into this state, where we have int times int on the stack, and we
are out of input. We are at the end of the input. So let's see what happens on the
stack int times int. The automaton reads it int times int and it winds up back in
state three. Sa3 tells us that we can shift if the, next input item is a times
and which it is not. Or we can reduce, if whatever the next. Is in the next input is
in the follow of T. And in fact dollar is in, the follow of T. So, in, the end of
the input come after a T on the stack. And that means it's fine to reduce by T goes
to int. So, once we do that, once we do the reduction T goes to int, we wind up in
the state times T. That's our stack contents and of course we're still at the
end of the input. So once again the DFA is going to read the entire stack contents
from the bottom to the top. First it reads the int at the bottom of the stack, then
it sees the times. And then it finally reads the t at the top of the stack. And
it winds up in a new state, state four. And the interesting thing about this
particular step is that the DFA took a different path through the state graph
than it did the previous time. And that's because the stack contents changed. We
didn't just add stuff to the stack, and so we didn't extend the previous path. We
actually replaced some symbols or a symbol on the stack with a new symbol, in this
case, the non-terminal T and that caused the DFA to take a different path. Now what
does this item in state four tell us to do? Well it says that we can reduce by T
goes to N times T if whatever. Follows in the input is in the follow of T. And, once
again, dollar is in the follow of T. And so we'll do that reduction, and now we're
left with the static contents just consisting of T. And, of course we're
still at the end of the input. And let's see what happens now. So now of course the
contents of the stack have changed even more radically and so the DFA just goes
off in a completely different direction. It reads T winds up in this state and this
state says we can either shift a plus if there's a plus in the input. And again,
there's no more input. Or we can reduce by E goes to T if dollar, if the end of the
input is in the follow of E, Which it is. And so the reduction will be the one that
we do. And now we have, this stack contents, consisting only of E. Let's see
what happens in that situation. Now we make a transition to this state, state
two. And we only have one item, S prime goes to E dot. And so this is a reduced
move. And again, dollar is in the follow of S prime, ' cause that is the start
symbol. And since that is the start symbol, we accept at this point. So once
we get to that item as our, reduce move, we know that the input has been
successfully parsed.