At this point we know enough to state the second important
fact about bottom- up parsing. So in shift reduce parsing handles appear
only at the top of the stack Never in sight Side, and in fact this is what justifies
using a stack because that string to the left of our focus point we know
that all the action will take place immediately to the left of the focus point.
We won't have to dive down to the string to look at its [inaudible] and therefore
the stack will be sufficient. So here's an informal proof, that handles only
appear at the top of the stack. And this is by induction on the number of reduce
moves. So this is true initially because the stack is empty. And so, we don't,
you know, so the only possible reduction is at the top of the stack if there's
an epsilon move, to make. And immediately after we reduce, the right most
non terminal is going to be on top of the stack. So immediately after we perform
a reduction, we have a, our stack, and then we have a, non terminal. And then our
vertical bar, And this is the right most non terminal. And since this is the right
most derivation that means that the next handle has to be somewhere to the right. The
next handle has to be, It has to include something that, and you know possibly
include some of this stuff. But it's either right here at the current focus
point, or it's to the right, Because we can't be doing any reductions to the left
of the rightmost non-terminal. And so it's gonna require a sequence of shift moves
to reach the next handle. So once we have this non-terminal on top of the stack,
it is by definition the rightmost non-terminal, and so the next handle has to
be somewhere to the right of that. Therefore in shift reduce parsing handles
always appear at the top of the stack. Handles are never to the left of the right
most knot terminal and this is why shift and reduce moves are sufficient. The shift
move only moves the vertical part to the right because we never need to move it left.
And bottom of parsing algorithms are based on recognizing handles. So as we saw
in the example at the beginning of this video. Just because you have a right hand
side on top of the stack that doesn't mean that it's a handle. And so we need to be smarter
about where we perform our