In this video we're going to talk about type checking in cool. Thus far, we've
seen two examples of formal notation used to specify parts of a compiler. Regular
expressions were used in lexical analysis, and context free grammars which we used in
parsing. It turns out that there's another formalism which has gained widespread
acceptance in type checking, and that's logical rules of inference. If-else rules
are logical statements that have the form; if some hypothesis is true then some
conclusion is true. So, if-else rules are implication statements that some
hypothesis implies some conclusion And in the particular case of type checking an
example or typical kind of reasoning that we see in type checking is that if a
couple of expressions have certain types then some other expression is guaranteed
to have a certain type. And so clearly that the type checking statement here is
an example of an inference rule. An inference rule notation is just a compact
way of encoding these kinds of if then statements. Now if you haven't seen this
notation before, it will be unfamiliar, but actually it's quite easy to read with
practice And we'll start with a very simple system and gradually add features.
So we'll use a logical conjunction for the English word and, and implication for the
English word if and then. And now, one special thing, the string x colon t is
read that x has type t. So this is logical assertion saying that x has a particular
type. So now consider the following very simple type rule. If E one has type int,
and E two has type int, then E one plus E two also has type int. And we could just
take the definitions we gave on the previous slide and just gradually reduce
this to a mathematical statement. So, for example, we can replace the if then with
an implication. And we can replace the word and with a conjunction. And now we
just have these has type statements, alright? And we had a notation for that,
and we wind up with this purely mathematical statement that, which says
exactly the same thing. That if E1 has type int and E2 has type int, that implies
that E1 + E2 has type int. And notice that, that statement that we just wrote
out is a special case of an inference rule. It's a bunch of hypothesis conjoined
together and implies some conclusion. The traditional notation for inference rules
is given here. The hypotheses are written about the horizontal line, and the
conclusion is written below. And it means exactly the same thing as what we had on
the previous slide. Mainly that if all the things above the horizontal line are true.
These are all the hypotheses, then the thing below. The horizontal line can be
concluded to be true. And there's one piece of new notation here. This is the
turnstiles that are used for the hypotheses and the conclusion. And the
turnstile is read, it is provable that. And what this means is that we're just
going to say explicitly. That something is provable in the system of rules that we're
defining. So the way you would read this is that if it's provable that all these
hypotheses are true. So, if it's provable the first hypothesis is true, all the
middle hypotheses, and if it's improvable, if it's provable the last hypothesis is
true. Then it is provable that the conclusion is true And cool type rules are
going to have. The following kinds of hypothesis and conclusions we're going to
prove, within the system, that some expression has a particular type. So with
those definitions out of the way we actually have enough to write at least a
few simple type rules. So, if I integer literally if it's an integer class
interfering in my program then this rules says it is provable that I has type ENT.
So every integer constant has type ENT. And here's the rule for add written out
now in the [inaudible] rule notation. If it's provable then that E1 has type int
and is provable that E2 has type ENT. Then it is provable that E1 plus E2 has type
ENT. So notice that these rules give templates for describing how to type
integers and expressions. The rule for integer constants just use a generic
integer i. It didn't give a separate rule for every possible integer, and the rule
for plus used expressions e one and e two. It didn't tell you what particular
expressions they were. It just said give me any expression e one, any expressions e
one and e two that have type int. And so we can plug any expressions we want in
that satisfy the hypotheses, and then we can produce a complete typing for actual
expressions. So as a concrete example, let's show that one plus two has type ent.
So we want to type the expression one plus two, and since we know the rule for add
that means we need to construct a proof of the type of the number one, and a proof of
the type of the number two. And we have a rule for dealing with integer classes,
mainly we can prove because one is an integer class that has type ent, and we
can prove that two is type ent, and then now we have the two hypothesis we need for
the sum expression and we can prove that one plus two has type ent. So, an
important property of any reasonable type system is that it be sound. And sound is
here is a correctness condition. What we want is whatever the type system can prove
that some expression has the type systems has a particular type T. The if I actually
run that program. If I take E and I execute it on the computer the value that
it returns, the value that comes after running E in fact has the type predicted
by the type system. So, if the type system It is able to give types of things that
actually reflect what kind of value you get when you run the program then we say
that the type system is sound. Now clearly we only want sound rules but some sound
rules are actually quite a bit better than others, so for example. If I have an
integer literal And I want to give it a type, while we, we, I showed you the best
possible rule before where we said that [inaudible] has type [inaudible] But it
would also be correct, just not very precise to say that has [inaudible] has
type object. Certainly if I evaluate an integer I will get back an object because
every integer in , is also an object But this isn't all that useful because now I
can't do any of the integer operations And so there are lots of different sound
rules, there's not just one unique rule for any given [inaudible] expression that
will be sound, but some of them are better than others, and in the case of integer
literals the one we really want. Literal has type it because that is the most
specific type that we can give to that type of program.