In this video we're going to talk about simple tables an important data structure
in many filers before we talk about what a simple table is I want to talk about a
generic algorithm that we're going to be seeing instances of over and over again
for the rest of the course. So, a lot of semantic analysis and in fact, a lot of
code generation can be expressed as a recursive descent of an abstract syntax
tree. And the basic idea is that in each step we do the following three things:
we're always processing a particular node in the tree, so if I draw a picture of the
abstract syntax tree it might have a node and some sub-trees hanging off of it. And
we may do some processing of the node before we do anything else. We arrive at
the node say from the parents, we come to here for the parent, we do some processing
in the node and I'm just indicating that by coloring it blue to indicate that we
did something here. And then we go off and we process the children. Okay. And after
we process the children, after we come back to the node, we do something else. We
may do some post processing of the node, and then we return. And of course, at the
same time, when we've gone off and processed the children, then we're
processing all their nodes in the same pre imposed fashion, so they're getting the
same treatment, with some stuff being done before each node is touched, and some
stuff being done after all their children have been processed. Okay. And. There are
many, many examples of this kind of an algorithm. This is called a recursive
descent traversal of a tree. There are some instances in which we'll only process
each note before we process the children. Some where we only process each note after
we process all the children. Some where we do both as illustrated here in this little
diagram And returning to the main topic of this particular video. When we're
performing semantic analysis on a portion of the abstract syntax tree, we're going
to know, need to know which identifiers are defined. Which identifiers are in
scope? An exam ple of this kind of recursive descent strategy is how we can
process let bindings to track the set of variables that are in the scope. So we
have our let node in the fx syntax tree and in one sub tree we have the
initialization, and in the other sub tree we have e, the body of the let, and then
this is a let for some particular variable, and let's just write that
variable inside the parent node here. And so, when we begin processing of this O,
just imagine that we're coming from above. So we're doing this. We're processing the
abstract syntax tree recursively. And so we reach this point from some parent and.
There's going to be a set of symbols that are currently in scope. That, that's some
data structure that lives off to the side, And in fact, that's going to be our symbol
table And what is going to happen here? Well, the first we're going to have to do
is we're going to have to process, the initializer. We're going to need to know
whether that's, what, whatever function we're doing on this, like type checking or
whatever. We might get on and process that first And we'll pass the symbol table in.
Okay. And then we're going to process the body of the let But when we do that we're
going to pass in a set of symbols that are in scope. But now also X is now going to
be in scope. So X is going to be added before we process E to the set of symbols.
And then when we return from some expression E it's going to be removed. So,
it'll restore the symbol table to its previous state. So that after we leave
this sub tree of the abstract syntax tree, we only have the same set of symbols to
find that we had before we entered it, So in the terminology of the three part
algorithm For recursive descent that we had on the first slide. What are we doing
here? Well, before we process E we are going to add the definition of X to our
list of current definitions. Already any other definition of X that might have been
visible outside of that expression. Then we are going to recurse we going to
process all. Of the abstract syntax tree no des in the body of the [inaudible],
inside of E, and after we finish processing E, we are gonna remove the
definition of X and restore whatever old definition of X we had. And a symbol table
is just a data structure that accomplishes these things. It tracks the current
bindings of identifiers at each point in the abstract syntax tree. For a very
simple, simple table, we could just use a stack, and it would have just say the
following three operations, we could add a symbol. To the symbol table and that will
just push the symbol, push the variable onto the stack and whatever other
information we want, like its type. We'll have a find symbol operation that will
look up the current definition for a symbol. And that can be done by simply
searching the, the stack. Starting from the top for the first occurrence of the
variable name, And this will automatically take care of the hiding of all
definitions. So, for example, If we have a stack, let's say has X, Y and Z on it and
then we come into a scope that introduces a new Y. Y on top and now if we search the
stack we find this y first effectively hiding the old definition of y and then.
When we leave a scope we can remove a symbol simple popping a stack. We'll just
pop the current variable off of this stack. That will get rid of the most
recent definition. And, and leave the stack, leave the set of definitions in the
same state it was before we entered the node at all. So, this example, if we left
the scope where the Y is defined and that was popped off the stack, So that was
gone. Now, when we search for Y we'll find the outer definition. The one that was
defined outside of that inner scope, So this simple symbol table works well for
let, because the symbols rate at one at a time, and because declarations are
perfectly nested. And in fact, the fact that declarations were perfectly nested is
really the whole reason that we can use a stack/ So, take a look at this little
example, let's say we have three nested lets, and here I'm not showing the
initializers in the less sub trees, and they, they don't matter, for what I want
to illustrate. So if you think about it as we walk from the root here down to the
inner bindings, we're pushing things on the stack, we'll push things on the stack
in the order X, Y, and then Z. And then as we leave, after we've processed this sub
tree, and we're leaving it, walking back out, we're going to encounter these left
scopes in exactly the reverse order. And popping them off the stack is exactly the
order in which we want to remove them, and that's why a stack works well. So
Structure works fine for lets, but for some other constructs it's not quite as
good as it could be so for example consider the following piece of code.
Illegal piece of code I should add. Let's say we're declaring a method, and it has
two arguments named X. Now, that's not legal but in order to detect that it's not
legal you. Why is it not legal? It's not legal cause they're both defined in the
same scope. So, Functions, or methods, have the property that they introduce
multiple names at once into the same scope. And it's not quite so easy, to use
a stack, where we only add one thing at a time, or one name at a time, to model
simultaneous definition in a scope. So this problem is easily solved with just a
slightly fancier simple table. Here is the revised interface now with five methods
instead of three. The biggest change is that now we have explicit enter and exit
scope functions, and so these functions start in the nested scope and exit the
current scope. And the way you think about this is that our new structure is a stack
of scopes, so [inaudible] is the entire scope and the inner scope. Is, are all the
variables that are defined at the same level, within that single scope. So just
like before, we have a find symbol operation that will look up a variable
name, and it will return the current definition, or null if there is no
definition in any scope that's currently available. We'll have an add symbol
Operation that adds a new symbol to the table, and adds it in the curren t scope,
so whatever, scope is at the top of our scope stack. And then one more new
operation, check scope. Will return true if X is already defined in the current
scope, So this, just to be clear what this does, this returns true if X is defined in
exactly the top scope. It doesn't return true unless, X is defined in the scope at
the very, very top of the stack. And this allows you to check for double
definitions, So, for example, in the, code that I had before on the previous slide,
if we had two declarations of X. How would we check this? Well, we would add X to the
symbol table, in the current scope. And then we would ask, well, is X already
defined in this scope for the second one? And this interface would be return true,
and we would know to raise an error saying that X, had been multiply defined.
Finally, let me just add that this is the simple table interface or something very
close to this is the simple table interface that is supplied with the cool
project. And there's already implementation of this interface provided
if you don't want to write your own. So let's wrap up this video by talking a
little bit about class names, which behave quite differently from the variables
introduced in let bindings and in function parameters. In particular class names can
be used before they are defined, as we discussed a few videos ago. And what that
means is that we can't check class names, in a single pass. We can't just walk over
the program once. And check that every class that is used is defined because we
don't know that we've seen all the definitions of the classes until we reach
the very end of the program. And so there is a solution to this we have to make two
passes over the program. In the first pass we gather all the class definitions, we go
through and we find every place where a class is defined, record all of those
names. And in the second pass we go through and look at the bodies of the
classes and make sure they only use classes that were defined. And the lesson
here, this is actually not complicated to implement I think it's quite clear. Should
be quite clear how this will work. But the message here is that semantic analysis is
going to require multiple passes, and probably more than two. And, in fact, you
should not be afraid when structuring your compiler to add lots and lots of simple
passes if that makes your life easier, so it's better to break something up into
three or four simple passes rather than to have one very, very complicated pass where
all the code is entangled. I think you'll find it much easier to debug your
compilers if you're willing to make multiple passes over the input.