Welcome back. In this video, we're going to give a very brief introduction, an
overview, of what we're going to be talking about in semantic analysis. Let's
take a moment to review where we are in our discussion with compilers. So we
talked about lexical analysis, and from the point of view of enforcing the
language definition the main job that lexical analyses does is detect input
[inaudible] preemptive symbols that aren't part of our language. The next step is
parsing. We finished talking about that too. And, again, from the point of view of
trying to determine whether a program is well-formed or not, or whether it's a
valid program, the job of parsing is to detect all the sentences in the language
that are ill-formed, or that don't have a parse string. And finally What we're going
to talk about now, what's going to occupy us for a while is semantic analysis. And
this is the last of what are called the front end phases. So if you think of
lexical analysis, parsing, and semantic analysis as filters that progressively
reject more and more input strings until finally you're left after all three phases
have run with only valid programs to compile, well semantic analysis is the
last line of defense. It's the last one in that pipeline and its job is to catch all
potential remaining errors in a program. Now you might ask yourself, why do we even
need a separate semantic analysis phase? And the answer to that's very simple,
There are, there are some features of programming languages, some kinds of
mistakes you can make that parsings simply can't catch. Parsing we'll use in context
free grammars is not expressive enough to describe everything that we're interested
in, in a language definition. So, some of these language constructs are not context
free. And the situation here is very, very similar to what it was when we switched
from lexical analysis to parsing. Just like not everything could be done with a
finite [inaudible]. And we wanted to have something more. Our context free grammar
to describe additional features of our programming languages [inaudible] Grammars
by themselves are also not enough, and there some additional features beyond
those that can't be easily expressed using context free constructs. So what does
semantic analysis actually do? In a case of cool C, it does checks of many
different kinds, and that's pretty typical. So here's a list of six classes
of checks that are done by Cool C, and let's just run through them quickly. First
we want to check that all identifiers are declared, and we also have to check that
any scope restrictions on those identifiers are observed. Cool C compiler
has to do type checking, and this is actually a major function of the semantic
analyzer in Cool. There are a number of restrictions that come from the object
oriented nature of Cool. We have to check that the inheritance relationships between
classes make sense. We don't want classes to be redefined; we only want one class
definition per class. Similarly methods should only be defined once within a
class. Cool has a number of reserved identifiers and we have to be careful that
those aren't misused. And this is pretty typical; lots of languages have some
reserved identifiers with special rules that have to be followed for those
identifiers. And, actually this list is not even complete. There are a number of
other restrictions. And we'll be talking about all of those in future videos. The
main message here is that its medic analyzer needs to do quite a few different
kinds of checks. These checks will vary with the language. The kinds of checks
that cool C does are pretty typical of statically typed checked object oriented
languages. But other families of languages will have different kinds of checks.