Welcome back. In this video we're gonna begin our discussion of semantic analysis
with the topic of scope. The motivating problem for talking about scope is that we
want to be able to match identifier declarations with the uses of those
identifiers. We need to know which variable we're talking about when we see
variable X if variable X might have more than one definition in the program. And
this is an important aesthetic analysis step in most programming languages,
including, [inaudible]. So here are a couple of examples taken from cool. This
definition Y, this declaration Y that it's a string will be matched with this used
and so we'll know at this point here that Y is supposed to be a string and you'll
get some kind of an air for a compiler because you're trying to add a string and
a number. In the second example Here's a declaration of Y And then in the body of
the [inaudible] we, we don't see any use of Y And that, by itself is not an error.
It's perfectly fine to declare a variable that you don't use. Although you could
imagine generating a warning for that, that doesn't actually cause the program to
behave badly, But instead what we see here is a use of X and there's no matching
definitions. So the question is where is the definition of X? We can't see it And
if there is no outer definition of X then we'll get and undefined or undeclared
variable error here at this point. So these two examples illustrate the idea of
scope. The scope of an identifier is that portion of a program in which the
identifier is accessible. And just know that the same identifier may refer to
different things and different parts of the program. And different scopes for the
same name can't overlap. So whenever the variable x, for example, means, it can
only refer to one thing in an given part of the program. And identifiers can have
restricted scope. There are lots of examples, I'm sure you're familiar with
them, of identifiers whose scope is less than the entire program. Most programming
languages today have what is called static s cope. And cool is an example of a
statically scoped language. The characteristic of static scoping is that
the scope of the variable depends only on the program text, not on any kind of
runtime behavior. So what the program actually does at runtime doesn't matter.
The scope is defined purely syntactically from the way you wrote the program. Now it
may come as a surprise that there is any alternative to static scoping. In fact,
probably every language that you have used up to now has had static scoping But there
are a few languages that are, what are called, dynamically scoped. And for a long
time actually there was an argument about whether static scoping was better than
dynamic scoping. Although today, I think, it is pretty clear that static scoping
camp has, has won this discussion But historically, at least, LISP was an
example of a dynamically scoped language. And it has switched, in the meantime. This
is actually a long time ago now that it changed, to static scoping. Another
language which is now mostly of historical interest, it isn't really used anymore,
called Snowball, also had, dynamic scoping. And the characteristic of dynamic
scoping is that the scope of a variable depends on the execution behavior of the
program. So let's take a look at an example of [inaudible]. So, here we have
some [inaudible] code, and, a couple of different declarations of X, and also,
some different uses of X. Let me erase these. [inaudible] underline so I can use
the color to indicate, binding. So, let's take a look at this definition. The
question is which of these uses of x, we have three uses of x, actually refer to
that definition. So, it is, in fact, these two, the ones that are outside of the
inner let. These actually refer to this definition. So, here if you refer to x,
you get the value zero But, this other definition here. The inner definition of
x, is, is used by this use of x. So this use of x, gets this va-, this meaning of
x, which in this case, returns the value one. And what's going on here is that
we're using the most closely, what's called the most closely nested rule. So a
variable binds to the definition that is most closely enclosing it of the same
name. So this x the closest enclosing definition of x is this one, but for these
two x's, the closest and only enclosing definition of x is this outer one. So in
dynamically scoped language, a variable would refer to the closest binding in the
execution of the program, meaning the most recent binding of the variables, so here's
an example, let's say we have a function G, and G defines a variable A, and here's
it initialized say to four, and then it calls another function Another function
that isn't in the same syntactic scope. So here I've written F right next to G but
actually F could be in some completely other part of the code and F refers to A.
And the question is, what is the value of A here? Well. If it's if we dynamically
scoped then it's going to be the value that was defined in G and here F of X will
actually return four, that will be the result of this call because this reference
to A. We'll refer to this binding or this definition of A and G. And, we can't say
much more about how dynamics, how dynamics scope works until we talk in a little more
detail about how languages are implemented. So we'll talk about dynamic
scope again a little later on in the course. In Cool, identifier bindings are
introduced by a variety of mechanisms. Now there are class declarations, which
introduce class names. Method definitions, which introduce method names, And then
there is several different ways to introduce object, object identifiers. And
these are the [inaudible] expressions, [inaudible] parameters of functions,
attribute definitions in classes, and finally in the branches of case
expressions. It's important to understand that not all identifiers follow the most
closely nested rule that we outlined before. So for example a rather, rather
large exception to this rule is class definitions in Cool. So class definitions
cannot be nested. And in fact they are globally visibl e throughout the program.
And what does that mean? That means that a class name is defined everywhere If it's
defined anywhere in the program, that class name is available for use anywhere
in the program or everywhere in the program. And in particular, a class name
can be used before it is defined. So as an example, take a look at this fragment of
cool code here. And here we see that in class foo, we declare y to be of type var
and then later on we declare class var. This is perfectly fine cool code. The fact
that var is used before it is defined has no effect on whether the program is
correct. This is a completely legal cool code Similarly with attribute names.
Attribute names are global within the class in which they are defined, so, I,
that means they can be used again before they are defined. So for example, I can
define a class foo, and I can define a method that uses attribute a, and then
later on, only later on, do I define what attribute a is, and that is perfectly
legal. So normally The list attribute definitions before method definitions, but
that's not required. A actually the method and attributory definitions can come in
any order we like, within a class, and in-particular an attribute can be used
before it is defined. Finally method names have quite complex rules. For example, a
method doesn't have to be defined in the class in which it is used. It could just
be defined in some pairing class. And also methods can be redefined. So it's possible
to what's called overwriting of a method and give a method a new definition Even
though it has been defined before. We don't actually have the language yet to
talk about these rules with any precision but we'll be going into this in future videos.