Now we can give a type-checking role for if-then-else. So
the first thing to know is about if-then-else expressions is that they do not
affect the environment, and if-then-else neither introduces nor removes
any variables from the environment, so all the sub-expressions are
typed in the same environment as the entire expression. Now, the predicate of the
FNL30, well that should have type [inaudible]. Because that's our decision whether
we're going to take the true branch or the false branch, But then the two
branches can have different types. E1 just has to have some type T1, and E2 just
has to have some type T2. So notice again what this is sayi ng. This is just saying
that E1 and E2 do have a type check. They have to be type correct but we don't care
what the type is. The type can be anything. And then the type of the entire
expression is just going to be the least upper bound of T1 and T2. Because that's going
to be the best Estimate we can give to the final type of the expression given
that the truth branch might return T one something of type T one. And the false branch
might return something of type T two. The rule for case expression is the most
complex one we've seen so far. But really it's a glorified if then L's. And it's
relatively easy to understand if we just pull it apart. So, so let's begin by
reminding ourselves of what case does. First of all it looks at E0. It evaluates
E0 and then it looks at the runtime type of E0. So, so it takes the dynamic class of
E0 and then it looks at the first branch. >> Let's do that. >> And what is it
going to do? It's going to compare the type of these [inaudible] at run time to the
type t one, and if t one is super type. Of the run time type of E O And in fact,
it is the smallest of all the possible branches. It's the smallest super
type of all the possible branches. Then it's going to pick this branch. It's going
to bind X1 to the value. It's going to give it the type T1. So combine X1 to the
value of E O. It's going to retype it as. Type T one and it's going to evaluate E one.
So you can see in one sense it's a, it's a glorified if then else, we're just
picking the best matching branch, the one that, whose type, declared type, is, most
closely matches the runtime type of E zero. And then we're going to execute that
branch with the variable that's named in that branch bound to the type of E zero. So
let's see how the typing works out. So first we type check E0 and we can some type
T0, and now what's going to happen well if we select. The branch, The first branch,
Well, then, we're going to take the environment and we're going to extend
it with the new variable x one which is going to have type t one. And so we only take
this branch, remember, if the runtime type of e zero matches t one, most closely
among all the branches, but if we do take it, then we're going to execute, execute e
one in this environment and we'll get back something of some type, t one prime, and similarly
for all the other branches until finally the last branch, which is exactly
the same as the first one, just with the letter n replacing the number one. And so
since we don't know which brain to match at one time, it could be any of the branches
that actually executes and therefore the type of the entire expression
is just going to be least upper bound over all of the types a, of the various
branches, and here I've just extendedly super bound from a binding area
of the operation a, to an in area operation a, that should be clear enough,
we're just going to take the least upper bound to all of these types.