Welcome back, in this video we're going to have an introductions to types. So a very
basic question to ask is what is a type anyway. And this question is worth asking
because the notion of type, what a type is, does vary from programming language to
programming language. Now roughly speaking the consensus is that a type is a set of
values, and also, perhaps more importantly, a set of operations that are
unique to those values, a set of operations that are defined on those
values. So, for example, if I looked at the type of integers, there are some
operations that you can do on integers. You can do things like, you can add. And
you can subtract integers and you can compare integers whether they are greater
than or equal or less than these operations are you know about numbers and
then there are operations on strings And strings are a different type. They have.
Operations like incantation and testing whether a string is, is an empty string or
not And the other various variety of functions that are defined on strings. And
the important thing that these operations are different from the operations defined
on integers and we don't want to mix them up. It would be bad if we started doing
string operations on integers for example. We would just get nonsense. So, in modern
programming languages types are expressed in a number of different ways. In object
orient languages. Often we see classes being the notion of type. So, [inaudible]
in cool, the class names are the types, they're all, the, with one exception,
called self type. The class names are exactly the types. And I just wanted to
point out that this need not be the case. It happens that it's often convenient in
[inaudible] Victorian languages to equate classes and types. But there are other
designs that, where the classes are not the only kinds of types, or whether
they're. And in some languages, [inaudible] where there's no notion of
class, the types are completely different things. So, classes and types are really
two different things that happen, to be identif ied in a lot of object oriented
designs. And I just want you to be aware that that's not necessarily the only way
to do it. So consider the assembly language fragment add R1 R2 R3 and what
does this actually do. Well it takes the contents of register R2 and the contents
of register R3 it adds them together, and it puts the results in register R1. And
the question is, what are the types of R1 R2 and R3 And you might hope that they're
integers but in fact this is a, this is a trick question Because at the assembly
language level I can't tell. There's nothing that prevents R1, R2, and R3 from
having arbitrary types. They could be, they could be representatives of any kind
of type and because they're just a bunch of registers with zero and 1's in them the
add operation will be happy to take them and add them up even if it doesn't make
sense And produce a bit pattern that then stores into R1. So, to make this a little
clear perhaps it's useful to think about a, a certain operations that are legal for
values of each type. So for example, it make perfect example to add two integers,
if I have two bit patterns that represent integers, then when I sum them up I would
get a bit pattern that represents the sum of those two integers. But on the other
hand, if I take a function pointer and integer and I add them together, I really
don't get anything. Okay this is another the function pointer is a bit pattern. The
imaginer s a bit pattern I can take those two bit patterns. I could run them through
and I do get out a new set of bits. But there's no useful interpretation of that
results. The resulting things I get doesn't mean anything, but the problem is
that these both have the same assembly language implementation. Okay, nothing at
the assembly language level, these two operations look exactly the same. So I
can't tell at the assembly language level, which one of these I'm doing. If I want
there to be types, if I want to make sure that I only do operations on the correct,
that I only do certain operations on, on their correc t types, then I need some
sort of type description, some sort of type system to enforce those distinctions.
Perhaps I'm belaboring this point, but I think it's important, so one more time. A
languages type system specifies which operations are valid for which types. Then
the goal for type checking is to ensure that operations are used only, only with
the correct types. And by doing this, type checking enforces the intended
interpretation of values because nothing else is going to check. Once we get to the
machine code level, it's all just a lot of 0's and 1's, and the machine will be happy
to do whatever operations we tell it to on those 0's and 1's, whether or not those
operations make sense. So the purpose of type systems is to enforce the intended
interpretations of those bit patterns and make sure that if I have a bit pattern for
integers that I don't do any non-integer operations on that and get something that
is meaningless. Today, programming languages fall into three different
categories with respect to how they treat types. There are the statically types
languages, where all, or almost all, of the checking of types is done as part of
compilation, and Cool is one of these And other languages that you've probably seen,
like C and Java, are also statically typed. Then there are the dynamically
typed languages, where almost all of the checking of types is done as part of
program execution. And the Lisp family of languages, like Scheme and Lisp itself,
are in this category, as are languages like Python And pearl So you've probably
used, or heard of, at least, some of those languages And finally there are the
un-typed languages where no type checking is done at all, either at compile time or
at run time. And this is basically what machine code does. So machine code has no
notion of types and it forces no extraction boundaries, when it executes.
For decades there has been debate about the relative merits of static versus
dynamic typing and without taking sides let me lay out for you what the various
proponents on each side say. So, the people who believe in static typing say,
that static checking catches many programming errors in compile time and it
also avoids the overhead of runtime type checks. If I hooked on all the type
checking and compiled time well I don't have to check the types at runtime. I
don't have to check when I go do an operation that the arguments are of the
correct type because I already that check once and for all in compile time. And
these things are both definitely true. These are the two big advantages of static
checking. First of all Proves that some errors can never happen those are caught
at compile time so I never have to worry about those errors at run time, and its
faster Dynamic typing proponents counter that aesthetic type systems are
restrictive. So essentially, aesthetic type system has to prove that the program
is well typed, that all the types makes sense And it does this by restricting what
kinds of programs you can write. There are some programs that are more difficult to
write in an aesthetic type language because the compiler has a hard time
proving them correct. And there's also a belief that I, I see commonly stated that
rapid prototyping is more difficult with ecstatic type system. I think the idea
here is that if you're prototyping something, if you're exploring some idea
you may not actually know exactly what all the types are at that point in time And
having to commit to something that is going to work in all cases. You know, to
having a type correct program when you're just trying to fiddle around and figure
out what it is you're trying to do. That's very constraining and makes the work go
quite a bit slower. So what's the actual situation and practice today? Well, an
awful lot of code is written in [inaudible] type languages. And the
practical [inaudible] type languages that people use a lot have always have some
kind of escape mechanism. So, in C, in Java, in C++, you have some notion of
unsafe cast. In C an unsafe cast can just results in a runtime crash. In Java it r
esults in an [inaudible] runtime, when you have an unsafe or failed downcast. But
the, the effect is that you can get run time errors for type reasons. [sound] Now
on the dynamic typing site, the people who programming dynamic languages, they always
end up or seemed end up record fitting static typing to these dynamically typed
languages. So typically if a dynamically typed language because popular enough than
people trying to write optimizing compilers for them and the first thing
that people want to have on an optimizing compiler. Is some insta, type information
because it helps to generate much better code? And so people wind up going back and
trying to figure out how to get as many types as they can from these dynamically
types languages as soon as they start trying to build serious tools to improve
the programs written in these languages. And in my opinion it's really debatable
whether either compromise because, both of these are compromises on the either strict
static or strict dynamic point of view. But if either one of these represents the
best or the worst of both worlds. But this is certainly where we are today in
practice. Now Cool is a statically typed language and the types that are available
in Cool are the class names, so every time you define a class you define a new type,
and the special reserve symbol SELF'lt;u>TYPE which we'll be talking about in a separate'lt;/u>
video all of its own. And the way cool works is that the user declares the types
for identifiers. For every identifier you have to say what its type is But then the
compiler does the rest of the work. The compiler refers the type for expressions.
And in particular the compiler assigns a type to every single expression in, in the
program. So it will go through the entire abstract syntax string and using the
declared types for identifiers it will calculate a type for every expression and
sub-expression. To wrap up, it's worth mentioning that there's a couple of
different terms people use for the process of computer types, and that they mean
slight ly different things. So the simpler problem is what is known as type checking.
Here, we have a fully typed program, meaning we have an abstract syntax, free
with all the types filled in on every node, and our only job is to check. That
the types are correct, so we can just look at each note and its neighbors and confirm
that the types are correct in that part of the tree. And we can do this for every
part of the tree and check that the Program is type correct. Type inference,
on the other hand, is the process of filling in missing type information. So
here the view is that we have an abstract syntax tree with no types on it, or
perhaps just a few types in key locations, on say, on the declared variables, and
then we want to fill in missing types. We have some nodes in there, there with
absolutely no type information at all, and it's not just a question of confirming or
checking that the types are correct, we actually have to fill in the missing type
information. And these two things are different. Actually there are many
languages that are actually very, very different, but people often use the terms
interchangeably, and will not be particularly careful in my videos about
which term I am using either.