The method environment has to be added to all of the other type rules in our
system. This is really easy to do, because only the dispatch rules actually care
about what the methods are. All the rest of the rules just pass the method environment
along. So what do I mean by that? Well, here's our rule for add, with
just the object environment. So now what were going to do, is we're going to add a
method environment. And the sub-expressions will be just type checked.
In exactly the same method environment as the entire expression and all the other rules
simply pass down the method environment from the root towards the leaves
without changing it just as in this rule. Now it turns out that for some cases
involving self-type, we actually need one more thing in our environment. And so, the
actual full environment for Cool type checking consists of three things. First of
all, there's the mapping O, that gives types to object IDs. There's this mapping
M, that gives types to methods. And finally, we just need to know the name of
the current class. So, whatever class the expression we're type checking actually sits
in. So the full form of a sentence in the Cool type checking [inaudible] looks like
this And is read as follows, under the assumption that the object identifiers
have the types given by O. That the methods have the signatures given by M And
that the expression sits in the class C. Then we can prove that the expression E has
the type T. And here's an example, the ad example, the, the rule for addition again,
written out with the full environment. So the rules that I've given
you for type checking here are cool specific and some other languages have very
different rules. But there are some general themes in type checking. First of
all, type rules are defined on the structure of expressions. So they're typically
done in this inductive fashion, where the types of an expres-, the type of
an expression depends on the types of its sub expressions. And also the types of variables
and more generally any free names in an expression, things like method
names, they're going to be modeled by an environment, so we're going to have some mapping
sitting around that's going to tell us any kind of fr-. A Russian what assumptions
the type rules should make about the types of those names And one thing
you've probably noticed by now but it's worth saying explicitly is that type
rules are really very compact. The notation is not complicated but there's actually
a lot of information in these rules. I mean you have to take some time to
sit and read them carefully to really understand what they are saying.