To summarize this video, The type environment gives types to the free
identifiers in the current scope. And this is very important, because it doesn't even
really makes sense to talk about type checking an expression, unless we have
some information for the types of the free identifiers. And the type environment is
just a way of formalizing that, of giving a name to some set of assumptions about
what the types of those free identifiers are. Notice that the type environment is
passed down the abstract syntax tree from the root towards the leaves. That is, as
we pass through definitions, the type environment is extended with new
definitions For example, [inaudible] expressions. And so the type environment
will grow as you pass from the root of the abstract syntax tree down towards the
leaves of the abstract syntax tree. And then the types are computed up the
abstract syntax tree from the leaves towards the roots. So we begin at the
leaves, get all the types of the leaf expressions, most of which are very easy.
Things like integers and string constants have the obvious types. And we just look
up the types of variables, in the type environment. And then we compute the types
for the more complicated expressions in a bottom up fashion.