To summarize, type checking proves facts with a form, E has type
T And notice that this proof is on the structure of the abstract syntax tree.
So, for the expression one+2, we prove something about one+2, but by first proving
something about each of the sub-expressions. So we prove that the sub-expressions
had type int. And then we managed to prove that the whole thing had
type int. And so the proof has the same shape as the abstract syntax tree. You can
look at this proof as a tree. Now the root of the tree in the case of the proof is at
the bottom, we usually draw the abstract syntax tree with the root at the top, so this
tree looks like this, whereas we often draw the abstract syntax tree in the
other way around. But, the important thing here is that the proof has the shape of the
abstract syntax tree and there's one type rule that's used for each abstract syntax
tree node. So there's a very direct correspondence between the structure of the
proof and the shape of the abstract syntax tree. And in general the type rule
used for a particular node of the abstract syntax string, the hypothesis, are going to
be the proofs of the type of E's sub-expressions. So, whatever sub-expressions
make up E we're going to need types for them first. And the conclusion
at, at that particular node will be the type of the entire expression
E. And this way you can that types are computed in a bottom up pass over the abstract
syntax string. That is I assign first types to the leads. Like here I know
that one has type int and two has type int and then. The types flow towards the root.
I'm able to compute then the next level abstract of syntax tree and so on And then
once I computed the types of all the sub expression of a knob. Then I can compute the
type at that knob.