In this video we are going to use what we have learned so far about self-type to
incorporate the self-type into the type checking rules for Cool. First let's
remind ourselves what the type checking rules for Cool actually prove. So the
sentences in the type logic look like this, and they prove things are the form
that some expression has some type, and they do that under the assumption that
object identifiers have some types given by O, methods have signatures given by M,
and the enclosing class, the current class in which E sits, in, in which we are doing
our type checking, is class C. And the whole reason for this additional piece
here we haven't actually discussed this before why we needed this C. It is because
self-types meaning depends on the enclosing class. So if you recall we.
Introduce this notation, self type sub C to record and what class a particular
occurrence of self-type sits. And this C in the environment is exactly that
subscript, it is tracking what class we are in. So when we see occurrences, an
occurrence of self-type we know what kind of self-type. We're talking about so now
I'm ready to actually give the type rules that use self-type. And for the most part,
this is really easy, because the rules just remain the same. That is, they look
the same, but they're actually a little bit different, because they use the new
sub typing and least upper bound operations that we defined before. So for
example, here is the rule for assignment, and this looks identical to the rule for
assignment that we discussed several videos ago. But notice that this use of
sub-typing here is now the extended definition of sub-typing to incorporate
self-type. So now this rule works with self-type as well as with the normal class
names. Now there are some rules that have change in the presents of self-type. And
in particular the dispatch rules need to be updated. So here is the old rule for
dynamic dispatch. And this rule, this part of the rule, actually doesn't change. It
stays the same. But, I just wanna point out the essential restriction in this
rule, is that the return type of the method could not be self-type. And that's
actually the place where self-type buys us something. So the whole purpose of having
self-type is to have methods who's return type is self-type. Because that's were we
actually get the extra expressive power. And know we have to consider the case, now
that we have self typing we done all this work, what if the methods return type is
self type. How are we going to type check that? Well here's the rule. So as usual,
we type check the. The expression that we're dispatching to that's E zero and all
of the argument and we just get their type. And their just type checked in the
same environmental as the entire expression. And now just like before we
look up in class T0 the type of E0, the method F and we get its signature. Okay.
And then we have to check that the arguments conform. That every actual
argument, E1 through En, has a type that's compatible with the corresponding formal
parameter in the method signature. And if all of that works out, then we can say
that this dispatch is going to have type, oh look, T0. So where did that come from?
Well, the return type is self-type. And so the result of this entire dispatch is
going to be the type of whatever e zero was. E zero is the self-parameter.
Whatever type we got for e zero, that is a sound static type for the result of the
entire expression. So we simply use the type of e zero as the type of the entire,
static, the entire dynamic dispatch. Now recall the full parameters of a function
cannot have type self type, but the actual arguments can have type self type, and the
extended sub typing relationship will handle that case just fine. One
interesting detail is that the dispatch expression itself could have a type,
self-type. And, so what do I mean by that, well, let's think about E zero.
Dispatching to method F, and then what happens if E zero has type self type? What
if we can prove that E zero has type self type. And the problem here is that we need
to lo okay up, in the, in the M environment, in the method environment, in
some class. The definition of or the signature of method F/, we have to get
back that type signature so we can do the rest of that type checking. And if E0 has
type soft type normally we use the type of E0 to do that, to do that look up. What
type do we use here? Well, if this whole thing is occurring in class C. If we have,
if we're type checking in class C. >> You just put the line there. >> And it's safe
and this is a soft type sub c and as always it's safe to replace soft type sub
c by c. So, we'll just use the class c there. The correct class that we are type
checking in to look up the method name test. We have to make similar changes to
the rules for static dispatch. So, here is the original rule for the static dispatch
and... And again, this part of the rule will not change. Uh... This... This
handles the case, where the return type of the method is not the self-type. But if
the return type of the method is self-typed, then the rule looks a little
bit different. So, we, once again we type check, the, expression that we're
dispatching to and all the arguments in the same environment as that of the entire
expression. We have to check that the class we're dispatching to, the type t
zero, is a sub type of the class, named in the static dispatch. We have to look up
the method. It has to exist in that class that we're statically dispatching to. So
we have to look up in class T, the method F and get its signature. And then we have
to check that the actual arguments conform to the formal parameters of their types.
If the types of the arguments match the types, the declared types of the formal
parameters. And then, the only thing that's kind of curious about this rule, is
that the result type here is, again, T zero. And, why is that right? It could
have been a, a T. It could have been the type to which we statically dispatched.
And it's not because self-type is the type of the self-parameter. And even though
we're dispatching to a method in class T , the self-parameter still has type T0. And
recall that T0 is a subtype of T. So we use the static dispatch to reach a method
definition that's hidden potentially by overwrite, overwritten methods, in the
subclasses. But that doesn't change the type of the self-parameter. The
self-parameter still has type T0 even though we're running a method. Of the, in
a superclass of G,0. There two new rules for self- type. One involves the
self-object. So, the self-object has type self-type sub-C. And notice this is one of
those places where we need to know the enclosing class. So, we know what kind of
self-type we're referring to. And similarly there's a rule for allocating
something of type self-type. So, a, the expression new self-type also produces
something of type self-type sub-C.