In this video we're going to wrap up our series on type checking with a discussion
of how to recover from type errors. So as with all the other front end phases, like
flexing and parsing, it's important to recover from errors that happen during
type checking But unlike parsing, it's much, much easier to recover from errors
in the type checker because we already have the up stacks and text tree and so
there's no need to skip over portions of the code as we did in parsing before we
even knew what the structure of the program was. The problem though, is what
type should we assign to an expression that has no legitimate type? The type
checker works by structural induction, and it can't just get stuck. So if we find
some sub expression that has no type that we can meaningfully give it, we still have
to do something with it so that we can type check all the expressions that
surround it. One possibility is to simply assign the type object as the type of any
ill typed expression. And the intuition here is that even if we couldn't figure
out what the type or the expression was supposed to be, certainly it was something
that was a sub type of object. So it is certainly safe to assign any expression
the type object. So let's consider what happens with this strategy in a simple
piece of code. So here we have a little code fragment and we just assume here that
X is undefined, that actually there's a bug in this code and that's at X has no
binding. So there's no type anywhere for X. So what happens when we type check
this? Well, we're going to recursively walk down the abstract syntax tree,
eventually we'll get to the leaves, and we'll try to type check X. And then we'll
discover that there is no type for X anywhere and that will result in an error
message Saying that X is undefined And then in order to proceed with type
checking, in order to recover, we'll have to assign X a type And so, we'll just
assume that X has type object, because that's our recovery strategy And now we'll
continue to type check as we walk up the abstr act syntax tree, and the next thing
we'll try to do is to type check this plus operation. We'll see that we're adding
something of type object to, an integer. And of course plus doesn't work on things
of type object, so we'll get an error. Something like plus applied to an object.
And then we'll have to decide, now that we couldn't type check this plus, what the
type is of X+2, so this whole sub-expression and of course our recovery
strategy is to say, well that also has type object And now the next thing up in
the abstract syntax tree is this initialization assignment. Here we're
assigning Y the result of this expression But we couldn't type check this expression
so it has type object And now the type checker sees that we're assigning
something of type object to something of type int and we get yet a third
error Saying that we have a bad assignment, of some kind. So The nut of
the, the problem here is that this simple recovery strategy works. If we do recover
we continue type checking. But a single error leads potentially to, lots of other
errors. So this is a workable solution. It, it, it achieves the goal of recovering
But in general it will lead, to cascading errors. Once you have on one type error
that type error will just cause many more because not very many things can be done
with something of type object And probably the code was written assuming some more
specific type And these errors will just propagate up the abstract syntax tree
until some point just result in multiple errors Another possibility is to introduce
a new type, a No type that is specifically for use with ill typed expressions And No
type is very special. It's not a type that is available to the programmer. It's only
available to the compiler and it's just there for error recovery and type
checking. And the special property of No type is that it's going to be a sub type
of every other type. So if you remember object was the opposite. Object is a super
type of every type and that had the bad property that there are very
few methods that defined on object and so if you plug in type object. Where you
expected some other type probably it's not going to type check. So we can fix that
problem by introducing no type. And no type will have this special property that
every operation, every operation is defined for no type And furthermore we'll
say that it produces no type as a result. So any operation in the language that
takes an argument of type no type it will produce a result of type no type. So the
no types will propagate. And now let's take a look at our same code fragment and
let's work through what happens if we use no type. So, again we walk down the
abstract syntax tree we get to this leaf X, we see that X is undefined, we
produce an error saying X is undefined. And then we have to assign a type to X so
we say well X has type no type and now we consider the plus operation And now plus
is taking an augmentative type no type integer And this is fine. We're not gonna
produce any errors that's consider to be well type and the results is also of type
no type. And now we're doing an assignment And no type is compatible with N. No type
is a subtype of N. So this assignment is also type correct And we don't produce any
type of error in that stage either And so, you can see what happens here is that no
types propagate up the abstract syntax tree just like the object types did before
But since no type is a special type it's used only for error recovery. We can
distinguish it from all the other regular types And we know that we shouldn't print
out an error message after the first one is produced. So a real compiler, a
production compiler would use something like no type, for error recovery But there
is an implementation issue with no type. And in particular, the fact that no type
is a subtype of every other class means that the class hierarchy is no longer a
tree. If you think about it, you have object at the top and then you have this
tree structure branching out. But then no type is a subtype of everything. So no
type becomes a bottom ele ment And This is now a DAG and not a tree, and that makes
it just slightly harder to implement. Instead of being able to just have tree
algorithms now you have to have either have a special case for no type or just do
something more general. And this is just enough extra hassle that I personally
don't think it's worth doing for the course project and I recommend that you
use the object solution and we just live with the propagating, or compounding,
errors that, that produces.