So now, let's move on to the least upper bound operation. And once again, T and
T prime will be any types except self-type. The least upper bound of self-type
with itself is just self-type, and I think that that's pret ty clear. The
least upper bound of self-types of C and T will be the least upper bound of the class
C and T. And once again, this is because C is the largest type, that self-type could
be. And therefore, the largest type is guaranteed to cover both self-types of C.
And T is going to be the least upper bound of C and T. And least of our bounds is the
symmetric operations, so if I reverse these two arguments, the answer is the same.
And finally if self-type is not one of the arguments at least upper bound then
we just do what we do before. The self-type, the least upper bound definition
excuse me, has not changed for class names for type names other than self-type.