What this means is that the soundness theorem for the Cool type
system is a bit more complicated than the one for simple type systems. So in the
presence of sub-typing, the, the property that we want is that the static type, computed
by the compiler for a given expression E, is going to be a correct predictor of all
the possible dynamic types that he could have, and we do that by using the sub typing
relationship right here. So we say that with every dynamic type E could have
whatever types E can take on at run time, they have to be a sub type of the single static
type that is predicted for E. What this means is that all the operations that
can be used on an object of type C have to also be able to be used on any object of type
C prime that's a subtype of C. So if C defines certain attributes and methods,
then all of those attributes and methods have to be available in C prime. And therefore
sub classes can only add attributes or methods. So whatever attributes
and methods a sub class will have, what c, c prime in this case, those
are all in addition to what c has. So c prime, a sub class, will never remove an attribute
or remove a method. It will only extend or add methods and attributes to the
class it is inheriting fro M. And note that you're allowed to redefine methods in
cool, and in most object oriented languages, but you cannot change the type.
So even though you can redefine the code that goes with that method, it still has to
type check according to the original type that you declared. And so whatever type
the method has in the first class in which it's defined, it's going to have that
same type, that same argument and result, the same types for the method arguments,
and the same types for the method result in all of the sub classes. And
that's a pretty standard, design point for a lot of object oriented languages.