To wrap up this video, here are a few comments on
implementing type checking in the presence of self-type. First of all, the extended
subtyping and least upper bound operations can do a lot of the work. If you extend
subtyping and least upper bound the way that we did then a lot of the rules don't
have to change and for the most part, you don't have to do anything special for self
type. Self-type can only be used in a very few places in the language and it's up to
you to check that it isn't used anywhere else. Those restrictions have to be
followed carefully. And finally, for the most part, a use of self-type always
refers to any sub-type of the current class. There is one exception to this in
the type checking of dispatch. In dispatch there's a method look up where we look up
in some class C, a method F. And it's possible that, that method will have a
return type self-type. And this class here c, may have nothing to do with the current
class. We are dispatching here to a different class and whatever our current
class is, this particular self type refers self type in That class, the class in
which we're doing the look up, not whatever class in which we're doing type
checking. And fortunately we never need to compare that self-type to any self -type
in the current class so there's no cross talk between different kinds of self-type.
And again this is the only place in the type checking rules where you look at a
self-type that is not one in the current class. To summarize our discussion of
self-type, self-type is still a research idea. It adds more expressiveness to the
type system, and I think that's, yeah, easy to see, but you won't find self type
in mainstream languages. Self-type by itself I think is not so important, except
for the project that you're going to implement. Rather, the reason for
including self-type is to illustrate that type checking can be quite subtle. It's
not all INT plus INT equals INT. There are actually are fairly sophisticated things
and fairly sophisticated reasoning that goes on inside type checking In practice,
of course, there needs to be a balance between the complexity of the type-system
and its expressiveness. So more complex type-systems are harder to learn and
they're harder to use effectively, but they also allow you to write more programs.