In this video, we're gonna talk about static typing versus dynamic typing. One
way to think about the purpose of static types system is to prevent common
programming errors and they do this at compile times. So they do this when the
program is compiled. And in particular they do it without knowing any input to
the program. So the only thing that is available is the program text, and that's
why we call them static Because they don't involve any of the dynamic behavior, the
actual execution behavior of the program. Now any type system that is correct, any
static type system that actually does the right thing, is going to have to disallow
some correct programs. It can't reason completely precisely at compile time about
everything that could happen as the program runs. Now what this means is that
some correct programs, by that I mean some programs that would actually run correctly
if you executed them, are going to have to be disallowed by the type checker. And so
for this reason some people argue for a dynamic type checking instead, and this is
type checking that's done solely when the program runs. So at run time we check
whether the actual operations were executing are appropriate for the actual
data that arises when the program executes. Other people say well the
problem is really just that the type systems just aren't expressive enough and
we should work on fancier static type checking systems. And. Over time, there's
been a considerable development in both camps. We see a lot of new dynamically
type checked languages, coming out, so a lot of the modern scripting like languages
and domain specific languages have some form of dynamic type checking. Other
people have been working on fancier and fancier type systems and actually there's
been a lot of progress, in static checking The disadvantage of the more expressive
text. Time checking systems they do tend to get more complicated though, and not
all of these features that these people have develop have actually found their way
yet into main stream languages. Now , one important idea that this discussion
suggests is that there are two different notions of type. There is the dynamic
type. That is the type that the object or the value that we're talking about
actually has at run time And then there is the static type, which is the compile time
notion, what the type checker knows about the object. And there is some relationship
that has to exist between the static type and the dynamic type if the static type
checker is to be correct. In this relationship can be formalized by some
kind of a theorem that proves something like the following, what we'd like to know
is that for every expression E, for every program expression E that you can write in
the programming language, the static type that the compiler says that the, the
expression is going to have is equal to the dynamic type of that expression.
Another way is saying that if you actually run the program. Then you get something
that is consistent with what you expected to get from the static type checker. That
the static type checker is actually able to correctly predict what values will hap,
will, will arise at run time. And in fact in the early days of programming languages
these were exactly the kinds of terms we had for the very simple type systems in
the languages at that time. Now the situations a little more complicated for a
language like COOL. So let's take a look at the execution of a, a typical COOL
program. So here's a couple of classes, class A and a class B that inherits from
A. So B is going to be a subtype of A which we'll write like that. And now we
have a declaration here of X having type A and this is the static type of X. So the
static type of X is A. And that's what the compiler knows about X's value. And then
here, when we execute this line of code, we can see that we assign a new A object
to X. And the fact that it's new is not important. All that's important is the
fact that it's an A object. And so, at this point, the dynamic type of X is also
A. Okay. So if this line of code when it actually execu tes A, which was declared
to have static type A, actually holds an object of class A. But a little bit later
on, down at this line of code, the dynamic type is actually different. The dynamic
type here of X Is going to be B. K line of code executes x holds a b object even
though it's declared Have a different type. And this is a very, very important
distinction to keep in mind. So there's a static type, there's a type that the
compiler knows about, and that's invariant. X has type A It always has type
a All the uses of x for the entire scope of our typed with class A by the compiler.
But at run time, because we have assignments and we can assign different
objects to x, x can actually take on objects of different types, different run
time types. Type b, that's assigned x when the program executes.