In this video we're gonna continue our discussion on self-type, by talking about
the type-level operations that are available on self-type. And this will help
to clarify what self-type actually is, and it's role in the type system. Let's begin
by thinking about the example that we discussed last time and if you've
forgotten what that is, let me just write it down quickly. We had a class called
count, and count had one. Field an integer I that was initialized to zero and it had
one method called INC that returned something itself type and all it did was
to increment the counter field and return the self-objects. And I've probably made
some syntax errors here but that's not really important. That's basic code for
the CAL class. And the question is what can be the dynamic type of the object
that's actually returned by INC. And the answer here is it could be whatever is the
type of this self-object. Whatever is the dynamic type of the self-object. And if we
think about a big program where there is multiple classes that inherit from count.
Then the answer is that INC could return count. Or any subclass of count. So it's
going to return something that's at least, at most count, and, but it could return
something more specific. The dynamic type, could be something more specific, it
could be a sub classic count, or a sub class of a sub class of count. Anything
that inherits directly or indirectly from count is a possibility. So what's the
general case? Well, let's think about a class c. And in this class C, there's some
expression buried somewhere inside of it that has the type self-type. It doesn't
really matter how that expression got the type, self-type or what it is. Let's just
say that it has that type somehow. Well, what are the possible dynamic types of the
expression e. And from our discussion on the previous slide, it seems clear the
dynamic type of e, when you run e, you're going to get back something that's a
subtype of the class c, the enclosing class in which the self-type appears. And
that's interestin g because it shows us that the, the meaning of self-type
actually depends on the context. So, what this self-type means, this self-type means
a subtype of the class C. If I'd written self-type in a class D, in the de,
somewhere in the definition of class D, there it would mean a subtype of the class
D. And so to remind ourselves, what class we're talking about, what enclosing class
we're talking about, we're gonna subscript occurrences of self-type with a class
name. So self-types of c here is going to refer to a syntactic occurrence of the
keyword self-type in the body of the class c. And this also suggests a very simple
typing rule. And really the first useful fact about self-type, which is that
self-types of c is a sub type of c. And this is really a key idea here that a
self-typing class C is some sub-type of the class C, because it also helps
illustrate what self-type really is. The best way to think of an occurrence of
self-type is that it's a type variable that ranges over all the sub-classes of
the class in which it appears. So self-types of C you should think of as a
type variable, it's something that doesn't have a fixed type, but is guaranteed to be
some type founded by C, so it's gonna be only one of the class. That inherits
directly or indirectly from the class c. Now that rule that self-types of c is a
sub type of the class c has an important consequence. It means that when we're
doing type checking with self-type, it is always safe, always safe to replace
self-types of c by c. So I say, it's okay to promote any self-types of c, which
could be c or a sub type of c, to just say, okay, we're just going to say it's c.
And that suggests one way to handle self-type which is just to replace all the
occurrences of self-type sub C by C. Now unfortunately that turns out not to be
very useful. Its sound, it's correct to do that, but that's really just like not
having self-type at all. That's as if we went back to the example we did in the
last video where we started out without self-type and we found out we couldn't use
inheritance in the way we expected. So to do better than just throwing all the
self-types away, we need to incorporate self-type into the type system. And the
way we're going to do that is by looking at the operations that work on types in
the type system, and there are two of them. There's the sub-type relationship
that we've talked about before, so when one type is a sub-type of another, and
there's the least upper bound operation that tells us what the smallest type is
that's bigger than both of two argument types. And, all we have to do and what
we're going to do now is extend these operations to handle the type self-type.
So let's begin with a sub-type relationship and in our definition here
we're going to use sub-types T and T', and these are just normal class names. They
are class names but not self-types. So one possibility is that we have self on both
sides of. Convince yourself of this. Think of self-type again, as a variable. And we
can plug in, for that variable, any sub-type of C. But, just like variables in
algebra, if we plug in one particular class for an occurrence of this variable,
we have to pick the same one for every occurrence of the variable. So in
particular, now if we pick some sub-class A of C, then we wind up with A. Is the sub
type of A. If we plug in A for both sides we can see if their relationship holds
similarly C is the sub type of C and for any sub type we might pick, if we bind the
variable to that sub type we can see that this relationship will be true. Now
another thing you might think is what if the self-type sub-C is compared with
self-type from another class? Say self-type sub-D. And it turns out in the
cool type rules this will just never come up. The cool type rules are written in
such a way that we never need to compare self-types from different classes. And I
haven't shown you that, that's the case yet. But when we actually go through the
type rules for self-type you'll see that is true. Now another possibility is that
we have self-type on one side and the n a regular type on the other side. So when is
self-types of c a type of t? Well, we're going to say if that's true if C is the
subtype of T. And here we're using our rule that it's always safe to replace
self-type by the class that, that index is in. So in this case C is a super-type of
anything that self-type C could be. Clearly if C is a sub-type of T if T is at
least C or possibly something higher in the class higher key, then T would be a
super-type of anything that self-types of C could stand for. Another case is when we
have a regular class name on the left hand side of the sub typing relationship and
self-type on the right hand side. And in this case it turns out we have to say that
this relationship is false. That so T is never, a regular class name is never. A
sub type of self-type sub C. And to see this just think about the possibilities.
So where can C and T be in the type hierarchy? So, if T and C are
unrelated. You know, if they are inherent from object and they have nothing to do
with each other. Well, than clearly T can't be a sub type of self-type sub C.
They are just two unregulated classes. So, the only way that this could
possibility work out is if they are related somehow. Now if. If T is a sub
type of C well then you might think that could work out. But it turns out that we
can't allow it even in that case. And here's the reason why, think about a
hierarchy where T has some subclass, let's just say that it has a subclass A. And now
because self-types of C ranges over all the possible subtypes of C, we could plug
in A here and T is not a subtype of A, they're in the wrong relationship. And so
it doesn't work for all the possible values of subtypes of C we can't say that
this is true we have to say that it is false. Now there is one very special case.
Where one could argue that we should allow this to be true. And that is in the case
where T is actually a leaf of the class hierarchy. And let me actually draw this a
little bit differently just to emphasize this. Let's say t hat C. Is a class up
here and then T you know, is through some chain of inheritance relationships is a
subtype of C. So it's not immediate but there might be other classes in between.
Just emphasize, this isn't, doesn't, this relationship doesn't have to be immediate
inheritance. It could be transitive inheritance. And now if T is a leaf. Of
the hierarchy. If n is the only leaf of c, if c has no other sub classes then in
fact T is a subtype of SELF_TYPE sub C. Because it is the unique minimal type that
is in the subtype hierarchy of C. But the problem is that this is extremely fragile,
and doesn't work, if you modify the program. In particular, a programmer might
come along, and add some class A over here that's unrelated to T, but is also a
subclass of C. And now this would no longer work. Because if I plug in A for
SELF_TYPE sub C, then I see that T is not a subtype of A. Right, so, we can allow
it, at a very special K. That C had only a chain of inheritance. Not a general tree
under it. And, that T was the least of that chain. But that is so fragile. To
future program extensions. And we, you know, if you, if you broke it by
adding another class over here, all of sudden you would get type errors and
pieces of codes that had previously been typed check to work and hadn't changed at
all. It just wouldn't be a very nice language design. So, summarize, T, is
never a sub type of self-types of C. And finally if we're comparing two normal
types with not self-type then we just use the rules that we gave before. So the
self-typing rules we had for normal class names haven't changed at all. And that
covers all four cases, we can have self-type on both sides, we can have
self-type just on the left side or just on the right side, and finally we can have a
subtyping relationship with no self-type at all.