In the previous video, we talked about activation but we never said what
information we actually need to keep for an activation. That's the topic of this
video. An activation record is all the information that's needed to manage the
execution of one procedure activation And often, this is also called a frame that
means exactly the same thing as activation record. These are just two names for the
same thing. Now one interesting fact about procedure activations is that they have
more information in them than you might expect. So in particular, when a procedure
f calls a procedure g, the activation record for g will actually have
information not only about g but very frequently also about the calling function
f. So typically the activation record for a procedure will contain a mixture of
information both about that procedure and about the procedure that called it. Now,
up this point, we haven't said why we need to keep information about activations at
all And the reason is that there is some state associated with this procedure
activation that is needed on order to properly execute the procedure and we have
to track that somewhere and that's the activation record is gonna be forced. It's
gonna be the whole, the information needed to properly execute the procedure. So,
let's look at that in a little bit more detail. Let's consider this situation
where a procedure F calls procedure G And what is going to happen so conceptually
what happens when f calls g is that f is suspended. F is going to stop Executing
while g is running. So g is going to be using the processor and all the resources
of the machine. But when g completes, we wanna start executing f again, f is going
to resume. And so in between, while g is running, we have to save the state of the
procedure activation of f somewhere so that we can resume it properly and that's
again what the activation record is for, And so g's activation record Is going to
have to have information in it that will help us to complete the execution of g, so
there will be some inform ation about g that we just need in order to run g, But
also, g's activation record is going to have to store whatever we need to be able
to resume the execution of procedure f. So let's work through an example. Here's one
of the programs that we looked at in the last video, and here is a design for a
concrete activation record for the procedure f. So we'll have one position
for the results of f that will hold the return value after we finished execution
of f. There will be a position here for the argument to f so is it, so fy takes
one parameter so I only need one word here to hold the, the argument to the function.
There will be a control link so a pointer to the previous or the caller's activation
and we'll also have a slot for the return address so the address in memory or the
address of the instruction that we are supposed to jump to after the execution of
f completes. So now let's just execute this program by hand and work out what the
activation records will look like down the stack. So when the front program is first
invoked, it will call main. There will be an activation record for main And we were
not gonna worry about that. We're just gonna focus on that. So there's some stuff
for main but we're not going to do to, to, to talk about that And then main is going
to call f, all right And so, when main calls f, an activation record will be
pushed onto the stack and we'll have four slots and or four fields for values. And
what we're going now while the first lines for the result well is just starting to
run if it's just beginning execution so there is nothing to put there at the
moment. That gets filled in when f returns. The second position will hold the
argument to f so that would be the number three. The third slot will hold the
controlling so that's gonna point back. To the activation for main and the fourth
position will hold the return address and this is actually not completely trivial
because f is called in multiple places. So if you look at the program, there's a
called f in main and there's a call to f inside of f itself. And so Depending on
where the function is called from after that function completes with one or return
to a different address. In the case of the main, when this called F completes we
wanna return to the. Whatever instructions comes after the called f which is just
gonna be something that wraps up the execution program since it's the only exit
point of main inside of f. It's going to be the conclusion of the conditionals. So,
this point double star here is going to be at whatever is left on the conditional
then the return from F. And so depending on what F is called from, we wanna return
to one of two different places, okay? So, in this case F is being called from main
and so we'll put the single star address in that position of the activation record,
All right? So then f is called the second time, the body of f executes and the
argument three is not zero that's way we wined up calling f again but that means
that another activation record will be pushed on to the stack that will also help
for slots as an activation record for f (I probably should label these) so that's an
activation of f, so it's also an activation of f. And what goes in this one
well again the result doesn't have anything initially in it. The argument in
this case would be two. The controlling in this case will point back to the previous
activation of f and the return address in this case will be the point double star.
So after two calls to f, this is what the stack will look like with this particular
activation record design. So, here is the same picture, just running a bit more
neatly, and there's one additional we want point out which is at this stack of
activation records and let me. Delineate the activation records here Is not as
extract as the kinds of stacks who were probably taught about in a data structures
class if you've had such a class. So here, there are distinct activation records on
the stack and we treat them as such, in the Runtime system we'll treat them as
such But this is also like one gigantic array. All o f this Data is just laid out
in contiguous memory. These were all contiguous addresses and one is activation
record here just follows on with the next address merely after the previous
activation record. And compiler is, compiler writer will often play tricks to
exploit the facts that these activations are adjacent to each other in memory and
we'll see one such potential trick in just a moment. To summarize some of the
highlights of these examples so far, I wanna repeat the main is not very
interesting. So it has no argument or local variables and if results is never
used And so while it does have an activation record, we're just not focusing
on that and we're not concerning ourselves with what goes in at activation record.
We're just focusing on the activation record for f. Just be true this clear, the
start and double star that I use in the example, these are addresses in memory.
These are actual memory addresses and they refer to addresses of code. Those are the
addresses of the instructions that come after they call f because that's the place
where f would return to. And finally, I want to stress that this really is only
one of many possible activation record designs. You can design a different
activation record for f that has had different information that would work just
fine depending on the structure of the rest of the cogenerator in the runtime
system. So, in particular many compilers don't use the controlling because they
don't need inexpensive link to be able to find the calling or the activation record
of the calling procedure and in fact, in your class project, the Khul compiler you
won't be using a control link Most. Activation records won't have the return
value on the activation record because it'd be more efficient and convenient to
return it in the register. All right, this is just one possible design and with and
you could just design other activation records that will work just fine. The
important thing about the activation record is that it just have to have
sufficient information in it to e nable the generated code to properly execute the
procedure that's being called And also to resume execution of the calling procedure.
So far, we've only looked at the procedure call for this activation record. We
haven't talked about what happens when activations return. So let's consider what
happens in our example after the second called f that this one this activation
down here returns. So what's going to happen is we're going to make the caller,
the current activation so it'll actually become the top of the stack so I'll have this big fat
green error here indicated that this is now the current activation this one up
here. Okay? So, this is the call, this is the what was the caller and is now going
to resume executing. And the interesting thing here is to note that, like I said
before, this isn't as abstract as a stack in a data structures course. So while we
have restored this as the active procedure, this data down here, this, this
activation that was running is still there in memory. And in fact we can go and look
at it if we want to. And the way I set this example up in fact we need to because
the results of the procedure that we called is now stored here. In the first
word of this activation, All right, So when f begins executing again, is going to
have to look up that result in order to know what the result was of the procedure
levels called. So the advantage of placing the return value in the first position in
the frame that the call can find it at a fix offset from its own frame. Let's back
up and just see that so here when the second call to f has returned and the, the
first call here has resumed executing this call, the code for this call will know
that the science of this activation record is four. There are four words in this
activation record and so they can find the result to the procedure that it called in
the four + one position and five words passed the top of the frame. So in
particular, they'll be able to find this where in memory and even though this has
been popped out of the stack as I said before, that data is still there at least
until another procedure is called. And so, if we immediately read the result of the
function call after we return from the function, we'll be able to pick up that
result and then use it in the continuation of the execution of the call in procedure.
And once again, I just wanna stress, I know this is a couple of times, but it's
very important that there's absolutely nothing magic about this organization. We
could rearrange the order of elements in the frame. We could divide the
responsibility between the caller and the calling differently And really the only
metric here is that one organization is better than another if it results and
faster code or in a simpler code generator And I know I also mentioned this before but
it's also an important point in a production compiler we would produce much
of the frame contents as possible in registers And in particular, there would
be a effort to pass the method results and the method arguments in registers because
those are excess so frequently. Finally to some up our discussion of activations and
activation records, the issue is that the compiler has to determine at compile time,
okay so this happens statically. The layout of the activation record and also
has to generate code that correctly accesses the locations in that activation
record. And what does this mean, this mean that the activation record layout and the
code generator have to be designed together. Okay. So, you can't just assign
your code generator and then figure out later what your activation record layout
is gonna be or vice versa, This two things needs to designed together because they
depend on each other.