In this video, we're going to being our discussions of run time structures with
the notion of procedure activations. Before we begin the discussion of
activations, it's worth being explicit that we have two overall goals in code
generation. One needs to be correct to generate code that actually faithfully
implements the programmer's program And the second is to be efficient that, that
code should made good use of resources and in particular we often care that it run
quickly And is very easy to solve These problems in isolation. If all we care
about is correctness, it's not a hard problem to generate Code that is very
simple but also very slow and correctly implements the program. If all we care
about is speed, we don't care about getting the right answer, the problem is
even easier. I can generate extremely fast programs that generate the wrong answer
for any problem that you carry to me And so really all the complications in code
generation arise from trying to solve These two problems simultaneously And,
what has grown up over time is fairly elaborate framework for how a code
generator and the run, and the corresponding run time structures should
be done to achieve both of these goals, okay? And the first step in talking about
that is to talk about activations. We're going to make two assumptions about the
kinds of programming languages for which we're generating code. The first
assumption is that execution is sequential. Given that we execute the
statement, the next statement that will be executed is easy to predict. In fact, it's
just a function of the statement that we just executed. So, controls is going to
move from one point in a program to another in some well defined order. The
second assumption is the one that procedure is called controllable always
return to the point immediately after the call. That is if I execute a procedure f,
once f is done executing, control will always return to the statement that
followed Point where f was call And there are certainly programming languages and
programming lan guage features that violate this assumption. So the most
important class of programming language is it violate assumption one are ones that
have concurrency. So the concurring program just because I execute one
statement there is no easy way to predict what the next statement is to execute it
because it might be in a completely different thread. And for assumption too
Advanced control constructs things like exceptions And Calls [cough]. If you
happen to know what call cc is, it's not important if you don't. These kinds of
constructs that affect the flow of control in fairly dramatic ways can violate
assumption to. So in particular, if you're familiar with catch and throw style
exceptions in Java and C++, when we throw an exception that exception might escape
from multiple procedures before it is caught and so there's no guarantee when
you call a procedure if that procedure can throw an exception that, that it control
whatever return to the point immediately after the procedure call. Now, we're gonna
keep these assumptions for the rest of the class. We may later on in future videos
briefly discuss how we would accommodate some of these more advanced features if
the, the material that we're going to cover. Is basic to all implementation and
even languages have concurrency and exception build upon the ideas that we're
going to discuss here. So first the definition When we invoke the procedure p.
We're going to say that is an activation of the procedure p and the life time of an
activation of p is gonna be all the steps are involved executing the procedure p and
including all the steps in the procedures that p calls so it's going to be all the
steps in the procedures that p calls. So it's going to be all the statements that
are executed between the moment that p is called and the moment that p returns
including all the functions and procedures that p itself calls. We could define an
analogous notion of the lifetime of a variable. So the lifetime of a variable x
is gonna be the portion of the execution in which x is defined, That means that
it's all the step of execution from the time that x is first created until the
time when x is destroyed or deal located and just note here that life time is a
dynamic concept so this is that implies to the executing program. We're talking about
the time when the variable first comes into existence until the moment in time
when it goes out of existence And scope on the other hand is a static concept that go
prefers to that portion of the program text in which the variable is visible.
Okay, so this is a very different idea from the life time of the variable and
again. It's very important to keep these two times, what happens at runtime and
what happens in compiler time or what is associated with the static properties of
the program distinct in your mind. From the assumptions that we gave a couple of
slides ago we can make a simple observation and that is when a procedure P
calls the procedure Q. Then Q is going to return before P returns. And what that
means is that the lifetime of procedures are going to be properly nested and
furthermore, that means that we can illustrate or represent activation
lifetimes as a tree. Let's illustrate activation with a simple example. So
here's a little cool program and as usual, it will begin running by executing the
main method in the main class. So the first activation and the root for our
activation tree for this program is the method main. And. Main is going to call
the method g and so g's lifetime, the set of instructions were g exist where a
period of time of the execution where g existed is gonna be properly contain
within the execution of this call to main. And so we can illustrate that by making g
a child of main. So this indicates that effect of g is a direct child of main
indicates that main calls g and also the g's lifetime is properly contained within
the lifetime of main. After g returns main will call f and so f will also. The, a
child of, of main And then F as itself is going to call G again And so, it's gonna
have another activation of G And so G Will also be a child of f. And this tree that
is actually the complete tree for this particular example illustrates the number
of things. First of all as we already said it shows the containment of life time. So
again for example g's life time is contained with a name but it also shows
some other interesting lifetime relationships. For example, the life time
of this activation of g and the life time of that activation of f are completely
distinct because their siblings in the tree, their lifetimes do no overlap at
all. And another thing to notice here is that there can be multiple occurrences of
the same method in the activation tree. So every time the method is called that is a
separate activation so in this particular activation tree there are two activations
of g. So, here's a somewhat more complicated example the involves a
recursive function. Let's begin here at the, at the first call. So The call to
main And all main does is call F with the argument three. So, there is an activation
of F from Main. And then what does f do, well f asks if it's argument is zero, and
if it is that calls g, while the initial argument is three so that's not going to
be true on the first call to f. In otherwise, it calls f with the argument
minus one. So, I was making note over here on the side about what the argument is
because we need to keep track of that. So f is called with three clearly that is not
zero, and so then f is going to be called again with the argument two, that will
results in f being called yet another time with the argument one and finally, f will
be called. With the argument zero, Which will then result in a call to G, And so
this is the activation tree for this particular program, And again notice that
there is gonna be multiple activation of the procedure on the same run of the
program. It just indicates that the same procedure can be called multiple times and
also note that the recursive procedure will result in nesting of activations of
the same function within itself, And so when f calls i tself and so the life time
say of the second call to f is properly contained within the life time with the
fist call to f.