In this video we're going to begin our discussion of run time systems. Now, at
this point we have actually covered the entire front end of the compiler which
consists of the three phases, lexical analysis, parsing and semantic analysis
And these three passes or these three phases together, their job is to really
enforce the language semantics or the language definition. So, we know. After
these three phases are done that if no errors have been generated by anyone of
those phases then the program is actually a valid program in the programming
language that we're compiling And at this point the compiler is going to be able to
produce codes to produce a translation of the program that you can actually execute.
And I should say that of course. Enforcing the language definition is just one
purpose of the front-end. The front-end also builds the data structures that are
needed to do co-generation as we seen but there is a real. Once we get through the
front-end we no longer looking for errors in the program. We're no longer trying to
figure out whether it's a valid program. Now we're really down to the point where
we're going to generate code And that is a job at the back end. So cogeneration is
certainly part of it. The other big part of the back end is program optimization so
doing transformations to improve the program. But before we can talk about
either one of those things, we need to talk about Runtime organization And why is
that, well because we need to understand what it is we're trying to generate before
we can talk about how we generated and have that makes sense. So first, we're
gonna talk about what the, the translator program looks like and how it's organized
and then we'll talk about algorithms and code generation algorithms were actually
producing those things. And this is a well-understood area or at least some very
standard techniques that are widely used and those are the ones we wanted to cover
and, and encourage you to use in your project. The main thing we're going to
cover in this sequence of videos is the management of Runtime resources and in
particular I'm going to be stressing the correspondence and the distinction between
static and dynamic structures. So static structures are things that exist to
compile time and dynamic structures, those are the things that exist or happen at
Runtime And, this is probably the most important distinction for you to try to
understand if you really want to understand how a compiler works. What
happens to the compile time and what happens at run time. Having a clear
separation in your mind between what is done by the compiler and what is deferred
to when the target program or the generated program actually runs that is
key to really understanding how compilers work. And we'll also be talking about
storage organization. So how memory is used to store the data structures of the
executing program. So let's begin at the beginning. So initially there is the
operating system and the operating system is the only thing that is running on the
machine and when a program is invoke. When the user says he wants to run a program,
what happens while the operating system is going to allocate space for the program
the code for the program is going to be loaded into that space and then the
operating system is going to execute a job to the entry point or the main function of
the program and then your program will be off and running. So, let's take a look at
what the organization memory looks like very roughly when the Operating System
began execution of the compiled program. So we're gonna draw our pictures of memory
like this. That would be just a big block and there will be a starting address at
the, a lower address and a higher address and this is all the memory that is
allocated to your program. Now into some portion of that space goes to code for the
program so the actual compiled code for the program is loaded usually at one end
of the memory space allocated to the program. And then there is a bunch. Of
other space that is going to be used for other things and we'll talk about that in
a minute. Before going on, I want to say a few words about this pictures of Run-time
Organization because I'm going to be drawing a lot of them over the next few
videos. So, it's just traditional to have memory drawn as a rectangle with the low
address at the top and the high address at the bottom. There's nothing magic about
that, just a convention we could adjust it easily every verse or order of the
address, no big deal. And then we'll be drawing lines to the limit different
regions of this memory showing different kinds of data and how they're stored in
the memory allocated to the program. And clearly these pictures are simplifications
if this, is a virtual memory system for example, there's no guarantee that these
data is actually laid out contiguously but it helps to understand you know, what the
different kinds of data are. And what the, a compiler needs to do with them to have
simple pictures like this. So coming back to our picture of run time organization,
we have some block memory and the first portion of that is occupied by the actual
generated code for the program and then there was this other space and we're what
goes to that space? Well, what goes to that space is the data for the program. So
all the data is in the rest of the space and the tricky thing about code generation
that the compiler is responsible for generating the code but it's also
responsible for orchestrating the data. So the compiler has to decide what the lay of
the data is going to be and then generate code that correctly manipulates that data
so there are references of course in the code. To the data and the code and data
need to be designed, the code and the layout of the data, excuse me, need to be
designed together so that the generated program will function correctly. Now, it
turns out that this actually more than one kind of data that the compiler is going to
be interested in and what we'll be talking about. In the next video is the different
kinds of data and the different distinction between the kinds of data that
go in this data area.