To sum up our discussion of activations it's obvious I think that
the activation tree depends on the runtime behavior of the program. So it depends on
the runtime value who's exactly which procedures are called and what the
activation tree turns out to be. Now, this was not illustrated in our examples but it
should be obvious that the activation tree can be different for different inputs. And
so the programs I showed you didn't take input and so we didn't have, every time
you run those programs we'll get the same activation tree, playing general if
program takes input, it will execute differently and may call different
procedures and different orders. And finally here's perhaps the most important
point for an implementation point of view. Since activations are properly nested, we
can use a stack to implement of detract the currently active activations. So,
let's see how we can use a stack to track activations. We'll use these examples that
we looked at before. And what I'm going to do is I'm going to show the activation
tree over here on the left and I'm going to show the stack of currently executing
activations on the right. So the stack is not gonna keep track of the entire
activation tree. It's only going to keep track of the activations that are
currently running so at each step of the program, the stack should contain all of
the currently active or currently running activations. So, the tree we already saw
have the build and we begin by executing main so that will be the root of the tree
And since the stack is supposed to have all of the currently running activations,
the stack will have to have main on it. So it will begin with just the procedure main
And now main calls g And so g becomes a child of main And over here on the stack,
we would push g on to the stack And then G returns and what that means is that, that
G is no longer running and so G will get popped off the stack and then, the, the
main procedure calls F and so F will get pushed on to the stack And you can see
here that after G finishes we can pop it off and we can push on that and we
maintain the environment that we have a stack of the currently running
activations. All right, then F is going to call G. I forgot to complete my tree here,
So main calls f and then f calls g. All right, So now the stack at this point is
main f and g. And once g finishes running, it will be Popped off of the stack because
it is no longer executing. And then f will finish, and f will also get popped off the
stack and finally main will finish and main will also be popped off the stack.
And so that's the idea. So that is how we can use the stack. So essentially when a
procedure is called we'll push an activation for that procedure on to the
stack. And when the procedure returns, we will pop that activation off the stack.
And because activation lifetimes are properly nested this will work out. So, to
conclude our discussion of activations, let's return to the runtime organization
As you may recall. We have a block of memory that is allocated to the program
and the first portion of that block is occupied by the code for the program
itself. And now in the rest of that memory that is allocated to the program, we are
going to have to restore the data that the program needs to execute and one of the
important structures that goes there is the stack of activations. So typically,
this will start after the code area. And the stack would grow towards the other end
of the memory space of the program and the stack will grow when procedures are called
and it will shrink when procedures return. And as we'll see, there are other things
that go in this data area that we are going to be discussing in the upcoming videos.