In this video, we are going to continue or discussion of run time organization by
talking about how compilers handle global variables and heap data structures. Let's
start by talking about global variables. The basic properties of the global
variables that all the references point to the same object. That what it means to be
global And for this reason, we can't store all the variables in the activation record
because the activation record if, of course, is the allocated. When the
activation completes and that would be the allocated global variable. So. The way
that little variables are implemented is that all global are signed the fix address
once And these variables with fixed addresses are said to be statically
allocated because they're allocated essentially at compiled times. So the
compiler decides where they going to live and then they will live there in all
executions of the program And depending on the language, there may be other
statically allocated values and we'll actually see some later on but they behave
just the same as global variables. So I think global variables changes our run
time organization picture a little bit. First we have the code as before, and
then, immediately after the code is typically all of the static data. So these
are the global variables and other static object, things that have fixed addresses
for the duration of the execution of the program and then the stack comes after
that. So the stack will start at the end of the static data area and grow towards
the end of the program's allocated memory. Trying out to the heat, any value that,
that outlives the procedure that creates it also cannot be stored in the activation
record. Let's take a look at this example. So here we have a procedure foo
and let's take a look at the activation record or frame for foo. Now let's
say that a foo allocates a bar object and that we're going to store that object in
foo activation And now when this method returns, of course the activation record
would be de-allocated so the bar obj ect will also go away but that won't work here
because notice that the dynamically allocated object - the object we allocated
during the execution of foo - is also the results of foo so this has to be, this has
to be accessible to foo's caller. After [inaudible] exits And so what that means
is that this borrow object and all dynamically allocated data has to be
stored some place other than the activation record and language is what
dynamically allocated data generally use a heap for that purpose. At this
point, we can summarize the different kinds of data that the language of
implementation has to deal with. First there is the code and in many languages, I
shouldn't say most. In many languages. The code is fixed size and read only. I mean
that the compiler creates all the code that will be used in the execution of the
program and that could be allocated once. It should say that there are many
languages also were this is not true and code can be dynamically created at one
time. The static area. Would contain data with six addresses and this would be
things like global variables and this is also typically fixed size and it was maybe
readable and writable as opposed to the code which I generally don't want to be
able to write. And then a stack is used to contain an activation record for each
currently active procedure and the activation record is generally fixed size
so each activation record for each particular kind of procedure has a fixed
size and this will contain all the local information, the local variables
contemporaries that needed to execute a particular activation. And finally, the
heap is for everything else. So the heap is just for all the data that doesn't fit
into other categories. This includes all of the dynamically allocated data And if
you are familiar with C, then the heap in C is managed by the programmer using
[inaudible] in Java, you have new. For dynamically allocating data and then
garbage collection actually takes care of reclaiming data from the heap that is no
longer used. Now many lang uage implementations use both the heap and the
stack and there is a little bit of an issue here because both the heap and the
stack grow. And so we have to take care that they don't grow into each and step on
each other's data And there is a very nice and simple solution to this and as a start
to heap and the stack at opposite ends of memory and let them grow towards each
other. So, let's take another look at our Runtime Organization picture And just for
review, first we have the code and then we have the static data. And then we have the
stack which grows towards in this case the high address allocated to the program And,
notice that the stack doesn't necessarily just grow as procedure three terms, stack
will also shrink. So as the program runs the stack will get bigger or smaller
depending on how many procedures are currently running. And the heap will start
at the other end of memory and grow towards the lower address and so we
allocate objects we'll be allocating from the back memory or the end of the memory
allocated the program up towards the top of stack And If these two points have ever
become equal and whether the two pointers. So, we have a stack allocation pointer
which says where we are going to allocate the next stack frame. And we have a heap
allocation point where it says where will allocate the next object if we have
another dynamically allocated object. As long as one of these two pointers don't
cross, as long as it never become equal then the program has memory to either add
another stack frame or another dynamically allocated object and the program can
continue away. If these programs ever become equal then the program is in fact
out of memory and at that point the run time system will abort the program or try
to get more memory from the operating or take some other course of action to deal
with the fact. If there is no there is no more memory But as long as these two
pointers don't cross, notice that this design Allows the heap and the stack to
share this, this data area in whatever way suits the program best. So, this same
design without any changes will work for programs that needed a lot of heap and
only a little stack and for programs that need a lot of stack and only a little heap
and things will have a rough balance between stack and heap as long as they
don't exceed the total memory allocated to the program.