Now that we've dealt with the layout of an object's attributes, we can switch
gears and talk about how we layout its methods and how we implement dynamic dispatch.
So, let's consider a dispatch called e.g where e here, let's say, is a class
b. Okay? So what do we wanted to have happen? Well, we want to invoke the g
method here in class b, okay? So that seems pretty straight forward. So now let's
consider a slightly more complicated example. What if we are invoking e.f of if
we're calling the f method? Well, if we have a b object. Then we are going to want
to evoke this method, this f method, okay, which is the f method to find in b. But if
we have an a object, we want to be sure that we invoke this method, okay, this version
of f. Alright, and so, this f down here is said to be overridden. Okay. So, we
have redefined. Method f in class b and this definition replaces the method definition
that b would otherwise have inherited from a so in particular in class
c, class c also have an f method okay and if we invoke the f method, if it turns out
that e here is a type c then which method should get involved? Well it would be this
one. It would be the one defining class a so all three of these classes has an f method.
If the, if we do a dynamic dispatch on either a c or a object or execute
the one defining class a. If we do the dispatch on the b object, we will execute
the method defined in class b. Now every class has a fixed set of methods including
the inherited methods. So if you, if you look, if I tell you the name of
a class, then you know exactly which methods it has. Those methods never change
at runtime. Okay? So don't be confused here because overriding is something that's
done at compile time is basically a static property. South compiler can figure
out even though you can redefine methods in subclasses the compiler can figure out
a compile time all the methods of a particular class. Methods never change while
the prog ram is executing. Alright So, a dispatch tape of there's a table of
some sort is used to index these methods and this is just in the ray of method entry
point. So, essentially for every method of the class there's an entry in the
ray for that method. And just like with attributes, the method f is going to
live at the fixed offset. In the dispatch table for a class and all of its subclasses
so once we determine the position that a method lives in. It lives
in the dispatch table; it will stay there for any subclasses of that class. So let's
take a look at our example again and just a reminder the structure of the example we
have class a and now we only really care about the method so class a define an f method
and then we have class b which inherits from a. And that define the g method.
And then there was the class which also inherits from a which defines an h method.
Alright so those three classes and these methods, Okay? And so the dispatch table
for class a only has one method in it so it's also at zero. We store a pointer
to the code for the f method define an a, okay? So this is actually literally
just a pointer to the first instruction of the code that will run method
a. So this is a pointer to the caller side or the calling sequence or the
label labeled instruction as the entry point for the method. Now, what about let's
take a look next actually at class c. Okay? So class inherits from a. So what's
going to happen with all the methods of a and they're going to be at the
same off sets. So in particular, the f method will appear at offset zero in class
and this points to the same method as the one in a And so this inherits that method
from a and then class c defines its own method h and so in the next position of the
table goes the pointer to the code for h. And, you know, there have been more methods
defined in this classes than they would have appeared you know, laid out in
textual order just like for the attributes. So, if there have been, say, two
methods defined in a, then there will be two entries here fo r the first method
and the second method define an a and then c define a three method then there will be
three more entries in the table and so on. Okay. Now the interesting case is what happens
in class b. So in class b the f method is redefined and I forgot to indicate
that so let me just indicate that up here so the f method, we have a new definition
of the f method in class b. Okay so the important thing to see here is
that the pointer to the code for the f method lives in the same position. It's still
the first entry in the table, okay so the position of the f method in the dispatch
table for class b is exactly the same that never changes. What's difference
is just the contents of that location. The first entry in the table here points to a
different function. It points to the method that was defined in b instead of the
one that was defined in a. And then since b defines some additional methods or
one additional method that gets laid out after the methods for a. You may recall a
while ago that we talked about the object header and we mentioned this thing called
the dispatch pointer so this would remind ourselves what goes in the object header.
There is the tag and then there is the size and then there was a dispatch pointer
so And then following dispatch pointer where all the, all the attributes of the class
And now this dispatch pointer is just a pointer to the table of methods for
that class, okay? So this would be a pointer to the table. That contains all the
entries for the methods, all the entry points of the methods for that class. And
the reason for using this level of in direction and so, why do we have this pointer
to a separate table and so, why are the methods laid out like that when all
the attributes are just embedded directly in the class And we could, if we
wanted to just embed all the functions directly inside the object and, ad, you know,
out this whole table inside t object and, and not have this extra pointer that
we have to, we have to maintain and follow And in the reason for this is th at the attributes
are, can be updated. Okay, So, the attributes for a and object can be unique
object. Every object and have its own set of attributes so alright But the functions,
the methods for an object never change. And so the same object table can be
shared Between all the objects of a given class. So if I have 100 a objects well
then I might have 100 different version of the attributes and so each a objects
has its own copy of the attributes. But all those 100 a objects will
have the same methods and I can save a lot of space by having them share a common
table of the methods And again every method of the class or every class is
a sign and offset and we'll call that Os of f. In the dispatch table compiled times.
So the job of the compiler to figure out all the methods of the class and
then assign each of those methods, a fixed position, a fixed offset in that dispatch
table, So to wrap up, how do we implement dynamic dispatch? So let's say we
have a dispatch to an expression e and we're calling the f method. So, here's the,
a slightly simplified version of the sequence of steps. So first, we evaluate the
expression e and that's going to give us back an object x. Okay, and then we are
going to get the dispatch table for x, where that does come from. Well, it's in the
header of x so we can just take the object x itself and we know that in every
object at the, in the third word there is a dispatch pointer for the, that's appropriate
to the class of x. So, we take that table and then we look up the entry point
of f at the offset For f in that dispatch table And then we'll jump to that
to that address, okay? That's the entry point of the function and, and when we do
that, we're buying self to x. So the, the self parameter inside of the f method will
be the x object.