In the next two videos, we're going to be looking at code generation for a language
that's higher level than a simple stack machine language we've been talking about
so far. So here's a language with integers and integer operation and this was the
grammar. So a program consists of a list of declarations, and what's a declaration?
A declaration is a function definition so it has a function name, the function takes
a list of arguments which are just identifiers, and the function has an
expression, which is the body of the function And what in function bodies look
like, well they expressions can be integers identifiers if then else, and the
only predicate that we're going to allow is an equality test between integers and
then sums of expressions, differences of expressions, and function calls. Now we'll
just say that the first function definition in the list is the entry point.
This will be the main routine, or the function that gets run when the program
starts And this language is expressive enough to write a Fibonacci function And
here it is And this is just a standard definition, if X is one then the result is
zero. If X is two, the result is one. Otherwise it's the sum of fib of X minus
one and fib of X minus two. Now, it's a two code generation for this language. We
need to generate code for each expression E; we need to produce MIPS code for each
expression E that accomplishes two things. First of all, that code is going to
compute the value of E, and leave it in the accumulator A zero. Right? So when the
code for E is done, the value of E will be stored in the accumulator And furthermore,
E is going to, the code for E, excuse me, the generated code for E is going to
preserve the stack pointer and the contents of the stack. That means whatever
the stack is when we started executing E, or the code for E, the stack will be
exactly the same after we're done, executing the code for E And we're going
to write a code generation function C-gen of E that produces code. Okay? So C-gen
would be something that produces a program. It produces code that will
accomplish these two things. Now our co-generation function is just going to
work by cases And to begin with let's focus on the expressions, and we're just
going to have, different kind of code or a certain kind of code that's generated for
each kind of expression in the language. So to evaluate an expression, which is a
just an integral constant, all we have to do is load that constant into the
accumulator. So, the code generation for ‘I', for the constant, ‘I', is the
instruction, load immediate into the accumulator the value of ‘I' And it's
easy to see that this preserves the stack as required, so this doesn't modify the
stack pointer or the contents of the stack at all, so the stack is exactly the same
before and after the execution of this instruction. >> And another thing I want
to point out or I want to emphasize here, is I'm going to be following a convention
that things that are in red, are things that are done at compile time And things
that are in blue are things that are going to be done in run time. So in this case,
at compile time we execute the function C gen of I And that produces code. Here that
will run at run time, okay. So, C gen of I, something that would execute a compile
time, and it produces a program that will be executed at run time And this is to
help you separate in your mind, and, and to develop a very, firm grip on the idea
that we have a real division of time in these programs, There's stuff that happens
inside the compiler, and then there's computation that's deferred until the
program that we are producing, actually executes. All right, now let's look at
another example. Let's, let's take on the addition of two expressions and think
about the code that gets generated for that. So, what are we going to do? Well
the first thing that happens when we execute E1+E2 is that we have to compute
the values of the sum expressions, we have to know what integers we're going to add.
So we better generate code for E1. And that's going to happen at com pile time.
We're definitely going to generate that code at compile time. And then, once we've
got the value of E1, well, remember we only have one, register stack machine, so
we're going to have to save that value somewhere until we also know the value of
E2 and where we're going to put it. We'll do what we always do; we'll put it on a
stack. So, E1 The, the, the code for E1 is guaranteed to leave the value of E1 and
the accumulator. So what we're going to store the value of E1 onto the stack. And
we know how to do that. We store A0 onto the stack, and then we have to bump the
stack pointer. >> And then we can generate code for E2. Okay and again, this stuff in
blue is a part of the program that will be executed at, at run time. These are calls
to the co-generator that are happening at compile time. And so we generate the code
for E2, and then that goes here after this code for pushing the value of E1 on the
stack And once we have the value for E2, now we can perform the add, So how do we
do that? Well, first we retrieve the value of E1. So we load the value of E1 Which is
on the stack. And notice that. This works because E2 is guaranteed the code for E2
is guaranteed to preserve the stack. You know this code for E2 here, and let me
digress for a moment; this code for E2 can be arbitrarily complicated. This could be
a whole program. It could go call functions. It could allocate data
structures. It could print things out. It could do all kinds of complicated things
But because we have this invariant that all code generation for all expressions
will preserve the stack, we know that no matter how complicated this is and how
long it takes. When it's done executing, the stack will be in the same state. And
that's what allows us to know. Where to find the value of E1 that we stored away
It's going to be at the top of the stack, Okay, so we load the value B one back into
a temporary register, now we can do the add Okay, so we add T1 and A0 together,
and store that back in the accumulator And now we have to pop the stack And now
notice that this is all the code, here, for E1+E2, and when we're done, we've,
established our the value of E1+E2 is in the accumulator. That was established by
this instruction. And this pop here restores the state of the stacks. Now, the
state of the stacks here is exactly what it was when we entered this block of code
up here. Now to be completely precise I really should write this code generation
function out a slightly different way And that would be like this. So what we're
really doing here is we are generating code for E1 and then we're printing out
into a file or something like that the code to do the push. Okay, and then we
generate the code for U2 And now, these calls, the code generation, are also
printing in to the same file, okay. So, here, you know, they just printed out
the instructions, whatever the instructions are, like security one, this
is printing out the code to execute, to do the push. You print out the code to do U2
And then, we print out the code to do the ad and the pop Fence. Yes, The add and the
pop. Okay, and this is just a, this is much more verbose over here, and so I'm
trying to go in and leave out the prints and just indicate in blue the instructions
that are deferred, but I hope you understand what this means. Everything in
red here, of course is being done in compile time so you know, we're calling
these co-generation functions a compile time. The print statements are being
executed in compile time and then we're accumulating somewhere in some data
structure or in a file, all the instructions that will be executed at run
time. So let's think about a possible optimization to this code. Instead of
pushing the result of E1 on the stack, what if we stored the result of E1 in a
temporary register T1. What would the code for that look like? >> Well in that world,
to generate code for E1 plus E2, what would we do? We'd generate code for E1 and
that would be followed now by instead of pushing the result on the stack, we would
take the result of E1, which of course is in the accumul ator A0, we would store it
in a temporary register And then we would generate code for E2. Alright, that we
followed by the code for E2, and then we could just do the add. We would, take the
result of E2, which is in the accumulator A0, add it to the contents of T1, and
store that into the accumulator A0, and of course there's no pushing and popping from
the stack here, so this code preserves the stack, and it looks like, anyway, that it
actually puts the value of E1 plus E2, into, the accumulator. Unfortunately, this
code is incorrect, so this is actually wrong, and you don't want to do this And
to see why, let's consider what would happen. If, E2 Was itself the actually,
let's do it for a concrete example. Let's do the example one plus two Plus three
Parenthesize like that, okay. So what's going to happen, so E1 here, so we're
doing one plus two plus three. So this will be a load immediate, the first, the
code for E1 will be a load immediate into A0 of the number one. Okay, and then we'll
have the move. We'll try to save that value I, in, temporary register T1. And
now we're going to generate code for E2. And what's E2? Well, E2 is itself, a plus
expression. So we're going to recursively call the code generator to generate code
for two+3. So we generate code for the new first, expression. So that will be a
load immediate, into A0 of the value two And now you should be able to
see what's going to go wrong, because. Since this uses the same co-generation
strategy, it's also going to try to use T-1 to hold the temporary value. So it's
going to move the accumulator into T-1, thereby clobbering the value of the
previous self expression that we had evaluated, the number one. Okay, so that
value's going to be overwritten and then we're going to do and add  And oops I may
have made a mistake, we're not going to do an ad, let me erase that Forgot to
generate the code for the three, so now we load the value of three. I, in to the
accumulator And now we can do the add, now comes the add And so we do A0 T1 A0 and
when you execute this what do you get. You get two + three which is five and that's
fine but now, Now we have the value of this sub expression. In the accumulator
and now ready to do the outer add. So that generates another add instruction. Which
is exactly the same But unfortunately, the first value of T1, the first temporary we
tried to restore has been overwritten And so what's in that, what's in T1 at this
point is the value two, instead of the value one, and we get that one+2+3=7.
Which is not what we wanted And so the problem here of course is that in the
presence of nested expressions, and particularly nested expressions of the
same kind, if the expressions try to use a fixed register for their temporary
values, then if you try to generate a code for two different expressions that are
nested - sorry two expressions of the same kind that are nested beside each
other, they will step on each other's temporary intermediate results And so
that's why we have to use a stack to store intermediate values. So this example
illustrates a couple of features of code generation that I just want to emphasize.
First of all, notice that the code for plus is really a template that has holes
in it for the code, for evaluating E1, E2, that is there are some fixed instructions,
that we admit And then there are places where we plug in the code for E one and
the code for E two, okay, so that's what I mean by a template, so there's some fixed
stuff which are the instructions that actually do the ad, and then there's a
place where we can just plug directly in, arbitrary code, whatever it is for
implementing E one and E two, and we'll see the same pattern with all the other
kinds of expressions. The other important point is that stack machine code,
generation is recursive. That is you know the code for E1 plus E2 is code for E1 and
E2 glued together and recursively regenerate code E1 and E2 which will have
their own templates and may even be other expressions of the same kind as we just
saw And what this means is that code generation can be written as a recursive
descent of the abstract syntax tree, at least for the expressions. Alright so
let's consider another new instruction. Let's add the subtraction instruction And
this is just like addition instruction so sub just subtraction to register instead
of adding them. And code generation then for subtraction expression as you might
imagine look and awful like code generation for a plus expression. So what
do we have first we have a place where we plug in the code for E1. >> Then we have
to store the value of E1 on the stack. We have to remember that intermediate result
And then we can go off and compute the value of E2. So this is where the code for
E2 gets plugged in And then at the end, we load the value of E1 back into a temporary
register. I actually do the operation, the subtraction, and then pop the stack And
the thing to do note about this code is that it's exactly the same as the code for
addition except for this instruction right here where we do a subtraction instead of
an add.