So to summarize the main points one very important thing is
that the activation record has to be designed together with the code generation.
So you have to do these things at the same time. You can't just design the
activation record without thinking about what code you're going to generate And
you can't just think about generating code without making some decisions about where
the data is going to be lived. So the code and the data it manipulates, have
to be designed simultaneously. Code generation can be done by a recursive traversal
of the abstract syntax street, so just like type checking. Cogeneration can
be expressed as a r ecursive tree-walk And that's a very handy way to think about
cogeneration because it allows you to think about one case at a time without having
to get mixed up thinking about all the different constructs at one time. >> And
finally I recommend that you use a stack machine for your compiler. So if you're
implementing a course project, the stack machine is the simplest discipline and
it gives you a nice framework for think, for breaking up the project into manageable
pieces. And because of that simplicity, I think it's a really good way
to learn about writing compilers. Now, it is important to realize that production compilers
do, do some different things. They're not quite as simple as, the stack
machine cogeneration that we have outlined in the last few videos. So, the main differences,
or, or, the main difference, is that the big emphasis in a production compiler
is on keeping values and registers. It's much more efficient to do
operations out of registers than to be saving and loading values from the stack And
so, especially the values in the current activation record or current stack
frame. It, in production compiler we try to keep those in registers instead of on the
stack And also, typically a pressure compiler, to the extent that it has to use
temporaries, in the activation record. These would be resolved, laid out directly
in the activation record, not pushed and popped from the stack. That means they'd be
assigned, pre-assigned locations in the activation record, just like, the function
arguments in the simple language we looked at are assigned fixed positions in the activation
record. So those temporary values would also be assigned fixed positions,
so you could save the trouble of manipulating the stack pointer.