Now, that we know how many temporaries or intermediate values we need
to evaluate a function and we also know where those intermediate value is going to
be stored in activation record. The last thing we need to know in order to code generation
is how many temporaries are in use at each point in the program. Change colors
here and so the way we're going to do that is we're going to add a new argument
to co-generation which is the position of the next available temporary.
So as temporaries gets used up, this argument, the co-generation will change while
other expressions to save their values and save places without stepping on
temporaries that are already having saved by all other expressions. And as you'll see
in a, in a moment here when we do an example, the temporary area of the activation
r ecord is going to be used like a small fixed size stack. Essentially,
we're going to have the same stack discipline that we had before only all
the computation on the stack pointer, all the discussion, all the computation of
what all sets to use has already been done by the compiler. So, what we used to do by
pushing and popping element from the stack in the generated code allow that computation
has been moved into the compiler and all that happens now is a bunch
of stores and load. To fix off that from the frame pointer So let's take a look
at how this works. Here's the code that we had for e1 + e2 under the old scheme
where we didn't have a separate area in the activation records for temporaries.
So we would generate a code for e1, and then we would save the results
of e1 on the stack, and that would be done by saving the value of the accumulator under
the stack and then we would have to adjust the stack pointer And then after we
had evaluated the two, then we would load the results of e1 back into a temporary register,
we could do the add And then we could pop the value off of the stack, the
intermediate value off of the stack Down to the new scheme. Co-generations going to
take a second argument saying what is the position of the next available temporary so
what is the position of the next unused temporary inside of the activation record
and so now we generate code for e1 and we pass along the argument okay because e1 may
itself have some temporaries that it needs to store And, and then after you [inaudible]
to evaluating, now we just do a direct store into, into the activation record
at all set empty from the frame pointer And so now as we have to do in store,
we have to save e1 in the activation record so we have it for later
on but we have to do any manipulation of the stacks. So, we could place two instructions
here by one And then we generate code for e2 but now. We just save
the temporary value at position at, at all set empty from the frame pointer so the next
available temporary would be of address empty o r offset, excuse me, nt+4
And then after each was evaluating, now we have to load the value of e1 back into a temporary
and again that was all set NT from the frame pointer of the current activation
record and then we can do the add and once again we saved the manipulation
of the stack pointers. So this code sequence here is two instructions
shorter than the one we had before and this actually substantially more
efficient.