In the last several videos, we have discussed code generation for a various
simple programming language. In this video, we are going to take a look at code
generation for more advanced feature objects. Fortunately, this dated code
generation strategy for objects is really just an extension of what we've already
learned. So, everything that you learn before we're going to be using and then
there's going to be some additional things that we do specifically for objects And,
the important thing to know about objects is slogan that you hear. When people
talked about object oriented programming is this one. So if b is a subclass of a
then an object of class b can be used wherever an object of class a as expected.
So there's a substitutability property. If I have a piece of code that can work on
a's then it could also work on b's and any other subclass of a. What this means for
the, for the case of code generation is that the code that we generate for class
a. So, the code that we produced for method in class a, has to work unmodified
for an object to class b And to see this, keep in mind that when we compile a, when
we compile class a, I, we may not even know all the subclasses of a. So, those
maybe not even have been defined yet. So, in the future some programs may come
along. To find a subclass of a then our compiled version of a will have to work
with that new subclass. So, there really only two questions that we have to answer
to give a complete description of how to generate code for objects. The first one
is how our object represented in memory. So, we need to decide a layout and
representation for objects And the second one is how is dynamic dispatch implemented
so that's the characteristic feature of using objects just so we can dispatch in
the method of an object and we need an implementation of that. So, to be
concrete, we're going to use this little example throughout this video and I'll
just take a moment here to, to point out some features of it. So, we have three
classes, classes am b, and c And notice that a, is a base class and b and c both
inherit from a, And all three classes define some attributes, some fields and
also some methods. Now, a couple of important features here is that notice
that because b inherits from a, and c inherits from a, they all, they both
inherit, both of those classes inherit the attributes a, and d from class a. So these
two attributes that are defined in class a are available in class b and in class c So
even though there's no mention Of a, and d in the definition say of class b. The
methods in class b can still refer to those attributes. They are part of the
attributes of class b. They are just copied over or inherited from a. Another
feature of this example that I like to point out is that all of the methods refer
to the attribute a so actually referred into this method and this one referred
twice in this method and also in this method. And the significance of this is
just what we discussed a couple of slides ago. For all of these methods to work
attribute a, is going to have to live in some place and some place where all of
them can find it they generate a code run. Some particular less considered the method
f. So the method f exists in all three classes. All three classes when it runs,
it will refer to attribute a, and even though the objects would be different. In
one case it might be running on an object and in another case on a c object. It
would need to be able to find the attribute a, and so therefore the
attribute a, has to be in the same place in each object And so, how do we
accomplish that? Well, the first principle is the objects are laid out to in
contiguous memory. So, an object is just a block of memory. Okay with no gaps and all
the data for the object is stored in the words of that lock of memory. And each
attribute is stored at a fixed off set in the objects. So for example, there may be
a place in this object for attribute a On this case it's at in the middle of the
object is in the, in the fourth position And, no matter what kind of object it is,
whether it's an a. B or c objects and are example as with a we always live with that
position so that any piece of code that refers to a, any method that refers a can
find can find the a attribute. Now the other thing that's important to understand
and this is you know slight digression from what we're talking about but it's a
key aspect of code generation for object is that when a method is invoked, the
object itself is the self parameter. So the self parameter is the entire object so
self. When a function is involved, it will refer to the entire object so you think
itself is going to be appointed to the entire object. Remember that self is like
that this variable or this name in Java. And then the fields we refer to particular
or the attributes of the object will refer to particular position within the objects.
So, for example, the attributes, we decided to leave it there. So here is the
particular object layout used in Kuhl. So the first three words of a Kuhl object
contain header information and every Kuhl object always has these three entries. The
first position is a class tag and also at zero then the next word it also four is
the size of the object and then something called the dispatch pointer and then all
of the attributes. Now the class tag is an integer which just identifies the class of
the object. So the compiler will number all of the classes. So in our example we
have three classes a, b, and c and the compiler for example might assign them the
numbers one, two, and three. It doesn't matter what these numbers are As long as
they are different from each other. So, it doesn't have these numbers consecutively
or anything like that The important thing is of the class tag is a unique identifier
for a class, each class has its own unique bit pattern that tells you what kind of
class the object is And the other fields here the object size is also an integer
which is just a size of the object in words and the dispatch pointer. Is a
pointer to a table of methods so the methods are stored off to the side and the
dispatch pointer is a pointer to that table and we'll talk about this more later
and then all the attributes are laid out in the sub-sequence slots in some order
that's determined by the compiler so the compiler will fix and order for the
attributes in the class and then all the objects of that class will have the
attributes of that class in the same order. And again all of this is laid out
in the continuous chunk of memory. Now, I'm ready to talk about how inheritance
works. So, the basic ideas like given a layout for class a, a layout for a
subclass b, so this is a subclass of a can be defined by extending the layout of a.
So, we don't need to move any of the attribute of a, we can just add more
fields onto the end of a's layout. And so, that's going to leave the layout of a
unchanged which is a great property because this is how the position of an
attribute in the a object will always be the same for all the subclasses. So
essentially, we will never, once we decide where an attribute lives in a class it
will never change for any of the subclasses of that object. So b is just
going to be an extension of the layout of a. So, let's take a look at our example
here and see how that, that works. Let me just write down here a little bit about
these classes because we don't have the example on the screen. So we have a class
a, and class a, had two attributes, a, and d, okay? And it doesn't matter what their
types are or what the methods were here. We're just looking at the class names and
the names of the attributes that are defined in the class. And then we have b.
Which inherits from a and b added a attribute b and then we had c which also
inherits from a but has no relationship to b. And class c define an attribute little
c. Alright. So, that's the structure of our example is relevant to the layout of
the objects. Okay. So Let's talk about the layout of class a. So, in position zero at
all sub zero, there'll be a tag for a that will be some small integer at the compiler
picks. There'll be a size of a, we'll come back to that in just a se cond. There will
be a dispatch pointer again, which we're going to talk about later. And then come
the attributes of a, and it just laid out the compiler, the way it's done in the,
the Kuhl c implementations is that they are laid out in the order in which they
appear textually in the class. So, in this case, first the attribute a, And then the
attribute d all sets twelve and sixteen And now since the object, there are two
attributes and three header words that means the size of the object is five words
and so it's a five that goes in the size field for a objects. Now, let's take a
look at b. Okay? So b is going to have a different tag, b objects will have a
different tag so they to distinguish them from a objects. There's going to be extra
fields so the size will be one bigger But now the layout preserves the layout of a.
So the attributes of a appears in the same position. So you can think of there being
an a object Actually embedded inside of the b object. If I were to strip off the
end here that were just you know cover up this last bit here b I would say that this
object here has the same size and the same attributes as an a object so any piece of
code that could work on an a object will also make sense running on a b object. Now
Of course, the tag is different because it actually is a subclass and you know, and
there is an extra field so the, the size is different but the point is that any
code that it refer is just to the fields here will still work just fine. So any a
method that was compiled that refer to the methods of an a object will still find
those attributes in the same place at the b object and afterwards, there is also one
more field here. Which is the new attribute b It just gets laid out after
all of a's fields. So after all of a's fields come all of b's fields in the same
order which they appear textually in the class because there's just only one,
there's just one new field there. And now looking with class c or the story with
class c is very similar so c has its own distinct tag and also has one more
attribute than a so it has size six. And now again the a attributes were on the
same position and now the c attribute just comes after the a attribute. And so notice
here that a methods again will work just fine on c objects because the attributes
are on the same places and so the methods will find the attributes where they expect
to. You cannot however call a method of class b on an object to class c. Okay
because they have different attributes in the third position. We may have completely
different types. It may not make sense to invoke a b method on c object but that's
just fine because if we look at our inheritance hierarchy over here we'll see that b and
c are actually unrelated. They are both subclasses of a but they have no
relationship to each other. B is not a subclass of c and c is not a subclass of b
and so anything beyond their shared ancestry with a can be completely
different in the layout. So, more generally, if we have a chain of
inheritance relationship, so let's say, we have a base class a1 and a1 inherits some
a1 and a3 inherits some a2 and so on with some class a and inheriting at the bottom
of this of this chain after some long sequence of, of other intermediate. Some
classes, you know, what is the layout of all these classes going to look like.
Well, there's going to be a header. Okay, the three word header and that will be
followed by a1's attributes. And then followed by a2's attributes followed by
a3's attributes and so on all the way down to an's attributes down here. Okay. And if
you look again so what we talked about before each prefix. Of this header is
essentially a valid object a valid one of these objects. If I look at the first set
of attributes, everything up to the end of a1 and attributes, that forms a valid
layout for one object is I stop with the a2 attributes. I have a, I have a, I have
a valid layout for a2 object going all the way from the header down to you know,
including the a1 and a2 objects. And then a3 includes all a1, a2 and a3's attributes
and so on. Okay? So, each prefix Of, of this object, Of this a and object has a
correct layout for some for some super class of A n.