So next we're going to talk about code generation for if then else
expressions And to do that we're going to need some control flow instructions. So
we'll have, we'll need two in fact. So here's the branch equal instruction, and
this jumps to a label if the contents of two registers are equal And then we'll
also need an unconditional jump. So this just does an unconditional branch, not
branch, an unconditional jump to a particular assembly instruction. So let's
look at the code generation for the expression if E1 is equal to E2 then
evaluate three otherwise evaluate four. So first we have to evaluate the predicate
and in order to evaluate the predicate, we first have to evaluate E1. And by now this
pattern for binary operation should be familiar. So we evaluate the first
sub-expression we save the result on a stack, so we push it on to the stack. It
takes two operations, one to save the result of the cumulate on the stack and
the other cumulate stack later. Then we evaluate E2. Now we have evaluate d both
of the arguments to the predicate. The result of E2 is in the accumulator and the
result of E1 is at the top of the stack because again, the evaluation of E2 will
preserve the stack. So now we load the value of E One back into a temporary
register. And we pop the stack And then we can actually do the comparison. So now we
do a branch equal. So if the value of E One is equal. Sorry this is actually the
value of E Two and E Zero and if that's equal to the value of E One. Then we
branch to the true branch. Otherwise we're going to fall through if there not equal.
Okay And so we'll call that the false branch And what are we going to do if we
fall through, if this test fails, well then we want to evaluate E4. And that will
leave the value of E4 in the accumulator and that will be the value of the entire
if then else in the case where the predicate is false. So when we're done,
we're going to branch now to some code that we'll just clean up and end the if
statement. We'll see what that does in a moment. Otherwise, we still need to
implement the true branch, so we'll stick the label for the true branch here And
what do we do on the true branch? We just evaluate E3. Okay And then the and if,
Well, actually, there is no cleanup to do Because, E3 and E4 both preserve the
stack, and they leave the result of their expressions of the accumulator. So we
reach and if, from E3 if we executed the true branch And then, in which case, the
value in the accumulator is the value of E3 And we reach and if, through this
branch if we executed the false branch And then the value in the accumulator is the
value of E4 And so this correctly implements an if then else expression.