In the next couple of videos, we're going to be looking at the details of the Cool
operational semantics going over the semantics of each individual kind of
expression. We'll start with easy ones and work our way up to the more complicated
ones. So the easiest rules are the rules for the constants in Cool. So the value
true, the expression true I should say, evaluates to a Boolean with the value true
And it doesn't modify the store so the store is unchanged because it doesn't do
any updates obviously And there's a corresponding rule for false And integers
are very, very similar so if a integer expression, integer literal i will
evaluate to, and integer object with the value i and again the store is not
modified by such evaluation. And finally, strings if a, if s is a string literal of
length n, then it will be evaluated by the string object of which the properties n
and the string constant s. The evaluation of identifiers is very straightforward,
given that we have both in environment in the store. So to evaluate an identifier
and this would be a variable lane y x or y or for What do we do? Well first we look
up in the environment where that identifier is stored so now we give us
back a memory location l. So by in this case And then we look up in the store what
the value is at that memory locations, So, we use the same memory location here as an
argument to the store to get back the value that, that, that variable currently
has And notice I just have a reference, this is a read of memories so this is
loading, I think it was loading the value of the variable. This does not affect the
store so the store is the same before and after. This is just looking at the value
of the variable not updating the variable. The expression self just evaluates to the
self object. So, this is a place where we just make use of the fact that the self
object is part of the environment so let's just copy them over here as the result of
expression and that was again that the store is unaffected by evaluation of self.
Now let's see of a more slightly more complicated evaluation is evaluated, in
particular the assignment expression. So an assignment consists of two parts, an
identifier that is being updated and an expression that is going to give us the
new value. So for example, just to remind you we might have something like x gets
one + one so one + one here would be the expression e and x would be the identifier
All right? And so in order to evaluate the assignment, the first thing we have to do
is we have to know what value we're going to be writing into the identifier. So what
is the, what is the update we're going to perform? So the first thing to do is to
evaluate e, okay? And notice here that e is evaluated in the same environment so it
has the same three components here, and here, all right? So it just says the first
thing we do is we run e. Okay. That will give us back a new value. We're going to
get back on value b excuse and possibly an updated score so you can arbitrate a piece
of code. You could yourself have assignment statements in it so the story
that we get out might be different. Alright, so e produces the value of e and
an update store s1 And now it's actually due to assignment, what do we do? Well we
have to know what memory location was supposed to update so we look up the
memory location for id and that would give us some location else of id. And then we
modify the store with the new, we modify the store at that point with the new value
so we replace the location l, i, d or we update the value of l, i, d to be the
value of e, the value b and we do that in store s1 which gives us a new store s2.
And I've noticed. That s2 is the store that results from the evaluation of e,
okay? So after we do the assignment, the assignment returns the value b which is of
course the value of a, of running e. And, it returns the updated store s2. Next,
let's talk about the operational rule for addition. So, to evaluate e1+e2, what we
are going to do? So, first we evaluate e1 And notice that is done in the same
context as the context of the entire e xpression, okay? So the components the
context here for evaluating one are exactly the same as the components for the
overall expression e1 + e2. So when we evaluate e1 it's going to give us a value
of e1 and it's also going to give us an updated store s1 And then we're going to
evaluate e2 and notice here And I think context is different. The soft objects in
the environment are the same; same but now we're running e2 in the new store s1. And
what does its saying is that if e2 has, has assignments or variable references in
it those assignments and variable references have to be done on the store
that resulted from running e1, okay? So, it's very important that we get that any
side effects would happen in running e1 are visible or that are seen by the
expression e2. So we run e2 in this environment, we're going to get the value
of e2 and the updated store s2 And then the result of the entire expression is
going to be b1 + b2 and the results it store will be the store s2. And notice
here how the stores tell you the order in which you have to evaluate the
expressions. So because e1 is evaluated in the same store as the overall expression
that tells you that e1 has to be evaluated first. And then because e2 is evaluated in
the store that's produced by e1, that tells you that e1, e2 excuse me, has to be
evaluated after you've evaluated e1 and then the fact that. S2 is the result of
the whole thing. It tells you that E2 is also the last thing that you evaluate
during the execution of this particular expression. Okay, let's take a look at the
statement block and just a variety here on the change my colors. How are we going to
evaluate the, a statement block of statements e1 through en, okay, so, while
this is semantics, this is that we should run, I mean order beginning of e1 and the
results of the entire execution will be the, let's say the value of the entire
block with the value of the last expression. And this, this rule just says
that. So, first, we evaluate e1 and also it's done on the same store as the overall
expressio n as it tells you it has to come first and that produces a new store s1 and
the value b1. Okay And then e2 is evaluated in the store s1 and it produces
the store s2 and so on And then expression en is evaluated in the store sn - one and
it produces a value of bn and an updated store s (N). Okay? And then the result of
the whole thing is the value of vn and also the updated store s (N) and this
tells you, this would really tell you the order which had to evaluate the sub
expressions. The dependencies here on the store of course you do evaluate e1 and
then e2 and then e3 and so on so you have to do them to net order to get the side
effects to get. You know the side effects in the correct order for all of these
expressions And furthermore, it also tells you the only value that you're going to
keep is the value vn. Notice that none of the other values that are produced here
are used for anything. They don't appear anywhere else in the rules. Let's think
what we've learned so far and do a small example. So we want to know what happens
when we evaluate the block. X gets assigns seven + five, that's the first statement
and the second and the last statement in the block, is just the expression four.
And the first thing we have to do is to say what the context did and which we are
going to evaluate this and the context consists of three parts. There'll be a
self object and in this case it doesn't really matter what's in the self object
because self is not referred to in the program and so it won't play any role in
the evaluation. But we, we still need it so there still be, there'll be some self
object out there just won't get used and Now, in the new environment which tells us
the locations where all the free variables in the programs. So, we'll just need a
place for x is going to be stored and so s will be stored in some location l And then
we know our memory content is, where our store is and let's just say that at l we
have initially the value zero, okay? So now we can use our rules to run this
program or to evaluate thi s program. I'm going to make this line here much longer
And recall that, that evaluation of block consist of the evaluation of the, all the
statements within the block. Okay, so the first one is going to be s gets seven+5
and that will be evaluated in the same environment as the overall expression. So,
we have up here. So the same context excuse me and I should say I often slip
and I realize and say environment for the entire left hand side of one of these
judgments. I'll try to be consistent. And just use environment for the, for the
second components of the context often in the literature people call the entire
thing on the left hand side of the environment that's why they make this
mistake but you know for this instead of notes I'm trying to be consistent the
entire, all the components on left hand side together are called the context and
the environment is just the second component. The mapping from variables to
their locations Anyway coming back to the example, The first statement in the block
is s gets seven+5 alright. And then we're going to have the second statement as
well. And we know that the self object and the environment won't change but we don't
know what the store will be. The store might be different so I'll leave the store
empty for now and we'll figure that out later and we're going to be evaluating the
expression four. Okay, so this is the structure of the evaluation now in
progress. We should look at, at this first statement trying to make some forward
progress on that one. So, to evaluate the assignment, what do we have to do? Well,
the very first thing we have to do is we have to evaluate the right hand side so
we're going to have the context for that is going to be the same And the context
we've been looking at all on because it's the first thing that's actually going to
happen is to evaluate Seven + five, okay? And now, I'm leaving a little space down
here for the rest of the assignment role which we're not going to fill in just yet.
Now to evaluate the plus expression we have to evaluate the first express ion and
the second expression, okay? And so, how do we do that? Well, we know, finally, I
think how to do that because we're finally down and we're going to have a single
integer there and that we already have a rule for, okay and so an integer
literal evaluates to institute your object, okay And inside that object is
just about the value, okay. And the store is unmodified All right? And then
similarly for the other argument here, Okay. So the five will also evaluate to an
integer object with the value of five and the store will be unmodified okay so
that's the two sum expressions of this edition and so now we can fill in the
results here so to take the contents of the two integers we'll add them. That will
also be integer object so we're going to have the integer object twelve. And the
store has not been changed, okay? So the, the store that we get out of here happens
to be the same as the store that went in just because this expression had no
assignments in it, okay? And now we're ready to do the assignment. Okay. So how
do we do that? Well, we have to form a new store. Alright, so we're going to have a
new store which will the L gets zero with the value of l. Number which way, my
notation went here, I think it's the number comes first and we're going to put
twelve in the location l and of course, that's store was just equal to the store
where l has the value twelve, okay And so now, what happens down here and we do the
assignment and we get out The new value. Okay so, the value of the right hand side
is twelve and we have a new store where the location l has twelve, all right? So
now we're going to evaluate the second statement in the block and that will be
done in the store where l has the location twelve and of course this is just an
integer And so that will evaluate to the integer constant of four, the integer
value excuse me, 4or integer object containing, the integer object with the
value four and our store. And it's just going to fit not quite, all right? And
that's then the result of the entire evaluation . So, this block will produce
the value four, an integer object with the value four and an updated store where
location l has the value twelve. So, the next expression I would like to take a
look at is the if, then, else expression and to evaluate if, then, else what do we
do? Actually there should be if, then, else. See of course, so evaluating if,
then, else as well. First we have to evaluate the, the predicate and it's done
in the same store, the same context as the overall expression and if the result is
true If the, if the Boolean predicate returns the value true. Then we want to
evaluate just the true branch and not the false branch so that's why you only see
here, evaluation of e2 and e3 isn't mentioned anywhere and just know here that
the predicate may have side effects and so e2 is evaluated in whatever store that e1
produces And then the results of the entire expression is the value of e2.
Okay, that's v and also just the final store is produced by running the then
branch. And there is a symmetric rule for what happens if the predicate evaluates
the false. In that case, you would evaluate e3 and not e2. Next we'll take a
look with what happens with while loops and cool. So there are two cases. First if
the predicate of the while loop evaluates the false, okay. Well, in this case the
loop body is not going to execute, alright so the first thing we do is we evaluate
the predicate and that's done in the same context as the evaluation of the overall
expression and if the predicate is false then we exit the loop and so the results
of the loop is void. The value void and just whatever store resulting from
evaluating the predicate. The other possibility is that the predicate
evaluates the true. So here we evaluate the predicate again in the same context as
the overall loop. And if the predicate evaluates the true then we're going to run
the loop audio once. Okay. So we'll evaluate the loop audio and also that's
done in this, in whatever store results from evaluating the predicate. Evaluating
the loop audio is g onna give us a value of v and a new store s2 and then what we
need to do is we need to go back around and execute the loop again and how can we
do that? Well, we're really just running the whole loop in the new context. So, the
next thing we do is we evaluate the entire loop. Right in the new store So, after I
execute the loop by, loop body one time, then we go around and just evaluate the
loop again And when this may run for zero or more iterations, alright. And when I
finally terminate, if it terminates, it will produce it will produce a new store
s3 evaluated while because always produced the value of a void. And then what we'll
produce for the entire loops, for the entire expression is the value void and
the update and store s3. The next interesting expression to take a look at
is the let expression. So recall how, what this looks like so let and cool has a
variable thing declared and it's type and an initializer which is optional so this
is the value that the identifier will be initialized to and then the expression in
which that new variable is available. And so how do we evaluate this? Well first,
we're going to evaluate the initial value of the, of the new variables. So we
evaluate e1 and as usual that's done in the initial store it produces possibly
modified store. And now the question is, what are going to, what's going to be the
context here for the evaluation of e2 for the body of the latter? And so it seems
clear that it's going to involve s1 because it has all the updates from e2 but
it also has to have this new identifier in it. And so how are we going to do that?
So, what we want is to have a new environment e but with new binding of ID
to refresh location. So, we're introducing a new variable. Remember that the
environment has tracked all the free variables so this is one situation where
you should going to extend the environment e with the new binding, alright. And that
location, the location for the new variable has to be a fresh location. We
don't want to conflict with any other memory locations we are already using.
Okay And so, we're going to allocate a new memory location for the variable And then
the store, the new store will also will be like as one as we said we have to include
all the, the values for s1 But also, we can have these new location for the
variable and that's going to have the initial value of the variable e1. To
express that we need a new location, we're going to introduce a new operation on the
store which gives us a new fresh location. So new lo applied to a store it's just
going to give us some location that isn't being used by the store. So, the store has
a domain where it's a mapping from locations to values and we'll just pick
some new location that isn't in the current list of locations within the store
and that will be the one returned or that will be one, that will be the one returned
by new lo. Okay, so new lo if you can think of As modeling the memory allocation
function in the runtime system. So, then, here we can write out the rule. So, this
is the most complicated rule we seen so far. So, I'll just take a moment to walk
through it All right? So, the first thing we do is we evaluate e1, the initializer
for the new variable, okay? So just like before, this is done in the same context
as the overall expression and this is going to give us a value for e1 and an
updated store, all right? Then in the updated store, using the updated store
here we find an unused location, l new. Okay And then we're going to create a
store where that new location has, has the value of e1. So we're going to store the
value of e1 at that new location. We're going to update the store s1 to reflect
that and further more we're going to extend our environment with the new
identifier which will be stored at this new location and this is the context then.
Okay, with this updated environment in store in which we evaluate the body of the
lab which will produce the value b2 and possible update in store s2 and those are
the results of the overall expression.