To summarize our discussion of dynamic dispatch, the body of the method is
invoked with, within environment e. That has definitions for the formal arguments
and the attributes of the self object and a store that's just like color store
except that it also has the actual arguments bound to the locations allocated
for the formal parameters. Notice in the rules that the notion of a frame or
activation records is implicit. We don't actually build a data structure. That
contains you know, all of the values all of the arguments and the, the return
address and all that stuff together. That information is not gathered together in
one place, it's a little more abstract. We don't actually have to say you know,
whether things are allocated on the stack or on the heat and that's a good feature.
That allows us to have, potentially have a range of implementations like all
implement the semantics correctly. Now, we didn't do the semantics on the semantics
dispatch but it's extremely similar. The only difference is in how the class that
we are going to be dispatching to is looked up so in the stack dispatch you
might be able to you know, you can nam e the class that you want to dispatch to
this one extra line to the side where the class is being dispatched to in the formal
rule and you can look in the manual to see how that works. So it's worth pointing out
that while the operation of rules are very detailed, they intentionally omit some
cases that you might think they should cover so let's take a look at our dispatch
example again. So here notice that we look up the class of v0. So v0 is an object and
we checked what is class tag is and then we look up in that class, the name of the
method that we're dispatching to and we get out a definition of the method or not
the definition of the method that we can write the rest of the rule. Now what would
happen If there was no such method f in the class x, I mean this, this rule just
assumes that method is in fact to define the class x, And the rule doesn't say
anything about what to do if it turns out that this class x doesn't have any method
f? Well, that actually can't happen. So, type-checking has already guaranteed That
when we go to look up method as in class x it will exist. That was one of the points
with the type checking rules was that no dynamic dispatch could ever dispatch to a
method that wasn't defined. And so the fact that the time checking is already
been done, it will allows us to meet some cases. So there's some checks that we
don't have to do because we know that, that system has already effectively done
that And the rules would only be more complicated if we didn't have type
checking and we needed to actually say what would happen you know, all of the
cases where type checking will work where things were not typed correct. Now there
are some run time errors that the type checker doesn't prevent however and in
cool there are four. One is to dispatch the void. Divisions by zero you can have a
sub-screen in that excess out of range or you could run out of memory. You could try
allocating new objects that do not have enough space for that. And in such cases,
the execution has to aboard gracefully an d that means with an error message and not
just with a segmentation fault or some other kind of hard crash and in the manual
there some guidelines as to what a correct co-implementation should do in this four
situations. To summarize the material in the last couple of videos the operational
semantic rules are really very precised and detail. If you understand them then
you really understand how to implement a correct cool compiler. So the rules are
complete enough and give you enough detail that it really can't go wrong if you just
implement what the rules tell you to do. So you need to read the rules very
carefully And I'll emphasize that because there's actually quite a lot going on in
the rules. They're written in a certain way and you know, to, to achieve a certain
effect and I pointed out a couple of subtle things in the rules and so you
know, you really have to actually study the rules in order to internalize what
they mean and be able to. Implement them correctly. It's also a great way
understanding these rules and details was actually a great way to learn quite a bit
of the, the kind of formal thinking that goes in to the design of programming
languages and what it means for a programming language to have a semantics
and for implementation of something to be correct. Now having settled that, I should
say that most languages do not have a well specified operational semantics. There are
some there are some substantial languages and fairly realistic languages that do
have a formal semantics but most of the language is that you're familiar with do
not. Finally just a comment you know when portability is important, when you really
want software that you write behave the exactly the same in different environments
so you know if I take the same program and I move it to a different machine or a
different operating system and I still want to kind of guarantee that this offer
will behave as it as it you know the same on both machine or the old environment and
the new environment then I really need some independent defin ition of what it
means what the behavior of these programs should be. And that's where a formal
semantics becomes a really critical.