We are now ready to begin our next major topic, Program Optimization. In this
video, we're just going to give overview discussing why we want to perform
optimization and what the trade-offs are for compilers and deciding what kind of
optimizations to implement. Optimization is the last compiler phase that we're
going to discuss. Let's just very briefly review the compiler phases. First there is
lexical analysis and then that's followed by parsing. Then we have semantic
analysis. And after that we talked about code generation. And now we're going to
talk about optimization, okay? So optimization actually comes before code
generation because we want to improve the program before we commit it to machine
code but it is of course the last one that we've discussed. But, just point out here,
optimization fits in between generally semantic analysis and code generation and
in modern compilers this is where most of the action is. It's usually has by far the
most code, and it's also the most complex part of the compiler. Now, a very basic
question is, when we should perform optimizations? And we actually have some
choices. We could perform them on the abstract syntax tree and, a big advantage
of that is that it's machine independent but for many optimizations we want to do,
this, it turns out that the abstract syntax tree will be too high level that we
can't actually even express the optimizations we want to perform because
those optimizations depend on lower level details of the machine or of the kind of
machine that we're generating code for that aren't present in the abstract syntax
tree. Another possibility would be to perform optimizations directly on assembly
language and the advantage here that all the details of the machine are exposed. We
can see everything that the machine is doing. We can talk about all the resources
of the machine and so, in principle, any optimization we want to perform can be
expressed at the assembly language level. Now a disadvantage of doing optimizations
on assembly language is that they are machine-dependent. And then we would have
to potentially re-implement our optimizations for each new kind of
architecture. And so, as we mentioned in the previous video, another option is to
use an intermediate language And the intermediate language has the advantage
potentially, if it's designed well, of still being machine independent. Meaning
it can, it can be a little bit above the level of the concrete details of very,
very specific architectures. I mean, it can still represent a large family of
machines but while, at the same time, exposing enough optimization opportunities
that the compiler can do a good job of improving the program's performance. So,
we will be looking at optimizations that work on intermediate language that has
operations given by this grammar. So, in this case, a program is a sequence of
statements and a statement consists of either, an assignment Which could be a
simple copy, or a unary, or binary operation. We can push and pop things from
a stack and then we have a couple of different kinds of jumps. We have a
comparison in jump where we compare the value of two registers and then
conditionally jump to a label. We have unconditional jumps and finally there are
labels, the targets of jumps. And the identifiers here are the register names,
and we could also use immediate values on the right hand side of operations instead
of registers and the typical operators, we're just going to assume some typical
family of operators like +,,, -,,, 'lt;i>, etcetera. Now, optimizations typically'lt;/i>
work on groups of statements and one of the most important and useful statement
groupings is the basic block. So a basic block is a sequence of instructions and
typically we want it to be the longest possible sequence of instructions. So we
want it to be maximal and this sequence has two properties. First of all there are
no labels except possibly for the very first instruction. And there are no jumps
anywhere in this sequence of instructions except, possibly for the last instruction.
And a basic block the ide a behind a basic block, and the reason we require these two
properties is that it's guaranteed to flow, the execution is guaranteed to
proceed from the first statement in the block to the last statement in the block.
So the flow of control within a basic block is completely predictable. Once we
enter the block, once we begin at the first statement of the block which might
have a label, there will be a sequence of statements. That must all execute before
we reach the last statement which could potentially be a jump to some other part
of the code. But once we get here, once we get to this very first statement, then
we're guaranteed to execute the entire block without jumping out And furthermore,
there's no way to jump into the block. You couldn't just come from some other random
part of the program and begin execution, say, at the second or third instruction.
The only way into the block is through the first statement, and the only way out is
through the last statement. Say here's a example basic block and just to show you
why basic blocks are useful. Let's observ that we can actually optimize this piece
of code. Okay because three always executes after two. This instruction here
always execute after this instruction. We could change that third instruction to be
w = three x. Okay because we can see here that t is getting two x + x or two
x and here we're adding in another x and so w is actually always equal to three
x. And a question then, so that, that is certainly a correct optimization and, and
it's correct exactly because statement two is always guaranteed to execute before
statement three. Another question we might be is whether we can eliminate this
statement so once we replace this by three x, you know maybe we don't need this
assignment anymore if this was the only place that t was used if t was a temporary
value that was computed only to compute the, the value w. And then we can delete
this statement and this depends on the rest of the program. We have to know
whether t has any other uses someplace else in the program w hich we can't see
just by looking at the single basic block. The next important grouping of statements
is a control flow graph. And a control flow graph is a, just a graph of basic
blocks. And so there's an edge from block a to block b. If execution could pass from
the last instruction in a to the first instruction of b. So essentially the
control flow graph just shows how control flow can pass between the blocks and there
isn't of course no interesting control flow within the block. We know that the
basic block will just execute from the first instruction to the last instruction.
So, the control flow graph is a way of summarizing the interesting decision
points in a, in a procedure or a other piece of code showing where some
interesting control flow decision is actually made. So here's a simple control
flow graph consists of two basic blocks. The first basic block is outside of the
loop, and consists of some initialization code. And then we have one basic block
here in the loop. The basic block consists of these three instructions. And at the
bottom of the block is a branch, a testing branch where either we, exit and go
someplace else or we loop around and execute the loop body again, okay? And the
body of a method can always be represented as a control flow graph. The convention
that we'll use is always a distinguished entry node so a distinguished start node
of the control flow graph and typically it'll just be obvious it'll be the one
listed at the top. And then there will be some return nodes or one or some nodes of
which you can return from and you know you have a return statements in the procedure.
And return nodes or places where you exit the procedure will always be terminal.
Meaning there will be no edges out of those blocks. Now, the purpose of
optimization is to improve a program's resource utilization. And for the purposes
of this classroom, when we talk about optimization in, in our examples and in
the videos we're gonna be talking about execution time. And we're gonna be talking
about, we're g onna be talking about making the program run faster. And this is
mostly what people are interested in. So most compilers do spent quite a bit of
effort on making programs run faster but it's important to realize that there are
many other resources that we could optimize for. And, actually for any
resource that you can imagine there probably is a compiler out there that
spend some effort optimizing for an insert domain domains of application. So for
example there are compilers we might care about code size. We might care about the
number of network messages sent, other things that are commonly optimized for our
memory usage, disk accesses so, so databases, for example. Try to minimize
the number of times you access the disk and, and power for battery powered
devices. And the important thing about optimization is that it should not alter
what the program computes. The answer still must be the same, okay? So we're
allowed to improve, the program's resource utilization, but we can't change what the
program will produce. Now, for languages like C and Cool, and all of the languages
that you're probably familiar with, there are three granularities of optimization
that people typically talk about. One is called local optimization, and those are
optimizations that apply to a basic block in isolation. So these are optimizations
that occur within a single basic block. Then there are what are called global
optimizations and this is really misnamed because it's not global across the entire
program. What people mean by global optimization is that implies to a control
flow graph. It's global across an entire function alright so, so global
optimizations would apply to a single function and optimizer across all the
basic blocks of that function. And finally there are inter-procedural optimizations
these are optimizations that work across method boundaries. They take multiple
functions and move things around to try to optimize the collection of functions as a
whole. Many compilers do one, in fact almost all compilers do one. Many, many
compilers today do two, but not very many actually do three, okay? So you see
decreasing numbers of compilers doing, these optimizations as you move up in the
granularity, and partly that's because the optimization's are more difficult to
implement so it's just more work to implement the inter-procedural
optimization's but also because a lot of the payoff is in the more local
optimizations. So, expanding on that last point a little bit more. It turns out
that, in practice, while we know how to do many, many optimizations. Often a
conscious decision is made not to implement the fanciest optimization that
is known in the research literature. And that's kind of an unfortunate thing from
my point of view being somebody who's really likes compilers and spent a lot of
time thinking about optimization. And maybe it's a little bit hard to accept for
the professional compiler researchers that, that people don't always want to
implement the latest and greatest optimization. But it's worth understanding
why that might not be the case and it boils down essentially to software
engineering. Some of these optimizations are really hard to implement, I mean
they're just complicated to implement. Some of the optimizations are costly in
compilation time. So even though the compiling happens offline, it is not part
of the running of the program, you know the programmer still has to wait while the
optimizing compiler compiles, does its compilation and if it takes hours or in
some cases days, to optimize a program, you know, that's not necessarily great.
And, some of these optimizations have low pay off. They might, always improve the
program, but they might only do it by a very small amount and unfortunately, many
of the fanciest optimizations in the literature have all three of these
properties. They're complicated, they take a long time to run, and they don't do very
much. And so it's not so surprising That and not all of these to get implemented in
production compilers. And this actually, you kn ow points out what the real goal is
in optimization. What we really want is maximum benefit for minimum cost. We're
really talking about a cost benefit ratio. So, like optimization costs a certain
amount, in code complexity, complexity of the compiler In programmer time I mean
waiting for the compiler to run and, and the benefit, the amount that it improves
the program has to be sufficient to justify those costs.