In this short video, I'm going to say a few words about a variation on local
optimization that applies directly to assembly code called Peephole
Optimization. The basic idea here is that instead of optimizing on intermediate code
we could do our optimizations directly on assembly code And people optimization is
one such technique. The peephole is, stands for a short sequence of usually
continuous instructions. So, the idea is that we have our program. We can see, we
can think of it as a long sequence of instructions and our peephole is some
window onto this program. So, if we have a peephole of size four, we can think of
ourselves as staring through a small hole at the program and all we can see is a
short sequence of four instructions and then we can optimize that sequence. So,
then we can slide the peephole around and optimize different parts of the program
And the, what the, what the optimizer will do is it will, you know, stare at this
short sequence of instructions and if it knows a better sequence it will replace
that sequence by the other one and then it will repeat this as I said. You know,
applying other transformations to, to possibly the same or other parts of the
assembly program. So, people optimizations are generally written as replacement
rules. So, the we'll have the window of instructions on the left. So, it'll be
some sequence of instructions and we'll know some other sequence of instructions
that we would prefer on the right. So, if we see this instruction sequence on the
left, then we'll replace by the one on the right-hand side. So, for example, if I
have a move from register b to register a and then I move back from register a to
register b well, that's the second move is useless, can, can just be deleted as a way
to replace this two instruction sequence by a one instruction, instruction
sequence. And this will work provided that there's no possible jump target here. So
if, if there's no possibility that the code would ever jump to this instruction
then that instruction can be removed. Another example, If I add i to the
register a, and then I subsequently add j to the register a, I can do a constant
folding optimization here, and combine those two add two additions into one
addition where I add the sum of i = j to the register A. So, many but not quite all
of the basic block optimizations that we've discussed in the last video, can be
cast also as peephole optimizations. So, for example if we are adding zero to a
register and we're storing it in another register, well, that can be replaced by a
register move. If we're moving a value from the same register to itself so this
is like a self-assignment, well, that instruction can just be deleted, replaced
by the empty sequence of instructions. And together for those two instructions would
be those two optimizations, excuse me, would be able to eliminate adding zero to
a register. So, first this would get translated into a move from a to a. And
then the move from a to a would get deleted. And as this little example
illustrates just like with local optimizations, people optimizations have
to be applied repeatedly to get the maximum effect. I hope this simple
discussion has illustrated for you that many optimizations can be applied directly
to assembly code and that there's really nothing magic about optimizing
intermediate code. So, if you have a program written in any language, source
language, intermediate language, assembly language. It makes sense to talk about
doing transformations of programs written in that language to improve the behavior
of the program. And it's also a good time here to mention that program optimization
is really a terrible term. The compilers do not produce optimal code and it's
purely an accident if a compiler were to somehow generate the best possible code
for a given program. Really, what compilers do is they have a bunch of
transformations that they know will improve the behavior of the program. And
they'll just improve it as much as they ca N. So, really what program optimization is
all about is program improvement. We're trying to make the program better but
there's no guarantee that we will reach the best possible code for a given program.