In this video we are going to continue our discussion on global data flow analysis by
taking a look at how global constant propagation works in detail. To begin,
let's review what the conditions are to do global constant propagation. So to replace
a use of a variable x by a constant k, we have to know the following property. That
on, that on every path to the use of x, the last assignment to the variable x is,
x equals the constant k, okay? And this has to be true again on every path to the
use of x. Now, global constant propagation can be performed at any point where this
property holds. What we're going to look at in this video, is the case of computing
the property for a single variable x at all program points. So we're going to take
one, we're going to focus on one variable x and we're going to compute whether it's
a constant at every program point. It's easy to extend the algorithm to compute
this property for all variables. One very simple but very efficient way to do that
is just to repeat the computation once for each variable in the method body. The way
we are going to compute the information that we want is to associate one of the
following values with the variable x at every point in the program. And, let's
start with the last one here we will assign x this special value here which is
pronounced top if x is not a constant. So if we can't figure out whether x is a
constant at a particular point in the program, then we'll just say x is top at
that point. And, this is going to be our safe situation. It's always okay to say we
don't know what the value of x is and when we say that x has a value top, and we
could say, we, we were essentially saying we don't know whether x is a constant or
not at this point in the program, x could have any value. Alright? Now, another
possibility is that we will say that x is some constant c, okay? So this is a
particular constant and if we say that x is a constant c at a program point, that
means, in fact, at that program point, we believe o r we have proven that x is
always that constant. Now, there is a third possibility which is not immediately
intuitive, perhaps. But, as we will see, plays a very important role in algorithms
for, for global constant propagation. And in fact, in all global data flow analysis,
and that is bottom, okay? So this value is pronounced bottom and intuitively the idea
anyway that is kind of opposite of top, alright? And the interpretation of bottom
is going to be that this statement never executes, alright? So, when we don't know
whether a statement is even executed at all we will say that x at that point has a
value bottom. Meaning that, as far as we know that point in the program is never
reached. It doesn't matter what the value of x is at that point because that
statement never executes. Alright, so we're going to assign x one of these three
kinds of values. Either bottom, some constant, or top. Let's begin by working
through an example by hand and our goal is going to be for every program point to
decide whether x could be a constant definitely not a constant, or whether we
think that statement might not ever execute, okay? So, execution will begin at
the top of this control flip graph. So this the entry point and before executions
begins, we don't anything about the value of x. So, I'm not making any assumptions
about what code came before this basic block and so to be safe, I will say that
at this point, x has some unknown value. We don't know what the value of x is, it
could be anything. So x = T, is the property that we want entry to the first
basic block. Now after the assignment x = three, that was indicated there, where
what point we're talking about. So, after the assignment x = three, we'll definitely
will know that x is the constant three. Alright, now there's something here that's
worth pointing out which is that our program points, the points that we're
attaching this knowledge to or these, these facts to are in between the statem
ents. So, when I say x = three at this program point, what I mean is that after
x, after this assignment has executed, x = three, but before this predicate of the
conditional has executed, I know that x = three, okay? So, the program points are in
between statements and there's a program point before and after every statement.
Alright, so the next thing that happens is this conditional branch. Notice that the
branch doesn't update x, doesn't even refer to x so after the branch executes
we'll definitely knows that x = three on both branches. Alright, now let's do the
right hand branch. The next thing that happens is the assignment to y that would
not affect the value of x. So after the assignment to y, we'll still know that x =
three, alright? Now let's take a look at the left hand branch so the first thing
that happens over here is another assignment to y. Well that won't affect
the value of x. After the assignment of Y we'll know that x = three. And now comes
to the assignment of x, alright. So after this assignment happens at this program
point we're going to know that the value of x is different. We're going to know
that x = four, alright. So, now after this statement we know x = four and after this
statement over here we know x = three, alright? Now what do we know then about
what happens before this statement, okay? The a = two x and I just want to point
out here. I said that there's a program point before and after every statement And
so this program point here, which is before this assignment to a is different
from the program points that are after x = four and y = zero. So intuitively, after x
= four we know that we're still on this path over here on the left and so we know
that x = four and over here after y = zero, we still know that we're on this
path is x = three. But, when we reach the point before a = two x, we no longer
know which path we're coming from. This is the point of the merge of these two paths
that both lead to this statement. And what can we say about the value of x here?
Well, there is no constant that we can assign to x because on o ne path x is
three and on the other path, x is four. And so what we have to say here is that
before this assignment executes, a = x, sorry, x = T. We don't know what the value
of x is. Another way of saying it is we know we, we don't know that x is a
constant, alright. So, after the assignment executes it doesn't affect the
value of x, we will also have that x = T. Now notice that once we have the global
constant information, once we know for every program point, what the state of x
is, it's going to be very easy to perform the optimization. We simply look at the
information associated with the statement and then it will tell us whether x is a
constant when that statement executes or not. And if x is a constant at that point,
then we can replace that use of x by the constant. And crucial question of course
is how do we compute these properties. So, we did this example by hand but how in a
systematic fashion, an arbitrary control flow graph do we actually compute these
properties for x for every program point? Now we're ready to talk about data flow
analysis algorithms and there's one basic principle that you see in all of these
algorithms that's worth mentioning right away. And that's that the analysis of a
complicated program can be expressed as a combination of very simple rules that
relate the change in information between adjacent statements. So we're just going
to focus on local rules and the way we're going to build our global data flow
analysis is actually by a combination of rules that look only at a single statement
and its neighbors. The idea behind the rules is going to be the push or transfer
information from one statement to the next And so for each statement s, we're going
to compute information about the value of x immediately before and after s. Remember
that's where, those are the program points that we want to attach information to. So
in particular we're going to have a function C. It stands for constant
information and C will take three arguments, takes the name of the variable,
x. It takes the stat ement that we're talking about, the particular statement in
the program that we're looking at. And then either in or out and this is what
distinguishes the value of x before s executes versus the value of x after s
executes. We're going to be defining a set of transfer functions that push
information or transfer information from one statement to another. And in the rules
for constant propagation we need to talk about a statement and its predecessors. So
we're going to say that every statement s has some set of immediate predecessors p1
through pn, alright? So, it's either of these statements that lead in one step to
the statement s. Let's do our first rule. So we have a statement s and it has some
set of predecessor statements, P1, P2, P3, P4. And the situation that we're
interested in here is, let's assume that x is top at the program point after one of
these predecessors. So, after some predecessor, it doesn't matter which one,
if it happens that x is top at the program point after that predecessor, well, then x
has to be top before the execution of s, okay? So that's what this rule says. It
says if the out of any predecessor for x is top, then the in of s for x is also
top. Alright, and this makes sense. It says that if we don't know whether x is a
constant on some path that leads to s, well then, we don't know that x is a
constant at s. Because for all we know, execution came down that particular, came
from that particular predecessor and so, we can't make any prediction about whether
s is, whether x is a constant before s executes. Now let's look at another
situation. Let's say that x is some constant C after the execution of some
predecessor. And that on a, after another predecessor a distinct predecessor x is a
different constant D. So D is not equal to C. Well then what do we know about x at
the program point before s executes? Well, we don't know anything, x has to be top,
because we don't know which constant, s will be, since we don't know which path
will reach s at run time. And this is the situation that we saw in the example we
did by hand. Another possibility is that the predecessors all agree on what the
value of x could be. So let's say that we have, you know, predecessor here and that
after it executes x is known to be the constant C and x is known to be the
constant C after this predecessor and x is known to be the constant C after this
predecessor. There's one other possibility. Let's say that after this
predecessor over here, all we know is that x is bottom, okay? And so what the rule
says is that if we have this situation where either x has the property bottom
after a predecessor or all the predecessors agree on the particular
constant that x could be, then before at the program point before s executes, we
know that x is going to guarantee to be the constant C. And if you think about it
for a second, it's easy to see why this is correct. First of all, clearly if we come
along one of the paths where x is known to be the constant C, since they all agree
and then when we get to s, x will definitely have the value C. What about
the bottom case? Well, remember what that means. That means that this statement is
never reached so there's some predecessor P here which never executes. Which means
if P never executes then we could never reach S along this path from P. So the
only paths that will reach s are the ones where x is known to be a constant,
alright? So that's why it's okay in this situation say that x, if control if
execution reaches s at all its guaranteed to reach it in a state where x is the
constant C. One last possibility is let's say that x is bottom for all the
predecessors, okay? And what does that mean? Well, that means that every
predecessor of S never executes so they're all unreachable. And therefore if every
predecessor of x never executes s itself can never execute, and so we can conclude
that entry to s, x is bottom. The first four rules that we just looked at relate
the out of one statement to the in of the next. We also have to have rules that
relate the in of a statement to the out of the same statement. So we have to push
information from the input of a statement to the output of the same statement. So,
once again, there are several cases. And let's take a look at an easy one first. If
x is bottom on an entry s, if the program point before s well, that says that at
the, that s is never reached, that s never executes. And therefore, x will be bottom
after s, after s as well. So if the program point before s is never reached,
the program point after s definitely can't be reached either. Another possibility is
that we're assigning x to constant C in this statement. In that case the out of
the statement is going to be equal to C. Alright, so it doesn't matter what the
state of x was before the statement, after we execute the statement, x will be the
constant C. And I should say there is a conflict with the previous rule. Okay, it
could be that x is bottom, before the statement. So rule six, has lower priority
than rule five. So we, so if we could say that x is bottom after the statement, we
would prefer you to say that so rule five would be applied first, and then if rule
five does not apply. So if x is some other constant D or x = T, then we would apply
this rule and we would conclude that x is the constancy afterwards and that makes
sense. If x is d or x is the, is top that means that control, as far as we know, can
reach this statement. And then what we're saying here is that well, after the
execution of this statement, if control can reach this statement after the
execution of it, x is guaranteed to be the constant C. Another possibility is that we
have an assignment to x but the right hand side is more complicated than a constant.
So this case is for everything other than the constant assignment. Okay, so this F
here just stands for some more complicated expression than just a simple constant.
And in this case we, we're just going to say we don't know what the value is, we're
not going to try to guess what the result of that computation is and we'll just say
that x = T. X, w e don't know what the value of x is after the execution of this
statement. And once again, rule five takes precedence so if rule five applies, then
we would apply then, then we would use that rule instead of rule seven. But, if
control can reach this statement, so up here x = C or x = T. Then we'll apply rule
seven and conclude that x is top after the statement. And finally Rule eight, another
possibility is that we're assigning to some variable other than x. And in that
case, if x = k before the statement then we just keep that value. Okay, so whatever
x was before the statement bottom, a constant or top, if the assignment is to
some other variable other than x then x will have the same property after the
statement executes. Now, we can put these rules together into an algorithm. For
every entry point, for every entry, statement to the program, we're going to
say on entry that we don't know anything about the value of x. So the program point
before that entry point we're gonna say that x has an unknown value, top. And then
everywhere else we're going to say that the value of x, is bottom, okay. And this
is actually important so we're going, what this intuitively is doing is its saying
well, as far as we know except for the entry point to the program, which can
definitely be executed, we don't know whether any of the other statements in the
control flow graph are actually ever executed and so we're going to assume
initially, that they're not. And we're just going to say that x has the value
bottom everywhere except at an entry point And now what we're going to do is a kind
of constraint satisfaction algorithm. We're going to pick some statement that
doesn't satisfy one of the rules, one through eight. And then we're going to
update it using the appropriate rules. So we'll look for places in the control flow
graph where the information is inconsistent according to the rules and
then we'll update, the information to make it consistent with the rules. Let's take a
look at our example again. So, we're going to start out by saying x = T at the entry
point, and then we're going to have all of our other program points And let me
indicate them here. Okay, so these are all the other program points that we have to
be concerned with. And there again, there's a program point before and after
every statement. And we are going to say the x = bottom for all of these. So, again
what this means is, that as far as we know, control doesn't reach any of these
points. We have not yet proven to ourselves that any of these statements can
execute. And now we just look around in the program and try to find places, where
the information is inconsistent according to the rules, and then we update the
information. Let me switch colors here. So, when we begin, the information is
consistent everywhere except at this first statement because if x is T before and
we're assigning x to value three. Well, then we should not have x = bottom as the
result. In fact this should be x = three. It should be the appropriate information
here and once we update that, then we see that this next statement is inconsistent
because now we know this statement is reachable. We have a statement here and
we're concluding that the point after is not reachable which is not, not correct
according to the rules. So that I believe that this is an application of rule eight.
We have a statement here that doesn't refer to x as and so whatever the value of
x was before the statement becomes the value of x after the statement so that
becomes x = three. And then, now we can see that this information is inconsistent.
The out of the statement here, is not consistent with the in of the statement
here. In this case, you know, it's just one predecessor. And so, the, the value
should be the same so x should be three. At this point And similarly x should be
three at this point. Here we have an assignment to a variable other than x.
That should, information should be the same before and after the statements, same
thing here. Now we have an assignment x. The point before that assignment is
reachable and so sin ce this is a constant assignment we should know that x is that
constant after the assignment. So here again we have a in and out issue so the
out of this statement is not consistent with the in of this statement. So this is
going to have to be updated but now, what should this be? Well, we have two
inconsistent predecessors and so this has to be top and then finally, an assignment
to x, sorry, an assignment to a state, to a variable other than x so the information
should just propagate across. And that, same is updated like this so now x is
known to be top afterwards. And now, if we look around at all the program points,
we'd see that all the information is consistent. All the rules, if you, if you,
if you check whether the information before and after a statement or across a
statement. I'm sorry, or between predecessors and successors is correct,
it's correct everywhere according to the rules and so we're done.