In this video, we're gonna continue our discussion of analysis of controlled flow
graphs by focusing on what is undoubtedly the most interesting aspect of the whole
problem, the analysis of loops. Here's an example of control flow graph with a loop
in it. And it turns out that the need for the special element bottom in our analysis
is intimately tied to the analysis of loops. And so, let's just think about how
we would do our constant propagation example analysis with this particular
control flow graph, all right. So, what do we know about x? Okay. So, initially, we
don't know anything so before we enter the control flow graph, its value, its top
and, and after the assignment of three, we'll know that x has the value three. The
conditional branch here, the predicate won't affect the value of x. So, it'll be
three on both branches. The assignment to y won't affect it so it'll be three here
as well. And now we come here okay, and let's focus on this statement right here.
So, the rule is that the analysis of x at y equals zero. Okay, So with a value of x
right here before, before the assignment to y. Is a function of all the
predecessors. So, we need to know what the value of x is on both of the incoming
edges. Okay. Well, we don't have a value down here yet. So, the question is, you
know, what is the value of x here on this edge? And in order to figure that out,
we'd have to look at its predecessors. Okay, what are its predecessors? Well,
there's this point here after the predicate there's this point here between
the two statements, and then there's this point here after the execution of y. We're
just following the edges backwards here. Looking at, you know, where we need to
know information for x. We need to know it here, we need to know it here, and we know
it here, alright? And then because of this edge, that means we again need to know it
at both of the predecessors of y = zero. So, now we're in the loop and this isn't
too surprising. I mean, if you have, if information about x depends on t he
predecessors of a statement and you do follow that recursively then you're gonna
wind up going around loops like this. And, and there's no good way at least there's
no, no particularly immediately obvious way to solve this problem. So, how do we I
get information about the predecessor the predecessors of y = zero when they depend
on themselves? So, to be more precise looking at that particular statement again
in order to compute whether x is constant at the point right before the statement y
= zero, we need to know whether x is constant as the two predecessor and that
information depends on his predecessors, which include y = zero. Okay, so this is
the conundrum. So, how are we to solve this recursive problem. And there's a
standard solution that, that is actually used in many areas of Mathematics and not
just in the analysis of, of loops. When you have these kinds of recurrence
relationships or recursive equations. And the standard solution is to break the
cycle by starting with some initial guess. So, you have some initial approximation
that is really not perhaps even expected to be the final result but allows you to
get going. So, and so, what we're going to do is that because of the cycles, all of
the points, all the program points have to have values at all times. And so we're
going to assign an initial value and that is what bottom is for. And the initial
value bottom means, so far as we know, control never reaches this point. Remember
this, we've said this quite a while ago on several videos ago. And this will allow us
to make progress. And to see that let's go ahead and analyze this control flow graph
now where we assume that all points, and at all points, initially, x has the value
bottom except at the entry point. So, the entry point is special. Here, we assume
that we don't know anything about x because we know the control reaches the
initial point. But, initially, we're going to just say, well, x is bottom everywhere
else. Okay, so, [inaudible] the bottom there, [inaudible] bottom there, okay, I'm
gonna just fill in all the values. And I'm just writing it everywhere here. And
there's really another one right here after the merge of these two paths. So, I
indicate that. All right, so there, now we have our initial setup and now remember
what the procedure is, we go and look where the information is inconsistent and
we update it. So where is the place where the information is inconsistent? Well,
clearly it's not correct here, all right, because we know that after if, if control
reaches the point before x = three, then after the assignment, x will be equal to
three. Again the predicate will not change the value of x, so we have to update the
results of the two branches after the predicate, and after it's assignment, that
doesn't affect x to make that information consistent that we have that. Now, let's
go back to our interesting case. Here we know that x = three on this branch coming
in to y = zero. And, so far as we know, control never reaches the other
predecessor. So, we're gonna start out by assuming that, that, that part, that path
is never taken. And if that path is never taken, then it won't contribute anything.
And s, at this point in the program, we will know that x = three. So, assuming
that all this information is correct we will be able to conclude that x = three at
this point. And notice how we've been able to break the cycle here and get started.
So, we just assume that the, you know, this last edge in the cycle never executes
and if that's not correct, we'll find out later and this value down here will become
something other than bottom and then we'll update the assignment again. Alright, so
let's continue on. So, we have x = three before y is assigned zero. So the
assignment of y will not affect the value of x. So, make the information afterward
consistent we'll have to make x=3 there. Now, we have a merge of two paths. Okay.
So, the, at this point here before the execution of this assignment we will also
know that x = three. The assignment a will not affect x. We'll update that point
there and the predicate will not affect the value of x. So, we'll know that x =
three on the back edge. And now this information has changed. We now know the
control can reach this edge cuz we followed the control path all the way
here. We have some new information about x and so now we have to double check that
everything is still okay. So, here we have x = three on this edge, x = three on this
edge and our previous conclusion that x = three on the entry to the statement y =
zero. Well, that is also consistent. There are no places left in the control flow
graph that are inconsistent. So, all the information is consistent with all the
rules And so we're done, and this is the final analysis. We're able to conclude
that all, at all of these points here, like I say, every point except the entry
point, that x is in fact, the constant three.