In this video, we're going to look at another global analysis called liveness
analysis. So, in the past several videos we've looked at a procedure for globally
propagating constants through a control flow graph And let's, here's, here's one
of the control flow graphs we've been looking at and recall that this algorithm
that we discussed would be sufficient to show that we could replace this use of x
here by the constant three. And once we do that. This assignment x might no longer be
useful. It might not be used anywhere And so we could potentially delete this
statement from the program And that would be a real optimization, an important
optimization to do. However, we can only do that if x is not used elsewhere in the
program. So let's be a little more careful about what we mean by saying that x is not
used. So down here is a use of x, a reference to x, in a statement. And,
clearly this particular reference to x, is, use, picking up the value that's
defined by this right x here. So, we say that the right of x here, is live. This
one is live. Okay, And what that means is that the value may be used in the future.
So, live, equals, may be used. In the future, Okay? So the value written to x at
this line of code maybe used by some subsequent instruction And here it's not
just that it may be used. It's actually guaranteed to be used because there's only
one path. And that one path has a reference to x on it before there's
another assignment to x. Okay? So this particular value of x as written here is
guaranteed to be used. But in general we don't require that. We just mean there has
to be a possibility that it will be used. Now in contrast let's take a look at this.
Other statement in this example, Here, we assign x a value three but this assignment
x, this value of x is never used. This one, is dead. Alright? Because the value
three here is overwritten by the value four before there's any use of, the
variable x, Okay? So this particular right to x will never see the light of day.
It'll never get used by any part of the program. And we say that it is dead. So,
to summarize a variable x is live as a statement S if, there exist some statement
that uses x. Okay. So, some other statement S prime that uses x, and there
is some path from S to S prime and there is no intervening assignments on that path
to x. Alright? So, there needs to be an assignment to x, at some statement S there
is some path through the program that reaches a read of x. Add sum statement to
S prime, and along that path, there is no right to x, Okay? And if this situation
arises, then we say that this value written in this first statement s is live.
Now if a value is not live, then it is dead. And a statement that assigns to x is
going to be dead code if x is dead after the assignment. So, if we know that
immediately after the assignment, immediately after this assignment to x,
there is no possibility that a value of x will be used in the future. Well then the
assignment was useless, and the entire statement can be removed. Alright, So dead
assignments can be deleted from the program, But notice that in order to do
that we have to have the liveness information. We need to know whether x is
dead at this point. So, once again, what we want to do is to have global
information about the control flow graph. In this case, the property is whether x
will be used in the future. We want to make that information local to a specific
point in the program, so we can make a local optimization decision. Alright, And
just like for constant propagation, we're going to define in a, an algorithm for
performing liveness analysis And it's going to follow the same framework. If
we're going to express liveness in terms of information transferred between
adjacent statements, just as we did for copy of constant propagation And it's
gonna turn out that liveness is actually quite, If it's simpler, or somewhat
simpler, than constant propagation, since it's just a Boolean property. Eh, you
know, it's either true of false. Alright So let's take a look at some of the rules
for liveness. So here, we're defining what it means for x to be live at this point
here. So we're immediately after p is x live And it's going to be live. Remember
what the intuition is. The intuition is that a, the variable x is live right after
p if the value of x is used on some path. On one of the paths that begin at p.
Alright, And so, in order to know whether it's live, we're going to take the
liveness information at each of the input points. So that would be here, here, here,
and here. So each of the successor statements after p And we're gonna ask, is
x live at any of those points? So it's just a big or over the liveness of x and
all of the successors of p And that's the liveness of x at the out of p. Next, let's
consider the effect of individual statements on the liveness of x. So, the
first rule is, that if we have a statement, and it reads the value of x,
Okay? So here, we have an assignment statement, and on the right hand side, it
refers to x, so its reading x Then, x is live Before that statement. Clearly, x is
just about to be used on the end of this statement, and so x is live at that point.
Alright? So if a statement, or if, if a statement reads the
value of x, then the in of that statement, x, is true. Sorry, the liveness of x is
true. A second case is when a statement writes the value of x So here we have an
assignment to x And the rest of the statement does not refer x Does not read
the value of x. So there's no x in E. Okay So in this situation x is not live before
the statement. X is not live or we can say that x is dead Before the statement And
why is that? Well, we're overriding the value of x, so whatever value, x had
before this statement is never gonna be read. Okay, Because the ee here, the
right-hand side of the assignment, doesn't refer to x And, so, immediately before the
statement, the current value of x is never gonna be used in the future. And so x is
dead at that point. And finally, the last case is what if we have a statement that
does not refer to x? Okay, So it neither reads no r writes x. Well, then whatever
the line this is of x after the statement, it has the same liveness, before this
statement. So if x is live here. Then x will be live here. Okay, and similarly, if
x is dead After the statement. Then x must be dead before the statement. And that's
because x if x is not use in the future after the statement S then it still want
be use in the future before the statement S. Since the statement S neither reads nor
write x. So those are the only four rules and now I can give the algorithm. So
initially we left the liveness information for x be false at all program points And
then we repeat the following until all the statements satisfy the rules one through
four, and just has it's the same algorithm that we used for constant propagation. We
pick some statement where the information is inconsistent and then up, update the
information at that statement with the appropriate rule. So let's do a simple
example, something with a loop. So let's begin, say by initializing x to zero, and
then what should our loop body do? Well, we can check whether x is equal to ten,
and if it is, we'll, we'll exit, the loop And let's assume that x is dead on exit.
So x is not refer to outside of the loop. In other wise if x is not ten Then we will
increment x and we'll branch back to the top of the loop. So this is a very, very
silly little program. It just counts to ten and then exits. Well let's do the
lightness now to see where x is life. So since x is dead here on exit it's clearly
gonna be dead on the out Of, of this, conditional on this branch, Okay? So I
should say that x is not live. So we're using booleans here, so that's x's,
liveness would be false And we're assuming And x is also, not live everyplace else,
initially. Okay And so, there's a program point in there, also Where the liveness of
x is false. Okay, So now, let's propagate the information. Well, so here we have
read of x. And let me switch colors here. So here we have a read of x. So in fact
the information's inconsistent here because ri ght before this statement since
we have a read of x, x must be live. So in fact, x is live at this point. Now notice
that this statement both reads and writes x. Okay? But the rule that says x is live
before, when we do a read, takes priority here Because, the read happens before the
write. So we'll read the old value of x, before we write the new value of x, Okay.
So the old value of x does get used, and that's why x is live immediately before
this statement. Okay, so then here's another, read of x. Okay, so on the, so
the point immediately before this when I left out one program point here, x is also
Y. Okay, And then following edges backwards, well, that means x is gonna be
live on the back edge of the loop And it's also gonna be live by going into the
initialization block. Alright? Now we come back around here and we see that we're
done 'cause x is already known to be, live within the loop body. And now, live, x is
also live here And then the question is, you know, what about this point on, the
entrance, at the entrance to the control flow graph? Well, there's a right of x And
with no read of x on the right-hand side. So, in fact, x, is not live on entry to
this control flow graph. So in fact, x is dead at this point. So whatever value x
has when we enter the control flow graph, it will never be used in the future.
Alright, and so that is the correct liveness information for every
program point in this example. Now another thing you can see from our little example
is that values change from false to true, but not the other way around. So every
value starts at false, and it can change at most once. To say that the value is
actually live, the property becomes true, and then it won't ever change back to
false again. So, going back to orderings, We only have two values in this analysis,
false and true And the ordering is that false is less than true. Okay, And we
know, so everything starts at the lowest possible element of the ordering and they
only move up, and so they can be promoted to true, but no t vice versa And so since
each value can only change once, termination is guaranteed. That eventually
we're guaranteed to have consistent information throughout the control flow
graph, and the analysis will terminate.