To wrap up and summarize our discussion of the global analysis of control flow graphs,
we've talked about two kinds of analysis in the past several videos. Constant
propagation is what is called a forwards analysis Because information is pushed
from the inputs to the outputs. So if you think about a control flow graph. What
happens in control flow analysis is that information flows in this direction.
It flows in the same direction as computation. If I have a constant up here
x is assigned constant down here, and x is used later on and that constant will flow
forward to the uses. Okay So information flows in the same direction as computation.
Liveness on the other hand is a backwards analysis. Information is pushed
from outputs back towards inputs. So here in this example and let me change
colors. Here we see that x is live before the statement. And that liveness gets propagated
in the other direction. It gets propagated against the control, against the
flow, of execution, backwards towards the beginning of the program.
So they're many other kinds of global flow analysis in the literature. The
constant propagation analysis and the liveness analysis are two of the most important.
There is a number of others that are also very important and many, many
more that people have investigated. Almost all these analyses can be classified
as either forward or backward. There are some analyses and some important
ones that are neither forward nor backward. That information is basically pushed
in both directions. And the other thing is that the, almost all the analyses
in the literature that do global flow analysis anyway also follow this methodology
of local Rules that relay information between adjacent program points.
So it, it's the local rules part that's important. So we break down the complicate
d problem of analyzing an entire control flow graph into a collection
of rules that only do ver, propagate information very, very locally.