PROFESSOR: In this video, we're going to begin our discussion of global program optimization.
And it turns out that, in order to talk about global optimization, there's another topic
that we have to deal with first known as data flow analysis.
Let's begin by reviewing the simple basic-block optimizations. In particular, constant propagation
and dead code elimination. So here's a little piece of code. And you'll notice that there's
an assignment of a constant X. And we know from our lecture in local optimizations that
that constant assignment could be propagated forward to the uses of X. If the basic block
is in single assignment form, this is particularly easy to do. And then if the value of X here
is not used anyplace else in the program, that statement is dead and can be deleted.
So here's a simple example over a basic block combining constant propagation and dead code
elimination.
Now, these optimizations can be extended to an entire control-flow graph. So here now
we have a nontrivial control-flow graph. Remember, a control-flow graph is a graph of basic blocks
where the nodes are the basic blocks and the edges show the transfers of control between
basic blocks. And so this first basic block here has a testament, an if statement. And
it'll go to one basic block if the test is true. Into a different basic block if the
test is false.
Now, in this control-flow graph, we can observe that X is assigned a constant. And then down
here, there are uses of X. And, in fact, in this particular case, it is going to be safe
to replace this use of X by the constant 3. So just like we propagated constants in a
single basic block, we can also, at least in some circumstances, propagate constants
across entire control-flow graphs.
Now, it turns out that there are some situations in which it's not safe to propagate constants.
So here again let's observe that we have an assignment of X, an assignment of a constant
X, and down here we have a use of X. But we cannot replace this X here by 3. And why is
that? Well, that's because over here, we have another assignment X where X gets the value
4.
And the interesting thing about this example is that notice that X is only assigned constants.
So X is assigned a constant here, and X is assigned a constant here, but this value of
X down here is not known. We don't know which constant it's going to be, because if we come
from this path in the execution, then X will be 4. And if we come from this path, the value
of X will be 3. And so we can't replace x here by either one of those values, and it's
not safe in this case to propagate constants to this use of X.
And so the question then is, how do we know when it is OK to globally propagate constants?
Now, for constant propagation, it turns out there's a simple criteria. To replace a use
of x by a constant k, we have to know the following fact that on every path to the use
of x. So every path that leads to the use of x, the last assignment that x is, x is
equal to k. So every single path that goes to x-- and this make sense, I think, intuitively--
we must have assigned a constant x along that path. And that must, in fact, be the last
assignment to x on each path.
Let's take a look at our example again, and I'll switch colors here. So here we have the
assignment X equals 3, and down here we have the use of X. And now what we need to do is
we need to check, in order to replace this X by 3, that on every path it arrives at this
X. It reaches this X that X is assigned 3 along that path. Well, there are only two
paths. There's this path, and there's this path. And it's easy to see that this assignment
is on both of those paths. And therefore the last assignment done on both paths, on all
paths, is X equals 3. And therefore we can replace this X by 3.
In contrast, with this use of X in this example, we have a path here where X is assigned 3,
and we have a path here that reaches along this path. Let me draw the whole path, actually.
And along this path, the last assignment to X is 4, and so we cannot propagate any constant
value to this use of X.
In general, the correctness condition that a variable is assigned the same constant to
lock all paths to a use of that variable is not that easy to check, because 'quot;all paths'quot;
includes paths that go around loops as well as paths that go through conditionals, as
we saw in the example. So checking these conditions is done through a family of techniques called
'quot;global dataflow analysis,'quot; and it's designed specifically to check conditions like this.
And essentially, global dataflow analysis is called 'quot;global'quot; because it requires an
analysis of the entire control-flow graph.
Stepping back for a moment, there are many global optimization tasks that we would like
a compiler to perform. A constant propagation, global constant propagation, is just one of
those. Now, it turns out that all of these global optimization problems share several
common traits. So first of all, the optimization always depends on knowing some property X
at a particular point in the program. So we want to know some piece of very local information.
So, for example, is X at a particular point in the program guaranteed to be a constant?
OK? That's the property for a constant propagation.
Now, however, even though we want to know some local fact, something that's specific
to a particular point in the program, proving this fact requires knowledge of the entire
program, so at least the entire control-flow graph. So as we saw in the case of constant
propagation, to figure out whether X is a constant at a particular point in the program
requires reasoning about all the paths that lead to that statement. And that is a global
property. So when you think about all-paths, that could be a path from the entry point
of the method all the way through loops and across conditionals to the particular statement.
So, in general, that's a very hard problem to solve. And for certain kinds of questions,
it's really extremely expensive to solve it exactly. The thing that saves us is that it
is OK always to be conservative. So typically for these optimizations-- and if we want to
know some property X-- then what we really want to know is either X is definitely true--
So if we say that the property is true, then we have to be right. We can't make a mistake.
But it is always OK to say that you don't know. So it's OK to give up and say we don't
know whether the property holds or not. Because of the worst case, we just don't do the optimization.
If we can't establish the conditions that would mean it was definitely correct to the
optimizations, then we want to play it safe and not do the optimization.
So having approximate techniques or techniques that don't always give the correct answer
to the questions that we wanted to ask is OK as long as we are always right when we
say that the property holds and otherwise we just say that we don't know whether the
property holds or not.
To sum up, global dataflow analysis is a standard technique or family of techniques for solving
problems with the characteristics that we just discussed. And global constant propagation
is one example of an optimization that requires global dataflow analysis. And in the next
several videos, we'll be looking at global constant propagation and another dataflow
analysis in more detail.