In the last several videos, we've been talking about doing a kind of abstract
computation. Computing with elements like Bottom the Constants and Top. And, in this
video, we're going to start to generalize those ideas a little bit. And the first
thing we're going to talk about, the first step towards that generalization, is to
talk about orderings of those values. First, I'd like to introduce a technical
term. These values that we compute within program analysis, things like Bottom, the
Constants and Top, these are called Abstract Values. And that's just to
distinguish them from the Concrete Values, so the Concrete Values are the actual
run-time values that a program computes with. Things like actual objects, and
numbers and things like that. And the Abstract Values here the program analysis
uses are in general, more abstract. Some particular Abstract Values can stand for a
set of possible Concrete Values. And in a particular set of Abstract Values we're
using for concept propagation, there's only one very Abstract Value and that's
the Top and it stands for any possible run time value. So it stands for the entire
set of run time values. Anyway, it turns out that there is a way to simplify the
presentation of, of the analysis that we have been discussing by ordering the
Abstract Values. So we're going to say is that Bottom is less than all the constants
and that, and all the Constants are less than Top. And so if we draw a picture with
the lower values drawn towards at the bottom picture and the higher values drawn
at the top. And, and edges between values where there's a relationship, we get this
diagram here. So you have bottom down here, underneath all the other values,
Bottom is less than every Constant. Okay. So notice that all the constants are here
on the middle level, alright? And also notice that the constants are not
comparable to each other, alright? So this ordering is different than the numeric
ordering. So zero is not less than one for example. Zero and one are inco mparable,
as are every other pair of Constants. So you have, you know, Bottom at the Bottom.
You have all the Constants in the middle and they're incomparable, And then, bigger
than everything else is Top. Now with the ordering defined, there's a useful
operation we can define on collections of elements and that is the Least Upper
Bound, or LUB, alright? And, and this means is taking the smallest element that
is bigger than everything in the Least Upper Bound. So, for example, if I have
the Least Upper Bound of Bottom and one, that is equal to one, okay? If I had the
Least Upper Bound of Top and Bottom, that is equal to Top. And perhaps more
interesting one, the Least Upper Bound of one and two, so two incomparable Constants
here. And remember, the meaning of the Least Upper Bound, it's the smallest
element in the ordering that's bigger than everything over which we're taking the
Least Upper Bound. So we just have two things here in our Least Upper Bound. But
the Least Upper Bound of one and two, the smallest thing that's bigger than both of
them, or greater than or equal I should say, both of them is Top, okay? And so,
the Least Upper Bound then, if you think about it, if you draw, draw our picture
again. So we had Bottom and we had Top, and if you pick out some points here,
let's say we want to take the Least Upper Bound of Bottom and two, you're just
picking the smallest thing that's bigger than both. Well, that's going to be two
itself, similarly two on Top, you will get Top. And then if have anything that's
incomparable, then you have to pick something that's bigger than both of them
and in this case that will always end up being Top for this very simple ordering,
alright? Then given this idea of the Least Upper Bound, it turns out that rules one
through four, all they're doing is computing the Least Upper Bound. So the in
of a statement is just equal to the Least Upper Bound of the out of all the
predecessors. Alright, and that's all that rules one through four we're saying. And
if you remember what we had there, we had, you know, we had a bunch of predecessors
and then there's some kind of statement s, and all we're doing is whatever the
information is on these predecessors, we're just taking the Least Upper Bound
over it, all right? And that is the information on entry to, to s. The
ordering on the Abstract Values also helps to clarify another important aspect of our
analysis algorithm which is why it terminates. So remember the algorithm's
termination condition is to repeat to repeatedly apply the rules until nothing
changes, until there are no more inconsistencies in the control flow graph
and there's no information left to update. Well, just because we say we're going to
repeat until nothing changes, that doesn't guarantee that eventually nothing changes.
It could be that, that goes on forever, that we always introduce new
inconsistencies with every update and we never actually get to the point where all
the information is consistent. So, the ordering actually shows why that can't
happen and the algorithm is guaranteed to terminate. So remember that in every
program point except the entry point, the values start as Bottom. So, they start at
the lowest place in the ordering. And then if you look carefully at the rules, it's
easy to see that the rules can only make the values increase at a program point. So
Bottom can be promoted, can be changed at a given program point up to some Constant
and, and, and another update could raise that Constant to Top but of course, once
we get the Top, there's no greater element. And if the rules can only make
the elements increase, then eventually we have to run out of elements that could be
increased, okay? So what that says is that each piece of information we're computing,
for every statement, for every variable, and for either in or out, it can change at
most twice, okay? So it can go from a Bottom to a Constant, and from Constant to
a Top but after that, it will never be updated again. And what this means is that
the constant propagation algorithm that we've described is actually linear in
program size. So the number of steps is gonna be bounded by the number of c values
that we're trying to compute times two, cuz each one of those could change two
times. And since there's one value for the entry and exit over the in and out of
every statement, the total number of steps that the algorithm can possibly take is
the number of program statements times four.