In this video, we're going to begin a discussion of Register Allocation which is
one of the most sophisticated things that compilers do to optimize performance and
also involves many of the concepts that we've been discussing in global flow
analysis. Recall that intermediate code can use unlimited numbers of temporaries
and this simplifies a number of things. Particularly it simplifies optimization so
we don't have to worry about preserving the right number of registers in the code.
But, it does complicate the final translation into assembly code cuz we
might be using too many temporaries and this is actually a problem in practice.
So, it's not uncommon at all for intermediate code to use more temporaries
than there are registers on the target machine. The problem then is to rewrite
the intermediate code to use no more temporaries than there are machine
registers and the way we're going to do that is we're going to assign multiple
temporaries to each register. So, we're going to have a many-one mapping. A many
to one mapping from temporaries to registers, okay? And, clearly there's a
little bit of an issue here if we really are using many temporaries, we will not be
able to fit them all into a single register. So there needs to be some kind
of a trick and we'll say what that trick is in a few minutes and there will be
situations actually when this will fail, we'll have to have some kind of back up
plan. But our default plan is to try to put as many temporaries as possible into
the same machine register. And doing all of this without changing the behavior of
the program. So, how can we do this? Magic thing. How can we actually make a single
register hold multiple values? Well, the trick is that it's fine for registers to
have local values as long as it only has one value at a time. So, let's consider
this program, I'm going to switch colors here. Okay. Simple three statement program
and notice here that a is used in the first two statements. So it's written in
the first statement, read in the second stateme nt e is written in the second
statement and read in the third statement and that is only written in the third
statement. And actually, these three values a, e and f, they don't ever really
co-exist at the same time but at the time we've read a we are really done with it.
We've all the uses that they are going to have in this little code fragment. Here,
I'm assuming that a and effort are not used anywhere else and so it turns out
that a, e, and f could all actually live in the same register. Alright, that's
assuming that a and e are dead after their uses. And what will that look like, well
let's allocate them all to a particular register r1 and let's assign c, d, and b
into their own individual registers and the code would like this, r1 would be r2 +
r3, and then r1 would be r1 + r4 and r1 would be r1 - one. And so now notice how
this is just a transliteration of the code over here into registers but there is a
many one mapping of names on the left to register names on the right. A register
allocation is an old problem. In fact, it was first recognized way back in the 1950s
in the original Fortran project but originally, register allocation was done
with a fairly crude algorithms and who is rapidly or very quickly noticed that was
actually a bottle neck in the quality of code generation that actually limitations
on the ability of register allocation and do a good job have a really significant
effect on the overall equality, overall quality of the code that compilers could
produce. And then about 30 years later, in 1980, a breakthrough occurred where people
discovered or a group of researchers at IBM discovered a register allocation
scheme based on graph coloring. And the great thing about this scheme is that it's
pretty simple. It's easy to explain. It's global, meaning it takes advantage of
information from the entire control flow graph at the same time and also happens to
work well in practice. And here's the basic principle that underlies the modern
register allocation algorithms. So, if I have two temporaries t1 and t2, I want to
know when they can share register. So, they're allowed to share a register and
they're allowed to be in the same register if they are not live at the same time,
okay? So like I said, any point in the program in most one of t1 or t2 as live.
And we are more concise which I already said was partially is, is that if t2, t1
and t2 are live at the same time, okay? Meaning that there's, there's some program
point were both are live then they cannot share a register, alright? So this is the
negative form of the statement and it just tells you that if, if you need two values
at the same moment in time, then they have to be in separate registers. Let's take a
look at a control flow graph and now, we know that in order to do the register allocation
to solve the register allocation at least in this in this way, we're going to need
liveness information. So, let's compute the live variables for each point of this
program. So, here it is and I'll just walk through it very quickly. Let's assume that
on exit from this loop that only b is live. So b is the output of this piece of
the code and it's used elsewhere but none of the other variables are live. So, now
if we work backwards, remember that line is a backward analysis. We'll see here
that b is written so it's not live before the statement but f and c are read. So,
both c and f are live before this basic block. Okay, and similarly if we, if we go
up another level here, here we see that e is now alive and f is dead because f was
written here and e was read. And over on this path, here we have another exit where
b is live and now at this point here right after this basic block the set of lot
variables that are live is b, c, and f because b is live on one path and c and f
are live on the other path. Remember for something to be live, it only has to be
live on some, in some future possible evolution of the execution. So, on some
path out of this node is a variables live, then it's live at the exit from this.
Working backwards here. B, c, and f are live here because e is read. And b, c, and
f are not referred to in this statement and so they just propagate upwards. Here b
is removed from the live f because it's written but d is added and set here and
similarly, for the other edges in this graph. If you go and check all the other
edges you will see that the live set is correct and it just follows from the
simple rules we gave in the previous video. But how are going to use the
liveness information to do register allocation? Well, we're going to construct
and undirected graph and in this graph, there will be a node for each temporaries
so each variable will have a node in the graph and there'll be an edge between two
temporaries if they are live simultaneously at some point in the
program, alright? So backing up and looking at our little example here, we can
see for example at this point in the program c and e are both live. They're
both in the live set after this basic block executes. So c and e cannot be in
the same register. Alright, continuing on, this is called, this data structure, this
graph is called the Register Interference Graph or RIG for short. And again, the
basic idea is that two temporaries can be allocated in the same register if there is
no edge connecting them in the register interference graph. So, here's a register
interference graph for our example. This is the graph constructed from the code and
the line analysis that we're given a few slides ago and you know, it's easy to read
off from the graph what the constraints are. So, for example b and c cannot be in
the same register because b and c are connected by an edge. Okay, seeing that
they're live simultaneously at some part, some point in the program and so they have
to live in different registers. On the other hand, there is at, there is no edge
between b and d, okay. So, this edge is missing and therefore, it's possible that
b and d could be allocated in the same register. They are live ranges all the
times in which they are alive do not overlapped. So a great thing about the
register interference graph is that it extracts exactly the information needed to
characterize a legal register assignment. So, it gives us a representation of all
the possible legal register assignments. Now, I haven't said I haven't actually get
a register assignment out of the register interference graph, but the first step is
to characterize the problem in some kind of precise way. And the graph of, cannot
live in the same register constraints does that for us. The other thing that is good
about is a, is a global view of the register requirements meaning it's over
the entire control flow graphs. So, takes into account information from every part
of control flow graph which will help us to make good global decisions about what
value is very important to live in registers. And finally, the other thing to
notice is that, that after reconstruction, the register allocation for algorithm is
going, is architecture independent. I haven't shown you the algorithm so you
just have to believe the statement for the moment but it's going to turn out that
were not going to depend on any property of the machine except for the number of
registers. So, that's the only thing we need to know about the machine in order to
take a RIG and, and do register allocation using it.