So far we've talked about what a register interference graph is and to
find the notion of a graph coloring but we haven't actually talked about how to
compute graph coloring so that's the next issue that we have to deal with. And
unfortunately it isn't easy so graph coloring is a very hard problem. If you
had a computer science theory class, then it would mean something to you when I say
that it is an NP-hard problem to compute a coloring of the graph. If you have not
heard about NP hardness before, that's not a problem. The important thing is that
nobody knows an efficient algorithm for this problem so there's no fast procedure
known. And so the solution that we will talk about, one that every compiler uses,
is to use some heuristics or basically approximation techniques that don't the
problem completely. But, there's a second problem which is that a coloring might not
even exist for a given number of registers. It might be that we only have
eight registers on our machine and there is no coloring of the graph that uses
fewer than say nine or ten colors and so we're going to have to have our way to
deal with that and we'll talk about that later. I won't say anything more about the
solution to that problem just now. So, now I'll present the most popular heuristic
for coloring register interference graphs. And the basic idea is very, very simple.
So, what we'll do is we'll pick a node t that has fewer than k-neighbors in the
register interference gr aph, okay. And this is actually the key things to just
find any node in the graph that has fewer than k-neighbors. And then we'll eliminate
t in its edges from register interference graphs so we'll just delete that node and
all the edges adjacent to it. And then if the resulting sub-graph is k-colorable
then so is the original graph. The idea here is to do a dividing conquer kind of
approach. We pick one node, we delete it from the graph, we color the remainder of
the graph. It's a smaller problem with one fewer nodes and then when we're done with
that, I claim that we can find the coloring for the original graph and why is
that? That has fewer than k-neighbors and let's just say for the sake of argument
that it has two neighbors and here's the rest of the graph. So, this big circle is
the rest of the graph, here is the node t that we're going to delete, and let's say
that it just has two neighbors, okay. So, now what we're going to do is we're going
to, conceptually we're going to delete t from the graph Well, let's draw a picture
here. So, let's say we have a node and so, and then we're going to color the
sub-graph. Now, let's say that we succeed in coloring the sub-graph. So, we can now
have a coloring for this big ball in red. And now we want to construct the coloring
for that big ball plus this node t. Well, since we said there are fewer than k
colors. I needed to color the sub-graph and that too is certainly less than k.
Well, then there must be a leftover color for t so we can look at all the colors of
the nodes that are adjacent to t. Since there are fewer than k of these, they
can't use all k of the colors and then we can pick one of the leftover colors for t.
So, here's a procedure that works very well in practice. First, we pick a node t
that has fewer than k-neighbors. We put t on the stack and remove it from the
register interference graph and then we recourse. We repeat this procedure until
the graph is empty. So, we just keep choosing nodes that have fewer than
k-neighbors, pushing them onto a stack a nd delete them from the graph and we do
that until the graph is completely empty out. And that's the first phase so that's
part one, okay. And then in part two, we assign a coloring. We build a coloring for
the nodes on the stack. And, the nodes are processed in reverse order they were
added. The last node added to the stack is processed first and each step, what we do
is, we pick a color that is different from those assigned to the already colored
neighbors. So the idea is we pick a node off a stack, we pop it off the stack, and
we add it back into the graph along with the edges that it had in the original
graph and then we color it. So then we look we look at its neighbors, since we
had fewer than k-neighbors at the time it was deleted, it will have fewer than k at
the time we send it back in, there will be a color available for it. We color it and
then we repeat, by picking another node from the stack. And we do that until all
the nodes of the graph have been processed. Let's do an example. Here is
our register interference graph so we are going to process this RIG with k = four so
initially we have the entire register interference graph and the stack is empty.
Alright? So the first step is to pick some node that has fewer than four neighbors.
So let's pick A, since it only has two neighbors. So what do we do? We delete A
from the graph and we push it onto the stack. So after that step our graph,
here's our graph with A removed and here's our stack, alright. Now we're going to
pick another hat has fewer than k-neighbors and if we look, sorry, fewer
than four neighbors. And if we look at this graph, we can see that we have the
option of picking a few different nodes. We can pick D or B. Actually, there's only
two different nodes we could pick, C, E, and F all have four neighbors. So let's
remove D. An arbitrary choice here, it doesn't matter which one we pick. And now
the stack will have D and A on it and our graph will be down to these four nodes.
And now something interesting to observe here, is that all the nodes at this point
have fewer than four neighbors. And so, since every node in the graph has fewer
neighbors than the number of colors we're allowed to use, at this point the graph
coloring is guaranteed to succeed. Because every time we remove a node we can only
reduce the number of neighbors of every other node in the graph. It's also
interesting to note That even though some of the notes had four neighbors in the
previous step and so might not have been colorable. We couldn't choose them at that
step because potentially a coloring of the neighbors would use up all the colors.
Notice that now they all have fewer than four neighbors. And this is one of the
interesting properties or one of the good properties of this graph coloring
heuristic is that even if a note has many more than k-neighbors eventually, we may
remove enough nodes from the graph that, that it's number of neighbors will drop
below the number of colors available and then we'll be able to, to color it. So
anyway now it doesn't matter which node we pick because we can process them in any
order at this point. We'll remove c from the graph and we wind up with this graph.
And now, picking another node, we can remove b. Now we're down to just a two
node graph. Let's pick e and remove it from the graph. Now we're down to just a
one node graph, and we move f from the graph, and now the graph is empty and we
have our stack. And notice that the stack, all we've really done in this procedure, I
mean the goal of the first phase of this procedure has been to put an order on the
nodes of the graph. This is the order in which we should assign colors to the nodes
of the graph, alright. So now, working backwards, afterward, you know done with
the first part now we got to do the second part which we'll assign the colors. And,
we're going to begin with the top of the stack. So we'll take note f and put it
back into the graph. And we'll assign it a color and let's just say we're going to
pick the lowest numbered register that is not used by any of its neighbors. And so,
since f is in th e graph by itself, we'll just assign it register one. Now we add e
back into the graph and it has to have a different register from f. And so, since F
is using register r1, we'll just assign e register r2. Now we add b back into the
graph. It has to have a different color or register than both f and d so we'll sign
it register r3. We assign c back into the graph. Now, notice that c has both, has
all of f, e, and b as neighbors. They're using the first three registers so c will
get assigned register r4. And now, we're out of registers. I mean these, these four
nodes are using all of the registers but because we deleted things in the right
order in the first phase, we know that when we add in other nodes the rest of the
nodes on the stack, they won't have all of those nodes as neighbors. So there will be
some register available to sign. So, looking at register d, I'm sorry. Looking
at node D here, it has, it shares it has as its neighbors f, e, and c. And so the
only register that it could be assigned is r3 which is the same register as b. This
is the only register that isn't used by one of its neighbors, okay. So d gets
assigned register r3. And then we assign a sorry, we add a back into the graph and we
look at its neighbors and they're using registers r1 and r4. So a can be assigned
either register r2 or r3. And since our rule is just to use the lowest number
register that isn't used by one of the neighbors, we'll assign it register r2.
And there's our complete coloring of the graph.