To summarize this video, register allocation is one of the most important jobs that a compiler
performs. And it's really, these days they must have an any kind of reasonable
production compiler. And, the reason you need it is because the inter-media
code just generally uses too many temporaries. We're allowed to be a little
bit sloppy with intermediate code precisely because we have good register allocation
algorithms. And the other reason, registers are just a very important
resource in making good user registers. Having some procedure for making
efficient use of the registers. Leads to much, much better code in the end,
much more efficient code. Now. The register allocation algorithm I described
here is really targeted at risk machine. So, for risk machine reduce instruction set
computer what kind of machine. You can pretty much take the register allocation algorithm
that I described and if any for those machines it would work out of the box.
CISC machines - which stands for complex instructions for computers - often
have restrictions on how the register can be used. Certain operation can only work with
certain registers. You may have register to different sizes that can only
hold certain values. And so it becomes more complicated to register allocation for
such machines. What people have done is to adapt the graph coloring procedure that
I described here. So, the basic idea is exactly the same and you would recognize
those algorithms is being primarily the graph color algorithms that
we discussed. There are just additional. Steps in those algorithms and places where
the particular constraints are what registers can be used have to be observed.