The graph  coloring here is like that we discussed in the previous video doesn't
always succeed in coloring an arbitrary graph. And it may well get stuck and not
be able to find a coloring. And so in that case the only conclusion we can reach is
that we can't hold all the values that we'd like to register. We have more
temporary values and we have registers to hold them. And those temporary values have
to live somewhere so where should they live? Well, they're going to have to live
in memory. That's the only other kind of stories that we have. And so we're going
to pick some values and spill them into memory. The ideas that we have, the
picture in your mind should be. A bucket and it can hold a fixed amount of stuff.
Those are the registers and when it gets too full, some of the stuff spills over
and, and ends up some place else. Now, when does the graph coloring here do get
stuck? Well, this only situation which we won't be able to make progress as if all
the notes have k or more neighbors. So, let's take a look at our
favorite register interference graph when we will be using at our examples and now,
let's say that our, the machine we want to use only has three registers and so we,
instead of finding a 4-coloring of this graph, we need to find a 3-coloring. So
let's think about how to find the three coloring of this graph. If we apply the
heuristic, we'll remove A from the graph but then we're going to get stuck. Because
once you take A out of the graph and it's edge is out and every node that's
left has more than has three or more neighbors as at least three neighbors. So,
there's no node that we can delete from the graph and be guaranteed to be able to
find the coloring for it with the heuristic that we discussed in the previous video.
So, in this situation, what we're going to do is we're going to pick and know that
there is a candidate for spilling. This is a know that we or a temporary that we are
probably or we think we may have to assign into a memory location rather than to our
register and let is assume for the sake of this example that we pick f and we talk
later about how to choose a, the know to spill, there's a number of different ways
to, to chose the particular know to spill but for the illustration of this example,
it doesn't matter how pick, we just have to pick one to remove from the. Graph. As
were going to say, we're going to remove, that we going to spill F. So what we'll do
then is we'll remove f from the graph just like before and then we'll continue with
our simplification and this will now succeed because once we move F from the
graph we can see that all the nodes well, actually several of the nodes have fewer
than three neighbors and so B, C, and D. Sorry, B and D both only have two
neighbors when [inaudible] E and C will only have one neighbor each and so clearly
coloring will now succeed and here's one order that we'll succeed with this reduced
graph. After we decide to spill f and we successfully color the sub-graph, now we
have to try to assign a color to f and it could be, we could get lucky and discover
that even though f had more than there neighbors or three or more neighbors when
we remove it from the graph, it could be that when we go to construct the coloring
for the sub-graph that. Those neighbors actually don't use all of the register. It
could wind up being at all those neighbors, for example or assign to the
same register and so there are plenty of registers left over to assign to f. And
so, this is called optimistic coloring. So we pick a candidate for spilling. We tried
to color the sub-graph. Once we have a coloring for the sub-graph, now we see if
we just get lucky. And are able to assign a register to F. In which case we can just
go ahead and continue the color of the rest of the graph as if nothing had
happened. So in this case let's take a look what happens. We're going add F back
into the graph. And. And look at all, and look at it's neighbors and we see that we
have a neighbor that's using r1. We have a neighbor that's using r2 and we have a
neighbor that's using r2 and we have a neighbor that's using r3. And so on in
this case, optimistic coloring will not work so in fact F had more than K
neighbors and after we color the sub-graph, it turns out that those
neighbors are using all K. In this case three, all three of the register names.
And so F where there is no register left over for F and we're going to have to
actually spill it and store in memory. So, if optimistic coloring fails as it does in
this example, then we spill f. So, what we're going to do is allocate the memory
location for f and typically, what that means is that we'll allocate a position in
the current stack frame. Let's call this address fa for the address of f. And then
we're going to modify the control flow graph. We're going to change the code for
that compiling. So, before each operation that reads f, we're going to insert a load
that loads from that address to current value of f into a temporary name. Okay,
that makes sense because if the value is out of memory, then if we have an
operation that needs to actually use the value. We're going to have to load it from
a memory first then to the register. And similarly after each operation that writes
F, we're going to insert the store so we're going to save the current value of F
into it's location in memory. So, here is the original code from which we
constructed the registry interference graph and notice that there are few
references to f in here and we just highlight them, alright. So, we have a
couple of reads, we have a right and so now, what are we going to do? So, here
we had the use of F, the read of F in this statement and now we preceded that by
a load. And notice that I've given a new name here. I've called this F1. And, that's
because the different uses of F in the control flow graph don't all have to have
the same temporary name. And actually it would be a good idea to separate them so
each distinct to use of F will get it's own name. So here we load the value of F
and then it get to use in the statement. Here we have a right to f and so we store
the current value of f and those argument to a different name, f2. So, that's
temporary is computed here as going to be stored and it's called f2. And finally,
the third use of f there's another load of f right here. Which is then used in this
computation here of b. Okay. So, that is the systematic way to modify the code to
use f in storage. And now, we have to recompute the aliveness of f. And so, what
happens there. Well, here is the original aliveness information from which we
computed the register interference graph, okay. And now notice that f is gone. We no
longer use f in the programs so we can delete all the places where we mentioned
that f was live and now we have the three new names, f1, f2, and f3. And we have to
add in their aliveness information so it creates a new program points here where we
inserted statements. And of course, where we have a load of the current value of f
that value if live right before the use in the next statement. Here, we have the
right of the current value of f and that's live right before the store and then
here's another load of the current value of f which is live until the store, I'm
sorry, until the use in the next statement. Okay. And so, now notice here
that f used to be live in many, many, many places in the, in the code. And now not
only is f or the, the different versions of f live in fewer places also we've
distinguish them. So, it actually separate the different uses of f and so this will
have their own nodes in their own set of interferences in the graph and they won't
share them with the other users of f and that will actually also reduce the number
of edges in the graph. To summarize the example on the previous slide, once we
have decided that we are actually going to spill a temporary f, that means we're
going to change the program where have loads and stores to the program and now
we're going to have a different program and that's going to change our register
allocation problems. We're going to have to recompute the aliveness of information,
we're have to rebuild the restrain interference graph and then we're going to
have to try again to color that block graph. Now, it turns out that this new
aliveness information is almost the same as it was before. So, all the temporary
names other than f are not much affected by the by the new statements that are
added. There are a few program points where they might be live but I replaced
they were alive before and they're still alive. And, F itself has changed fairly
dramatically. It's like this information has changed really dramatically. Certainly
the old name F is no longer used and so it's like this information goes away and
then we've also split F into three in this case three different temporaries. One for
each of the different uses of F in the control flow graph. And I noticed that
each of these new uses of F or these new versions of F is live in a very, very
small area so a load. In this video, we are going to continue our discussion of
as filling. For a load instruction The thing that were loading the temporary that
we're loading fi is live only between the load and the next instruction where it's
used and similarly for a store. It's score of a temporary fi is live only between the
store itself and the proceeding instruction. The one they created fi. And
the effective is, is to greatly reduce the live range of the spilled variable. So,
whatever name we decide to spill by adding the load and stores right next to the
places where those values are used We dramatically reduced the live range and in
addition, as I mentioned in the previous live by splitting the name f into multiple
different name, we also you know, avoid sharing. Those different liv e ranges
between the different versions of F. So because the live range of F is reduced by
spilling. It has fewer interferences in the new program than it did in the old
program. And so what that means the particulars in the rebuild [inaudible]
interference graph, F will have fewer neighbors. Some of the neighbors that it
had before have gone away because it just live in fewer places. So if we look at the
new register interference graph, we can see that among all the different versions
of F. Remember that F has been split into three temporaries in this graph. We see
that they only interfere with D and C. Whereas, before f have several other
neighbors in the graph. And now, in fact this new graph is three tolerable. Of
course it might be the case that we can't just spill one name. We might have to have
just spill several different temporaries before the coloring is found. And, the
tricky part is to siding what to spill. So, this is the hard decision that has to
be made during restore allocation. Now any choice is correct. It's only a question of
performance so you know some choices of spilling will lead to better code than
others but any choice of spilling is going to resolve in a correct program. And
there's heuristics that people use to pick which temporaries to spill and here are a
few or I think three of the most popular ones. One is to spill the temporaries and
have the most conflicts. And the reason for that is that this is the temporary.
The one thing that you can move into memory that will most affect the number of
interferences in the graph. So, the idea is by possible spilling justice on
variable. We'll remove enough edges from the graph that they becomes tolerable with
the number of registers we have. Another possibility is a spilled temporaries that
have few definitions and uses. And, here the idea is that by spilling those since
they're not used very much, the number of lows in storage will have to add, will be
relatively small and so if a variable just isn't used in many places, then the actual
cost, in terms of additional instructions that are going to be executed to spill it,
is relatively small. And another one and this is actually the one that I think that
all the compilers implement is to avoid spilling an inner loops. So, if you have a
choice between spilling a variable that's used within the. Innermost loop for the
program and one that is used some place else. You probably preferred this that you
spill the one that is used not in the innermost loop absolutely because again,
that will result in fewer loads in stores. You really want to avoid adding additional
instructions to your inner loop.