So, just as was the case with mark-and-sweep, when we scan an object, we
have to know how big it is and we also need to know where the pointers and the
object are. So, if we think about this for a minute, let's say we're scanning this
object, so this is our scan pointer and we want now to process all the pointers in
it, well, we have to know where the pointers are. So, there's a pointer here
and there's a pointer here and we'll be able to find those pointers and we don't
want to confuse them with other fields of the object that might look like pointers.
So, in a bit pattern for an integer could look an awful lot like a pointer. Now,
this is not a big problem because the compiler, of course, in terms of, a lot of
the objects in the heap and it can stor e that information somewhere communicated to
the garbage collector so that it will be able to find the pointers. So, you can
imagine easily a little bit of information stored with the program indicating for
each type where the pointers are. And similarly once we've scanned this object,
we need to be able to advance our scan pointer just past the object so that we
can find the beginning of the next object and that's why we need to know the size,
okay. So, we need to know that size so that the scan pointer can be moved past
the object and we can find the beginning of the next object. Another issue is that
whenever we do a garbage collection, I haven't mentioned this up to this point
but it should be clear, we also have to scan and copy objects pointed to by the
stack. And we also have to update pointers in the stack. And this can actually turn
out to be kind of an expensive operation with stop-and-copy because, you know, you
still have to walk the entire stack each time you do a collection in order to make
sure that you've copied all the objects pointed to by the stack. To conclude
stop-and-copy, I think it's fair to say, is generally believed to be the fastest
garbage collection technique. Certainly, I believe that variations on stop-and- copy
are the most efficient approaches known to automatic memory management. Allocation is
very cheap, alright. So, cuz all you have to do is increment the e-pointer. So,
you're just moving a, a, single pointer forward to allocate space. There's no
complicated free list future verse or decisions to make about where to put the
object, you know, you're just going to allocate it directly at the allocation
pointer. So, you know, this, this part of memory management is, is very inexpensive.
And at the same time, collection is also relatively cheap. And, and interestingly
it's especially cheap if there is a lot of garbage because, because of making a copy
of the reachable objects stop-and-copy only touches the reac hable object, It is
not, in particular, does not touch the garbage. So, if you think about that for a
minute, that means that the garbage collection is in stop-and-copy is order
the size of the live objects. So, whatever the sub-graph is that you're copying,
that's the cost of a garbage collection and that's in contrast to mark-and-sweep
were the cost is proportional to all the memory that you're using cuz you have the
sweep phase where you have to go through and touch every single object whether it's
live or garbage, okay. And so, if you have a relatively lot of garbage and a
relatively small set of live objects, stop-and-copy is actually much, much
faster than mark-and-sweep. Now, of course the down side of stop-and-copy is that it
moves the objects in some languages, in particular C and C++, can't allow you to
move objects because the address that which an object lives is actually visible
exposed in the program and is part of the semantics of the object. And so there, you
really have to use mark-and-sweep because you're not allowed to move anything.