Now, this algorithm is very simple. And conceptually,
I think it's, it's very clear how it works. But there are a number
of tricky details and this is very typical of automatic memory management algorithms.
And there's actually a serious problem with the mark phase. And, and this is also
typical of, of garbage collection algorithms. Now, notice that we only run this
algorithm when we are out of space, okay. So, the whole point is that we're garbage
collecting because there's no more system memory available for allocating new
objects. And yet we have this to-do list, okay. And notice that the work list was not
bounded in size. There was no guarantee about how many elements were going
to be on the to-do list. And I think, it's easy to see that, that data structure
could actually be fairly large, alright. And so, we can't just allocate a
fixed amount of space for the to-do list or reserve some constant amount of space.
But we need to deal with the fact that we actually don't have any space at all when
we get around to doing a garbage collect ion. Now, there is a trick that can be used
to maintain the to-do list during the mark phase without having to use any extra
storage. And that is to do what is called pointer reversal. So, when a pointer is followed,
it's going to be reversed to point back to its parent. And this is going
to allows us actually to track what elements or what objects in the heap still
need to be processed without having to use any extra space. And let's just if you don't
understand that I'm going to do an example in just a second. I wanna mention
a second problem as well and that is, you know, where is the free list stored? And this
is a little easier to see how that works. So, the free list consists of blocks
of memory. And, and we just use the space in these blocks to maintain the free
list so perhaps the first word or something of the block of memory will contain
the size of the block and then the second word will point to the next block in
the list, you know, something like that but we can use the space in the blocks themselves
to maintain the free list. And so, now let's come back to this pointer reversal
idea. Let's say that we have some objects, okay, and we want to track reachability,
okay, and we can't maintain the to-do list, all right in a separate data
structure. And so how are we going to do that? Well, well, here's the idea when
we change colors. So, we're doing to come in here and we're going to mark this first
object. Let's say this is reachable from the root and now that this is the root the
first object. And now we're going to follow the pointers in this object and let's
say this is one here, this one here is the first pointer in the object. So, we're
going to follow it and then we're going to reverse it. We're going to have it
point back to the parent. So, now we will mark this object and then we'll follow
the pointers in, in this object, okay. And as we go down, we'll have this pointer
point back and then we'll mark this object. And now, we got no point ers
in this object and so we need to go back and process any pointers that weren't covered
in the object set that we that we have already seen, okay. And how do we find
our way back? Well, that's what the pointer reversal was for. So, we could follow
the blue arrow back here, as we come back, we'll restore the original pointer.
So, we'll get rid of the reversed pointer. There are no more pointers in this
object either so we'll go back one more object and now, of course, this pointer
will go away and we'll restore the original pointer, alright. And now, we're
in this object and we see there was a second pointer that we haven't followed yet,
okay. And, and then we'll follow it and we'll reverse it and we'll follow the
other pointer from that, reversing it, and, and then we'll mark these two objects,
when we get down to this object and we discover there are no additional pointers,
we'll be able to use this, these blue arrows here to work our way back and
we'll restore the red arrows as we walk back up through the objects. So, essentially
the point of reversal does is it helps us maintain the stack for a depth
for search of the graph. So, if you're doing adept for search of the graph and you
want to be sure that you cover all the notes that are reachable then you have to
be able to do the back tracking. And the, the reversed pointers allow us to do that
[cough]. There's one more tiny issue here with the reversed pointers. So, notice that
there's a little bit of a problem. So, I want to talk about reversing pointers
and let me draw two new objects here just to illustrate the point. Let's say,
I have a, a pointer from this object to that object. So, when I cross over, to
the object that is pointed to, what does it mean to reverse this pointer? Well the,
you know, the space where the pointer is actually in this object, there's no space
necessarily for the pointer at all in, in the object that I'm going to. And so, in fact,
what's going to happen let's say this was part of a chain of objects, okay.
And, and this problem is easily solved, the issue is just off by one problem. So,
I have, I have space in this object for a pointer and I can change that pointer. I don't
know if I even have any pointers in this object yet, alright. So, let's say this
is part of a chain of objects, okay, and that I've walked down this chain to, to
this particular object. So, as I pass over to this third object with I, the pointer
that I will reverse is this one and I will make it point back to the previous
object, okay. And then I'm just going to remember this particular object,
you know, I'll keep the pointer to this particular object in a register. So, I'll
keep the last pointer at reversed in a register. An, and a pointer to the last object
that I came from in a register and then when I go on to another object, I will
use the pointer that I'm traversing in the current object to point back to the
parent of the previous object, okay. So, it's just a off by one problem, I need one
register here to hold on to the previous object that I visited and then I can reverse
pointers back up to their parents and grandparents. Alright, to summarize the
discussion of mark-and-sweep. Space for a new object is going to be allocated
from the free list, little typo there. And we're always going to pick a block, we always
have to pick a block from the free list that is large enough to hold the object
that we're allocating. And in an area of the size that we need is going to
be allocated from that block and then the leftovers is to be put back on the free list.
So, let's say the free list has a block, let's say it has 100 bytes and then
we need an object that has 50 bytes in it. So, what will happen is that this block will
get split up. We'll use this first half, the first 50 for the object and then
this other part the leftover will get put back on to the free list. And the result of
that kind of strategy where we, we have to find blocks that are big enough but then
we might not use the entire block is that mark-and-sweep can fragment the memory.
We might wind up with lots of little bits of leftover memory maybe nothing
big enough to actually hold an object. And these blocks, these little tiny
blocks might be scattered all over the place. So, it's important actually, for
mark-and-sweep to also merge blocks whenever possible. So, it's merge free blocks,
when possible. So, basically when the sweep phase is working on the free list.
It needs to recognize when it has two adjacent blocks of memory that will be
immediately adjacent to each other in memory. So, if I have two blocks that are
contiguous, what I really want to do is to merge them into one big block and just have
one entry in the free list. That's a counteract fragmentation of memory. Now, one
big advantage and perhaps the biggest advantage of mark-and-sweep is that objects
are not moved during garbage collection. And that means I don't have to
update the pointer objects. Object stay put, they don't move as part of garbage collection.
And what this means is it's actually possible to adapt mark and sweet,
for languages like CNC++. So, in CNC++, pointers are exposed to the programmer so
programmers can, can manipulate pointers and test pointers and so you can't move objects
in CNC++ because the pointer is part of their semantics. The pointer address,
I should say, is part of their semantics. But it is actually possible and
people actually have done it to build conservative or, you know, variations of a
mark-and-sweep garbage collection for C++ precisely because the objects don't move.