In this video, we're going to talk about the first of three garbage collection
techniques that we're going to look at in detail. First one is mark-and-sweep.
Mark-and-sweep works in two phases. And it's called, not surprisingly, mark and
sweep. So, the mark phase is going to trace all the reachable objects. So, when
memory runs out and we stop to do the garbage collection, the first thing we're
going to do is go and trace out all the reachable objects. And then the Sweep
phase is going to collect all the garbage objects. And to support this, every object
is going to have an extra bit somewhere in it called the mark bit. And, this is
reserved from memory management and it's not going to be used by anything except
the garbage collector. And initially, before we start a garbage collection, the
mark bit of every object will always be zero. And that's going to be set to one,
for the reachable objects in the mark phase. So, when we mark an object, we mark
it with a And that indicates that the object is reachable. So, here is the mark
phase. It's going to be a work list based algorithm and so initially our work list
consists of all the roots so all the initial pointers held in registers and
then while the work list, the to-do list is not empty, we're going to do the
following. We pick some element v out of the to-do list we'll remove it from the
to-do list, okay. And then, this is the crux of the algorithm. If the object v is
not already marked then we mark it, okay. So, we say, mark bit to one and then we
find all the pointers inside of it, alright. And we add those to our work
list. So, everything, every point gets added to work list. Now, if v is already
marked, well then we have already processed it and we've already add all the
things it points to, to the work list. And so we just need to do nothing there is no
else branch and we just drop it from the to-do list. So, once we've completed the
mark phase and every reachable object has been marked, then the sweep phase is going
to scan th rough the heap looking for objects that have mark bit zero. And the
sweep phase is just going to march through all of memory. It's going to start at the
bottom of the heap and walk over every object in the heap and check its mark bit.
And so, any of the objects that it finds that have mark bit zero, they were not
visited in mark phase and they're clearly not reachable. S, all those objects will
be added to a free list. And as we go through the memory is one other detail
that's important. Any object that has its mark bit set is gonna have its mark bit
reset to zero. So, that way it's ready for the next garbage collection. So, here is
the pseudo-code for the sweep phase and this will function, size of p is going to
size of block, the size of the object that starts at pointer p, alright. And as
you'll see this is actually, the reason that we have the size of objects encoded
in the object in COOL. So, remember in the header for COOL objects there is a size
field that is, so that the garbage collector as it's walking through memory
can figure out how big the objects are. Anyway, we start at the bottom of the
heap. And while we haven't reached the top of the heap, we do the following. We look
at where we're pointing and then we'll always be pointing to the beginning of an
object. So, we check to see if the mark bit of that object is one. And if it is,
well then it was a reachable object. So, we just reset its mark bit to zero.
Otherwise, if its mark bit was zero, then we're going to add that block of memory,
okay, which is the size of the object to the free list. And finally, in either
case, okay, we're going to increment p by the size of the object that it points to
so we point to the next object. Then we'll just repeat that loop over and over again
resetting the mark bits of things that were reached and adding things that were
not reached for the free list until we've touched every object in the heap. Here's a
little example. So, we're starting out here with a, a heap and we're gonna assume
there's just one root for simplicity. And here are all the objects and initially
their marked bits are zero and we do have a free list, an initial free list over
here. Notice that, you know, there's a little bit of memory that is on the free
list. Okay. So, after the mark phase, what has happened? Well, we've gone through,
and touched all the reachable objects. So, we started with A and, of course, we set
its mark bit to one. And then we followed pointers reachable from A, set the mark
bit there. Follow the pointer reachable from C, set the mark bit there. And so we
wind up A, C, and E being marked, nothing else is marked, okay. And now the sweep
phase will go through memory, it's going to reset all the marked bits to zero. And
as it finds unreachable objects, in this case B and D, it's going to add them to
the free list and so what we'll wind up the free list will wind up being a linked
list of, of, of blocks of memory that are available for future allocations.