We're now ready to wrap up our discussion of automatic memory management.
And so I just want to make a few, high level points here. First of all,
there's no question that automatic memory management is a great thing. It prevents very
serious storage bugs, some of the most difficult bugs in programming, and when
you're writing in the garbage collected language you really have just a
whole class of things you don't have to worry about and so it is certainly a more
productive way to program. So if, if your problem, your program is really a good fit
for automatic memory management then you'd be crazy not to use a system that provided
that kind of support. Now, the disadvantage of automatic memory management
is that it reduces programmer control. So you don't have control anymore
over the layout of data and memory, and you don't have control over when the memory
is reallocated. So, you neither have control over where the data is in memory
and you have only a very limited amount of control over how much memory your
program is using, okay? And so if these two things don't matter, if your, if
your application is not extremely data intensive where the precisely out of data
memory and how much data is residing in memory is important then garbage collection
will likely work very well. But there are applications particularly high end
data processing and scientific applications which use a lot of data and need
to make very, very efficient use of the memory where garbage collection actually
becomes too inefficient to do a good job and people in those domains still
use manual memory management. But there are some other issues. So, in real time applications
the pauses can be problematic. So, if you have a program that
needs to meet guaranteed deadlines, many embedded systems that are interacting
with the outside world say controlling dangerous machinery and things like that they
have to have response times that are guaranteed to make sure that nothing terrible
happens. And, and you know, introducing a automatic memory management
system that might pause for arbitrary amounts of time you know, makes that a very
problematic things guaranty. So, you don't always see garbage selection used in
real time applications. Although there has been a lot a progress in the last several
years on real time garbage collectors. Another issue for every programmer who uses
automatic memory management probably will have to face is the problem of memory
leaks. So, while automatic memory management prevents you from corrupting your
memory, it really doesn't prevent you from hanging on to too much data and possibly
affecting the performance of your program dramatically. So, memory leaks are
possible in garbage collected languages and I would say they are even likely. Said,
you know, the fact that you're not as aware or not as forced to be aware of how
the memory is being used makes it easier to have memory leaks. And the kind
of memory leak that you will have in say, a Java program is that you'll have some you
know, some variable say x that points to some data structure and this data structure
is gigantic, okay? So lets say that this is the abstract syntax tree, in
a compiler, alright? Now there may come a point in the computation where you don't need
the abstract syntax tree anymore. So let's say that we have converted to an intermediate
language and from the abstract syntax tree and now all our processing
for the rest of the compilation is going t be on the intermediate language
representation and generating code from that, we never go back and look at the abstract
syntax tree again. Well, the compiler I mean, excuse me, the, the garbage
collector doesn't know that you are not going to use the abstract syntax tree
again in the future. And if you have a variable that's pointing to this gigantic
data structure even if you are not using it, it's gong to hang around and
is going to be using up memory. And so the right thing to do is when you reach a point
in program where you are not going to use this data structure anymore is to assign
x the null value. You want to assign x to null at that point and essentially
dropping this pointer to the data structure. And now the garbage collector,
whatever form it is, mark and sweeps, Stop and copy or reference counting
will be able to see that this is no longer reachable and will collect that
big structure. And this is very, very common in, in production Java programs to
have these kinds of memory leaks where you just have pointers that you forgot about to
data that you're no longer going to use. So as a whole, I have conveyed in the
last few lectures, garbage collection is a very important technique. Every programmer
should be aware of its benefits and costs and it's also very interesting aspect of programming
language implementation. There are much more advanced garbage collecting
algorithms than we have discussed in these lectures and the primary dimensions along
which people have thought about improving garbage collection, that is making garbage
collection concurrent. That means allowing the program to continue to run while other
collection is happening. So the collector is working in the background actively while
the program is running. Another thing that's very common actually in, in production
collectors is to what's called a generational collector. And the basic idea
here is that we don't want to keep going over lo oking at objects that are very
long lived on every collection. So, collections happen very frequently and there
will be some objects that just live for very long time, the big data structures
that hang around for most of the program. And once we have seen them, in
a couple of collections we probably can assume that they're going to be around for
a few more collections. And so in a generational collection sorry in a generational
collector older objects, objects that have been around for a while
are put in a seperate area and they're collected less frequently. And this just allows
the collector to focus on the objects that are most likely to be garbage
which are the recently allocated objects. We already talked a little bit about Realtime.
So there are collectors that try to bound the length or the, bound the length
of the maximum pause, the maximum interruption to the program. And finally parallel
collectors. So collector systems where the garbage, there's actually several
garbage collectors running at the same time and somehow coordinating their actions.