In this video, we're going to talk about programmer defined exceptions. So, think
about the following typical programming scenario. You're deep into some fairly
complex section of code and you come to a place where you could experience an
unexpected error. That there could be something that could happen that would
violate some important property of your program. So, for example, maybe you're
going to discover there's a place where you could be out of memory or there's some
data structure that doesn't satisfy some variant. So, a list that's supposed to be
sorted, that is not, or something like that. And the question is, how do you
handle these errors? How do you write code that will handle the error gracefully and
not make your program really, really ugly? So, a popular solution to this problem in
many languages including Java is add a new kind of value to the language called an
exception. And we'll have a couple of control constructs for dealing with
exceptions. Here is the two that are probably the most popular. And these are,
as they appear in Java. So, we can throw exceptions and what this does is it causes
an exception to be created at this point wherever the throw occurs. And, that
exception will simply propagate out of the program. It will basically halt the
execution of the program at that point and any containing constructs will also throw
the exception. So, the exception will, you know, simply propagate up out of the code
that, that's currently executing, until it hits a try catch. So, how does this work?
Well, we can try something. We can execute some expression here and this will be some
expression. And if this expression throws an exception, if the throw occurs
somewhere inside this expression, then we will catch that exception and there can be
a binding here to say what we are going to call the exception value. So, this is like
a let, we will grab the exception that comes out of here. We'll call it X and
then we can execute this piece of cleanup code to how, to handle the exception in
some way. And so, the basic idea behind this thi design for handling exceptions,
is that the place where you have the exception, the place where you actually
detect the exception, might be somewhere deep inside the code and not a very good
place for actually dealing with the exception. So, what you want to do is get
out of that part of the code, get back to some higher level point where you can
clean things up deal with the exception, and then retry, perhaps, some larger block
of code. Here's a little example of using exceptions. So, here we have our main
method. And what are we going to do? We're going to have a try-block that just calls
a function X. And if that raises a, an exception, then we will catch the
exception. In this case we don't do anything with the exception, we just print
out a message saying there was an error and we terminate the program. So, we don't
do anything very smart but we do catch the exception and at least print out an error
rather than just terminating. So, what does x do? Well, X simply throws an
exception. So this function X allocates an exception object. This is just a value,
it's just a class like everything else. But it has a special property that it can
be thrown. So, when we throw it, that's when X terminates abnormally and we end up
in the catch block of the try-catch expression back in the main method. Now,
in the last couple of slides, I gave you a very informal description of how
exceptions work and it, it might not have been very clear and in fact it's hard I
think to give a very clear description without some kind of formal description of
how exceptions are supposed to behave. But fortunately, we've looked at operational
semantics in this class and so now you're familiar with those kinds of descriptions
of language behavior and I can actually describe you pretty succinctly how
try-catch actually really works, alright. So, we're going to give operational rules
here for Try-Catch expressions. And I just noticed, I just poin t out here that I had
some kind of font problem and so I had to write in the turnstiles by hand in this
slide. So those handwritten characters are all supposed to be the turnstile
character. Now, to more important things there's a distinction with exceptions.
Okay, there are two kinds of states that an exception object could be in. It could
just be an ordinary value. So, when I say new exception object in Java, so, when I
say something new, something exception class is just an ordinary value. At that
point, it just behaves like any other object. But then, there is a distinction
when the object is thrown. So, when the exception is actually thrown, it becomes a
special kind of value and it gets treated differently, alright. So, we're going to
distinguish between an ordinary object V, okay. And objects that have been thrown,
okay, which are then active exceptions. Alright? So, let's take a look at some of
the operational rules for the exception constructs. So, here's one rule for its
try-catch-block. And what this rule says is that if an expression evaluates to an
ordinary value. If it doesn't throw an exception, then the results of the
try-catch-block is just that value. So, the way the try-catch-block works is you
evaluate the expression in the try-block. If that terminates normally with a value,
then the results of the whole expression is just that value, alright? Now, the
other possibility is that you'll evaluate a try catch block and when you go to
evaluate the expression of the try-block E1, it will throw an exception. So, it
could result in a thrown exception. And so, in this case. Okay, that is that,
excuse me, that is this case where E1 evaluates to one of these special values
has been marked as a thrown exception. What do we do in that case? Well, like
unwrap the exception, we pull out value that is in the thrown exception, alright.
We bind it to some local name, alright, that's named in the catch expression and
then we evaluate the cleanup code. So, with the ex ception value available, we
evaluate E2 and whatever the result is of E2, that is the result of the
try-catch-block. How does throw work? It's very simple. So, throw just takes an
expression, it evaluates that expression against some value V. And then, it marks
that value as a thrown exception, as a thrown exception so it wraps the value in
this T thing and that indicate that this exception now has been thrown. Now, the
only other thing we need to talk about is how the rest of the language, all the
other constructs in the language deal with these thrown exceptions. And that's very
simple. We want those thrown exceptions to simply propagate out of any other kind of
expression. So, for example, we'll just do one example here because the idea is the
same for every other language construct. Let's say, that we're evaluating E1 + E2,
alright. So, the first thing we have to do of course is to evaluate E1 and if that
happens the thrown exception. So, if something goes wrong in the evaluation of
E1 and E1 evaluates to the thrown in exception, well then we stop the
evaluation of the plus right there. We don't even evaluate E2, notice that E2 is
not mentioned here above the line of one of the things to be evaluated so that E1
terminates normally with an exception, then the results of the entire addition is
that exception. And similarly, for all the other constructs if, if there's, one of
their sub-expressions results in an exception. In fact, if the, if, as soon as
one of their sub-expressions results in an exception, they stop evaluating and
propagate that exception up. The only thing that will stop the exception from
propagating all the way out to become the result of the whole program is if it is
caught in a try-catch-block. There are many ways to implement exceptions and here
is one simple way to do it. So, we encounter a try expression, we will mark
the current location in the stack. So, we will mark the position in the stack where
we encountered the try. So, for example, here, say, is our s tack. Let's say that,
you know, the stack is going this way. We encounter a try expression here so we put
some kind of marker in the stack to indicate that there's a try that was
encountered there. And then you go on, you know, evaluating things inside of the try
which might add more stuff to the stack. Now, when we throw an exception, if down
here, all of a sudden a throw occurs and we're at this point in the execution,
what's going to happen is we're going to unwind the stacks. We're going to knock
everything off the stack. We're going to pop all of this stuff of the stack, so
it's all gone, back to the first try. And then we'll execute the corresponding
catch. So, here we marked, you know, the place and the code where there was a try
and we can use that to find the expression the piece of the code that has the
corresponding catch-block and we'll unwind the stack to that point and then begin
evaluation of the catch. So at this particular design it has the disadvantage
that try actually cost something. So, even if you don't throw an, even if you don't
throw an exception, you still pay something to execute a try-catch-block.
You have to at least mark the stack and, and remember to unmark it of course, when
you pop things off the stack when you leave the try-block. So, more complex
techniques tries to reduce the cost of try and throw and also trade off between them.
And generally the thing you want to do is because exceptions are probably relatively
rare in, in most programs is to make the cost of try as low as possible, possibly
at the expense of making throws slightly more expensive. Now, here's a little
trivia question about Java. So, what happens to an uncaught exception as thrown
during object finalization? So, if you don't know what object finalization is,
well, when an object is collected, when an object is garbage collected, it is
possible to run a method on that object to clean it up before the garbage collector
actually deallocates it and this is called the finali zation method. So, objects have
finalization methods in, in Java and those methods are essentially invoked by the
garbage collector. Some garbage collector discovers that some objects, this garbage
is going to be clean it up, it will first invoke the finalization method. And why
would you wanted to do this unless, say, we have an object and it might have, say,
a file handle. It might have a pointer to an open file or something like that. And
now, when this object becomes unreachable, it will be collected by the garbage
collector. But if you don't close the file, well, that's gonna cause problems.
Having lots of open files that are hanging around without the program using them it
can cause problems later on, especially if you run out of file handles. Usually,
there's a fixed number of file handles available from the operating system. So,
the right thing to do is when this is garbage collected is to first close the
file and essentially get rid of this pointer, okay, and then, deallocate the
object, and that it was object finalization is for. So, again, you can
define the method in Java that will be run by the garbage collector to kinda clean up
any resources the object has before it's actually deallocated. And now the question
is, if that finalization method raises an exception, who catches it? Because it was
invoked by the garbage collector, it's unpredictable when it's going to be
invoked and it's not clear where that exception should be handled. And the
answer to the question is no one handles that method or nothing handles that
method. The exception is simply dropped. And so, any exceptions that happen during
object finalization that are not handled within the finalization method itself are
simply thrown away. One of the nice innovations in Java is that exceptions are
actually part of the method interface and they are checked by the compiler. So, in,
in the example that I gave at the beginning of this lecture, we had a method
X that could raise an exception, my exception, and notice that the declaration
of X actually declares that X can throw that exception. So, it's part of the
interfaced X, part of the checked interfaced X that it can raise a
particular exception. And why would you want to check this at compile time? Well,
the observation that was made, actually in the original Java project was that there
were many exceptions that could be raised by Java programs and people easily lost
rack of what possible exceptions could be raised, they didn't know what exceptions
they had to handle. And in fact, when they added this to the language the compiler
would actually enforce now that a method declared every exception it could raise.
They discovered lots of places in the, in the compiler where there were exceptions
being raised but not properly handled. So, this led to better air handling in, in the
Java compiler itself, and, and I think people generally agree that this is een a
good idea because it helps programmers to write more robust code because they can
see exactly which exceptions they have to handle. Now, there are some exceptions to
this rule. In particular there's, there's some kinds of runtime errors that don't
have to be part of the method signature simply because it's very hard to check
statistically that the method would never raise them. So, things like dereferencing
null or interprocedural overflow don't have to be handled and declared in the
interface. But for the most part any exception that a, a method can raise has
to be declared as part of its interface in Java. And then there are other
mundane-type rules about the particular design for exceptions in Java. So, for
example, throw has to be applied to an object of type exception, it can't be
applied to an object of an arbitrary type. But overall exceptions are rather nicely
done in Java and that this particular idea of, of declaring the types of exceptions
that a method can raise was a new idea in Java.