In this video, we're going to take a look at Java Arrays. Let's say we have two
classes, a and b, and that b is a sub class of a. And let's think about what
happens when we execute the following piece of code. So, the first thing we're
going to do is we're going to allocate an array of b's. So, this is an array that's
supposed to hold B's, okay? And, we're going to have an array variable b here
that points to it. And then, we're going to have another variable, array variable
A, that also points to the same array as B. But notice the type of a. So a is an
array of A's, little a here is an array of A's, and b is typed as an array of B's.
And now what we're going to do is we're going to assign into a sub zero, okay,
into the first position of a, a new a object. And that should be fine, right?
Because a is an array of A's and that seems like that should work out alright.
Alright, so here there will be an a sitting in the first position. And then,
we're going to access b sub zero which, because A and B point to the same array,
is the same element as a sub zero. And we're going to call some method that is
not declared in A. Now remember, B is a sub-type of A, alright? So B has all the
methods of A. A but B might have more methods. And since this is an array of
B's, we should be able to call all the B methods on it and yet here, when we call
some methods that's declared in B but not in A, we are going to get a run-time error
because the object stored in the array is actually an A object at the first
position. To understand what's going on in this example, we have to take a look at
the sub typing rules in Java. So, if we use a subtype of A if B inherits from A,
that's one case. So if B and B inherits from A, then B is a subtype of A. And
that's just like in Cool and, and most other object oriented languages. And
we're, we're very familiar with that from our lectures in type checking. Further
more, type, sub typing is transitive. So if C is a subtype of B, and B is a subtype
of A then C is also a subtype of A. Okay, a nd that's also completely standard. But
then there's this other rule that's not quite standard or is definitely
nonstandard. And that's that, an array of B's is a sub-type of an array of A's if
the element types are in a sub-type relationship. So if B is a sub-type of A,
then array of B is a sub-type of array of A. And Cool doesn't have anything like
that, Cool doesn't have arrays so it wouldn't even have the opportunity to have
something like that. But this is also not the way it's done in other languages that
have objects and sub-typing. So let's take a look at our little example again and let
me explain it in a slightly different way. So, the issue here is that we have a, area
of memory, and it actually doesn't matter here. It's not essential that this be an
array. What's important is that's an updatable part of memory so that we have
pointers to it. We have two pointers to it, a and b and we can, they can both read
and write this part of memory. So this could be just a single cell, it doesn't
have to be an array of multiple cells. But what's important is that there is some
memory location that both of these point to, that they can both read and write,
okay? And the trouble comes and by the way, that there's a name that, that's
called Aliasing, okay? So when you have two names, two program names for the same
part of memory that is called aliasing, and here you know, we have the, the two
arrays, A and B, that point to the same area of memory, okay? Now, aliasing is
very common in real programs since not bad by itself but the problem in this example
is that A and B have different types, okay? And in general, if you have aliasing
updatable references, okay? Meaning if two names for the same location, that location
is both readable and writable, so it can be updated through the two names. And
those two names have different types then that is going to be unsound, okay? We're
not going to have a sound type system and to see the problem, let's say here in this
case what was it? We had that B, type B was sub type of A, okay? And what did that
mean? Well that meant is we could do a wright through this pointer, okay? And
write an A object into this location and then we could read that out through this
point over here as a B object. But now, it doesn't have all the methods and, and
fields of A and treating it as the object, we could potentially use an operation on
it that's undefined. And you can see that it doesn't help if we swap the roles of,
of A and B, alright? So in particular, if we reverse the, if we reverse the
sub-typing relationship so that A was a sub type of B, we can do exactly the same
problem because aliasing is symmetric. We just do the write through the B pointer
and the read out of the A pointer swapping the roles of the recent right here and we
have exactly the same problem. So in general, multiple aliases do updatable
locations with different types is unsound, okay? And this problem actually has come
up in many different programming languages. Java is not the only
programming language to have had this issue. It's a fairly subtle aspect of type
systems and in many languages have done things similar to Java where they've
created a problem really for the static type system by wanting to have a
sub-typing work through arrays. Now, the standard solution or the solution that's
used in, I should say, in many languages and is probably most widely accepted in
the programming languages research community is that you need a different
sub-typing rule for arrays. So we would say, you know, the rule that is commonly
used the standard solution to this problem at the type level is that to do the
following things. So you only allows sub-typing on arrays. So, you know, an
array of B's is a sub-type in array of A's only if B and A are the same type. If B =
A. And if you think about that for a second, if we have an array and now we
have our two pointers to it, A and B and we know the type of A the subtype or the
type of B. Well, that only h appens if the element types are, are equal. And so we
can't create two references to an updateable location with different types.
Okay, and that will guarantee soundness of, of the type, of the type system. So
Java fixes the problem differently. So instead of statically checking that array
accesses will all be type correct, Java does this at run time. And so whenever an
assignment is done into an array at runtime, Java checks whether the type of
the object being assigned in compatible with the type of the array. So when you
say new B sub ten in Java, Java will remember inside the array that this was
supposed to be an array of Bs. And then whatever you assign into the array, it
will check that the thing you're assigning is either a B or a sub type of B. Now,
this obviously adds an overhead on array computations so every assignment to an
array is going to have, have a type check on it at run time. And fortunately though,
the most kinds of arrays are arrays of primitive types, in particular arrays of
ints and arrays of floating point numbers and these are not affected because the
primitive types are not classes. There's no subtyping on them and so you can never
create an array, say, of floating point numbers, with any kind of subtyping
relationship that would result in this problem. So, so, that we're saved, or in
better shape, for the primitive types, and they don't need these extra checks. But if
you have arrays of objects, then we do assignments into those arrays in Java,
there's additional run time overhead.