In this video, we're going to wrap up our discussion of Java by taking a look at a
couple of additional topics and how they are integrated into the language design.
Consistent with Java's dynamic nature Java allows classes to be loaded at runtime.
But this means that you can actually add functionality to an executing Java program
so, while it's running, by loading a new class. And this creates potential issues
with type safety and security because now there is a distinction between compiled
time and load time. So, type checking of the source takes place at compile time and
this is the kind of type checking we discussed in earlier in earlier videos.
But the, the loader, when you actually go to load a class, you're loading bytecode,
you're not loading source and it's not being type checked again. And it could be,
that this bytecode didn't come, you know, from a trusted source. This bytecode might
not be the output of a compiler that did type checking, before it produced the
bytecode. So, the bytecode might not actually satisfy the type assumptions of
the Java implementation. So essentially, we have to check the bytecode again. And
a, and a procedure called bytecode verification takes place when the class is
loaded, alright. And, and byte code verification is really a type checking of
bytecode. That's, that's essentially what it does. The procedure is a little bit
different because we don't have you know, the code here is much lower level and so
the algorithms look a little bit different. But what they're really doing
is type checking the, thebytecode. So, now the loading policies are handled by
something called the class loader. And the class loader is a special class in Java
and it decides what classes can be loaded and actually early on in Java, a bunch of
security problems were discovered. Aware an attacker could get control of the class
loader install it's own class loader that would be much more permissive than the
Java standard class loader and subve rt the system. But those issues were fixed
quite awhile ago, alright. And another interesting thing about Java is that the
classes may also be unloaded. So, you don't, you can not, not only load classes,
you can also unload classes. And the last time I checked this was not particularly
well specified in the definition and so it's a little bit unclear exactly what it
meant when you unloaded the class and what happened to all the existing objects, for
example, of that class. Now, I'd like to spend a few minutes talking about
initialization in Java, which is quite complex, and this shouldn't be too much of
a surprise because if you remember initialization in COOL was also pretty
complex and Java is just a superset of COOL so it has all the initialization
issues that COOL has plus much more. And now the main source of complication is
concurrency but other language features also add to the complexity of
initialization in Java. And, in fact you could do worse. If you want to understand
a new object oriented language, then study how it does object initialization and
class initialization. Because essentially what happens in initialization is that all
the features of the language are going to be interacting and you have to explain
what all those interactions are and how they are sorted out in order to have a
well-defined initialization procedure, alright. So, now let's talk about class
initialization. We won't talk about object initialization, we'll just talk about
initializing classes. So, this is how the, the object that represents a class
actually gets initialized when that class is first brought into the program. And so,
the first thing to know is that a class is initialized when a symbol in a class is
first used, okay, not when the class is loaded, alright? So, if you reference any
symbol in the class at the first time that happens that will cause the class to be
initialized. And the reason for doing this is if you are going to have an error in
class initialization, th is will cause that error to happen in a predictable
place. So, if you have an error and you run the, you, you have an error in class
initialization if you run the program five times you know, that error will probably
happen in the same place every time. So, it'll be repeatable and predictable where
the error occurs. If instead we had, the error happened where you loaded the class
at the time that you loaded the class, well, the class might be loaded at lots of
different times. And, and, and so this, this, this error here the error in the
initialization of the class would become non-deterministic if we didn't if we
didn't delay the initialization until some deterministic point in the execution. So,
now I'll discuss the procedure for initializing class objects in Java. And
the first thing I should stress is that this idea of a class object is something
that Java has that COOL does not have, I mentioned this on the previous slide. But
just to be completely clear, what is a class object? A class object is just what
it sounds like, it is the object for a class. It represents a class. Okay, this
is not an instance of the class. This is an object which is the class, okay. So,
this is an object which is the class, it has all the information about the class
so, you know, it tells you what the type of the class is, what the fields of the
class are, and everything else. So, this is used for introspection or reflection.
And it's necessary in Java because of features like dynamic loading. So, if, you
know, if you want, if you dynamically load a class though you want to be able to use
that class, you have to have some way of querying what the, what kinds of methods
and things the class has and that is what the class object is for. So, there is one
object, there is one class object for each class in Java, alright. So, when you load
a class, the first thing you have do is to initialize the class object. And how is
that done? Well, we lock the class object for the class, alright. And if th at, if
that object is already locked by another thread, then we'll simply wait on the
lock, okay. So, we will wait until somebody tells us that it's okay to
proceed. Now once we obtain the lock on the class, we have to do a check to see if
the class is already being initialized, alright. So, and it could turn out that it
is our thread, it is the same thread is already initializing the class. And how
could that happen? Well, remember that a class can have fields of the same type.
So, I could have a class of class called X and then it could have a field of type X
in it. And the way classes are going to be initialize if we're going to have to
initialize the class itself and then, and we're going to do that by recursively
initializing the classes for all the fields or at least making sure of the
classes for all the fields are initialize. And if we have a recursive structure here
with the same class mention in a field as in a name, as the name of the enclosing
class, then we will get the situation where the thread initializing the class
may attempt to initialize the same class again. So, if we discover that we're
already initializing this class, we simply release the lock and we turn. Now, another
possibility is that the class is already initialized. So, if when we finally get
the lock we discover that some other thread got in there and initialized the
class before we have a chance to., well, then there's nothing to do and we just
return normally, alright? Now, if neither one of these things is true, okay, if we
get the lock and we discover that the class is not already initialized and that
we're not already in the process of initializing the class, then we will mark
the class to, to note the initialization is in progress by this thread, okay. So,
we'll indicate, you know, this class is being initialized and that we are
initializing it and then we'll unlock the class. Alright, the next thing that
happens is we'll have to initialize the superclass and that will m ean initial,
and then we'll initialize all the fields in textual order. But because Java has
what are called static and final fields we will initialize those first, okay. So,
static final fields will get initialized before any other fields in textual order.
And, of course, we have to give every field of default value before
initialization just as in COOL. So, this step, step five is very similar to what
goes on in COOL. Now if there's an error during the initialization, so some part of
the initialization throws an exception, then we're going to mark the class as
erroneous, okay, we're going to mark this class as no good and can't be used and,
and that's the best we can do. So, if there's an exception during
initialization, we just have to give up on that class. And so it gets a special mark
on it saying that it's erroneous. And, if there are no errors if we succeed in
initializing the class and with and without any errors, then we're going to
lock the class again. We will label the class as initialized, alright? And then
we'll notify the threads that are waiting on the class object. So. Anybody who was
locked waiting on the class object will now be alerted that the object is, is
ready and then we'll unlock the class. Okay, and so that's a rough outline of how
class initialization in Java works. I skipped over a few things and
oversimplified it a bit. So, this isn't the complete description but these are the
main points and they, and they illustrate how the various features of the language
have to interact. So, you have to worry about concurrency, you have to worry about
exceptions, you have to worry about static and final fields, you have to worry about
inheritance. I mean, all these things have to be dealt with together in the design of
a single algorithm to do class initialization. Stepping back for a moment
this discussion of class initialization in Java illustrates a general point about
designing complex systems. So, in any system with a certain number of featu res
and every system is going to have some number of features, let's call it N,
because you want to provide some functionality, obviously the thing the
system's suppose to d so its going to have features to do those things. But as you
add features, you get lots of interactions, potential interactions
between the features and if we think about, even just the pairwise
interactions. If I have N features, then I'll have, I don't know, about N^2
pairwise feature interactions. And the point there, of course, is that as I add
features the number of possible interactions grows super linearly in the
number of features, I mean, it grows much more quickly than the number of features.
And so, adding the next feature, you're going to have to consider all of the
previous features that you already have in the system and how this new feature
affects them, and this is why it becomes very difficult to extend or build systems
that have a lot of features, alright. And this is just the pairwise features. These
are just, this is just considering pairwise interactions between one feature
and another. If I have to start worrying about subsets of features, I'm thinking
about how all possible subsets of features might interact with each other, well then,
this step, this number of, of potential interactions will grow not just it will
grow, in fact, exponentially. So, it'd be, you know, way more than quadratic. And the
bottom line here is that big, feature-full systems are hard to understand. You know,
this is you know, a general lesson in Computer Science and any kind of
discipline that wants to design complex systems and, and this lesson applies to
programming languages. It applies to every other kind of software system that you
might want to build. But, and somehow it has a particular force in programming
languages because these interactions between the features, you know, these are
the features of the programming language, they happen at a very fine grain. And
these things can be, really can b e composed arbitrarily and so you really do
have to work out in language design, you know, what all the interactions are in
order to have a language that people, that programmers can actually understand and
use productively. Alright? And that really I think is the big, big idea that, one of
the big ideas that we've talked about throughout the course. And, and I hope one
of the things that you would take away from this lecture at least in particular.
So, to summarize and to conclude our discussion of Java, I think Java is a, is
a well-done language. By production standards, it is extremely well-done. So,
it's one of the best designed and best specified languages that's in, in use
today. It brought several important ideas into the main stream. So, when it was new
it brought ideas that had been around for a long time but had not found their way
into a production language that was very, very widely used and in particular, Java
was the first language to be very widely used in, in commercial settings. They had
strong sets of typing there that had real guarantees they were, you know, provided
by the type-system and also there was a manage language and had a garbage
collected memory. But that doesn't mean it's perfect. And it, and Java also
includes some features that, at the time that it was designed, that we didn't fully
understand and I would say, you know, that this are probably the rough areas where
there's still some roughness in the, in, in the Java design. So, things like the
way the memory semantics work in the presence of concurrency, you know,
probably still has most people would agree I think, you now, has some problems and
some, some little gray areas that as a program, you probably want to stay out of.
And the other thing is that Java has a lot of features. And as I said before when you
have a lot of features, you're going to have even more feature interactions and
that leads to complexity that becomes difficult to manage.