In this video, we're going to talk about Coercions which is a feature of type
systems that appears in many languages and we will be looking specifically how
coercions are done in Java. Java allows primitive types to be coerced in certain
context. And, coerced means converted from one type to another. So here's an example,
lets take the expression one + 2.0 and the difficulty with this expression is that
the, the one here is, is an integer and the 2.0 is a floating point number. And
there is no way to add an int to a float directly. We either have to convert the
integer to a float and then do the add as floating point numbers or convert the
floating point number to an integer and then do the addition as integer addition.
So they have to be converted to a common representation, before we can actually do
the operation. And the normal thing to do, and the thing that Java does, is to
convert the integer to the floating point number 1.0. Now, a coercion the right way
I think, to think of coercions is they're really just primitive functions that the
compiler inserts for you. So it's like, you left out a function call and the
compiler notices that and puts it in. So, in this particular example, what would be
the function call? Well, there, we can think of there being a primitive function
that converts integers to floating point numbers in the obvious way. And so really
this expression here gets converted to the expression into float applied to the
number one plus 2.0. All right. So coercions are probably best thought of as
a convenience for you, the programmer to let you avoid having to write some
function calls. And, so where it is obvious that a type conversion is going on
the compiler can insert the function that performs that type conversion for you. And
most languages really have extensive coercions so the conversions are very,
very common particularly between numeric types and so this is not just Java. This
is really many different programming languages of all styles that have lots of
differe nt kinds of coercions. Now, Java in particular distinguishes two kinds of
coercions and casts. You have widening coercions and these will always succeed.
Alright, so that means that Java will always put them in and there will never be
any complaining from the compiler or the runtime system about them and we already
saw one of those, so the conversion from int to float is an example of a widening
cast. Now, narrowing casts may fail if the data can't be converted to the desired
type. So in particular, float to int well, this will work fine. Something like 2.0
can be converted in obvious way to two but if you're converting something that
doesn't have an integer representation something say like 2.5 you know, there's a
question of what we should do here. Okay, and for such narrowing casts, where there
isn't a, a clear mapping, whether we should go or, you know or whether we
should try here or round up, or whatever then Java will actually complain and not
let you do it. Okay perhaps for better example of the kind of narrowing cast
that's that Java will complain about is something like a down cast. So if I have
two classes A and B. And B is a subtype of A and then I have something of type A.
Well, I can cast it to B. I can say, let's say I have X which is a type A and then I
can have an expression where I try to convert x to a B object. So here I have a
cast, I've indicated that I want to treat this expression x as a B object and this
will type check, okay. So the, the compiler will let this through since B is
subtype of A. But at run time, it's actually going to check whether x is
actually a B object and if it's not you're going to get an exception. So this can
fail at run time if the object thatt x actually holds at the point of the cast is
not a B object. So the rule in Java is that narrowing cast must be explicit. You
have to put the function in yourself. You have to put in the typecase in the code so
that it's obvious that you really want to do it, but widening casts in coercions can
be implicit, so it's alright. If you're widening, if you're either promoting to a
super type or you are converting between initial type where it's clear that the,
one type embeds in the other then those can be filled in for you by the compiler.
And here's a little Java trivia question. So it turns out that there is one type in
Java for which there are no coercions or casts defined. Okay so there are no
implicit conversions or even explicit conversions from that type to any other
type. And the answer to the question, which is the only one, is bool. Okay so
only the type boolean has no conercions or casts to another type. Now personally, I'm
not a big fan of coercions. I think that it's clearly a convenience for
programmers, it's clearly something that is widely accepted as being necessary in
programming languages because casts, implicit casts and conversions are so
ubiquitous but I do think that it tends to lead to programs that have behavior that's
different from what the programmer probably expected. And, here's a good
example from the language PL/1, which recalls stood for Programming Language one
designed by IBM in the 1960s. And had many, many features in it so we've talked
about PL/1 a few times in this class. And one thing that PL/1 had was very extensive
cast and coercions and this could lead us to some surprising behaviors. So here's an
example we have a, A, B, and C are strings of three characters so it's important to
know here that the length three is part of the type. So B is string '123' C is '456'
and then A is going to be B + c and the question is what is A? And, and you
probably won't guess, so let me show you what I think is the right answer. So first
of all the question is what happens with this + operation here? Well, so that is
going to be interpreted as an integer + so B and C are both going to be cast to
integers and the, and this will be done as a integer arithmetic. So B will get
converted to the number 123. C will get conver ted to the number 456, okay? And
then we'll add them and we'll get out the number 579. Okay, so the result of this
expression is 579 but A is also a string of three characters so this has to be cast
back to a string. Now, it turns out that this cast happens in two steps. First
this, this number here is cast to a string of the default length, okay. And the
default length happens to be six so this is cast to a string looks like this.
There's three blanks followed by 579. And then that string of six characters is
converted to a string of three characters. And we just take the first three
characters and so we get out that, and so the answer is that this program stores a
string of three blanks in A. Which is probably not what was expected.